<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

<channel>
<title>Susam Pal</title>
<link>https://susam.net/</link>
<atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="https://susam.net/feed.xml"/>
<description>Susam's Feed</description>

<item>
<title>Circular Recursive Negating Acronyms</title>
<link>https://susam.net/circular-recursive-negating-acronynms.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">crnax</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  One of my favourite acronyms from the world of computing and
  technology is XINU.  It stands for 'XINU Is Not Unix'.  The
  delightful thing about this acronym is that XINU is also UNIX
  spelled backwards.
</p>
<p>
  For a given word <em>W</em>, a recursive acronym that both
  negates <em>W</em> and reverses it is possible when <em>W</em> has
  the form <em>W</em> = '?NI?' where each '?' denotes a distinct
  letter.  Some fictitious examples make this clearer:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>LINA Is Not ANIL.</li>
  <li>TINK Is Not KNIT.</li>
</ul>
<p>
  Words of the form '?N?' also work if we are happy to contract the
  word 'is' in the acronym.  In fact, in this case we can even obtain
  circular recursive acronyms:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>ANI's Not INA.  INA's Not ANI.</li>
  <li>ONE's Not ENO.  ENO's Not ONE.</li>
</ul>
<p>
  In each pair, the two acronyms negate each other, making them
  circular while also being reverses of one another.  Such acronyms
  could serve as amusing names for expressing friendly banter between
  rival projects.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/circular-recursive-negating-acronynms.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Ideas</title>
<link>https://susam.net/ideas.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">ideas</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>Ideas</h1>
<p>
  Hello!  This is my <a href="https://aboutideasnow.com/about">ideas
  page</a> where I keep a brief record of some ideas I might want to
  explore in the near future.  For ideas I have already begun
  exploring, please see my <a href="now.html">now page</a> or
  my <a href="pages.html">web log</a> instead.
</p>
<p>
  As of 03 Jan 2026, I have the following ideas in mind that I might
  want to explore in future:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Explore the problem of checking whether two self-complementary
    graphs are isomorphic.
  </li>
  <li>
    Learn why \( s \)-arc transitive graph must have \( s \le 7.  \)
  </li>
</ul>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/ideas.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Now</title>
<link>https://susam.net/now.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nowpg</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>Now</h1>
<p>
  Hello!  This is my <a href="https://nownownow.com/about">now
  page</a> where I keep a brief record of what I am up to these days.
</p>
<p>
  As of 03 Jan 2026, I am:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Studying the book <em>Algebraic Graph Theory</em> by Godsil and
    Royle.
  </li>
  <li>
    Learning about the Coxeter graph and Tutte's 8-cage.
  </li>
  <li>
    Learning about distance-transitive graphs, in general.
  </li>
  <li>
    Maintaining this website.
  </li>
  <li>
    Occasionally posting comments to Hacker News
    (<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/threads?id=susam">see here</a>).
  </li>
</ul>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/now.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>My Coding Adventures in 2025</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code-2025.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">cdtwf</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  In this post, I return with a retrospective on my coding adventures,
  where I summarise my hobby projects and recreational programming
  activities from the current year.  I did the last such retrospective
  in <a href="code-2023.html">2023</a>.  So I think this is a good
  time to do another retrospective.
</p>
<p>
  At the outset, I should mention that I have done less hobby
  computing this year than in the past few, largely because I spent a
  substantial portion of my leisure time studying Galois theory and
  algebraic graph theory.  In case you are wondering where I am
  learning these subjects from, the books are <em>Galois Theory</em>,
  5th ed. by Ian Stewart and <em>Algebraic Graph Theory</em> by Godsil
  and Royle.  Both are absolutely fascinating subjects and the two
  books I mentioned are quite good as well.  I highly recommend them.
</p>
<p>
  Now back to the coding adventures.  Here they go:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>
      <a href="https://github.com/susam/mathb">MathB</a>: The year
      began not with the release of a new project but with the
      opposite: discontinuing a project I had maintained for 13 years.
      MathB.in, a mathematics pastebin service, was discontinued early
      this year.  This is a project I developed in 2012 for myself and
      my friends.  Although a rather simple project, it was close to
      my heart, as I have many fond memories of exchanging
      mathematical puzzles and solutions with my friends using this
      service.  Over time, the project grew quite popular on IRC
      networks, as well as in some schools and universities, where IRC
      users, learners and students used the service to share problems
      and solutions with one another, much as my friends and I had
      done in its early days.
    </p>
    <p>
      I shut it down this year because I wanted to move on from the
      project.  Before the shutdown, a kind member of the
      <a href="https://wiki.archiveteam.org/">Archive Team</a> worked
      with me to
      <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/*/https://mathb.in/">archive</a>
      all posts from the now-defunct website.  Although shutting down
      this service was a bittersweet event for me, I feel relieved
      that I no longer have to run a live service in my spare time.
      While this was a good hobby ten years ago, it no longer is.  See
      my blog post
      <a href="mathbin-is-shutting-down.html">MathB.in Is Shutting
      Down</a> for more details on the reasons behind this decision.
      The source code of this project remains open source and
      available at
      <a href="https://github.com/susam/mathb">github.com/susam/mathb</a>.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      <a href="https://github.com/susam/quickqwerty">QuickQWERTY</a>:
      This is a touch-typing tutor that runs in a web browser.  I
      originally developed it in 2008 for myself and my friends.
      While I learnt touch typing on an actual typewriter as a child,
      those lessons did not stick with me.  Much later, while I was at
      university, I came across a Java applet-based touch-typing tutor
      that finally helped me learn touch typing properly.  I disliked
      installing Java plugins in the web browser, which is why I later
      developed this project in plain HTML and JavaScript.  This year,
      I carried out a major refactoring to collapse the entire project
      into a single standalone HTML file with no external
      dependencies.  The source code has been greatly simplified as
      well.
    </p>
    <p>
      When I was younger and more naive, inspired by the complexity
      and multiple layers of abstraction I saw in popular open source
      and professional projects, I tended to introduce similar
      abstractions and complexity into my personal projects.  Over
      time, however, I began to appreciate simplicity.  The new code
      for this project is smaller and simpler.  I am quite happy with
      the end result.  You can take a look at the code here:
      <a href="https://github.com/susam/quickqwerty/blob/main/quickqwerty.html">quickqwerty.html</a>.
      If you want to use the typing tutor, go here:
      <a href="quickqwerty.html">QuickQWERTY</a>.  Unfortunately, it
      does not support keyboard layouts other than QWERTY.  When I
      originally developed this project, my view of the computing
      world was rather limited.  I was not even aware that other
      keyboard layouts existed.  You are, however, very welcome to
      fork the project and adapt the lessons for other layouts.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      <a href="https://github.com/susam/cfrs">CFRS[]</a>: This project
      was my first contribution to the quirky world of esolangs.
      CFRS[] is an extremely minimal drawing language consisting of
      only six simple commands: <code>C</code>, <code>F</code>,
      <code>R</code>, <code>S</code>, <code>[</code> and
      <code>]</code>.  I developed it in 2023 and have since been
      maintaining it with occasional bug fixes.  This year, I
      <a href="https://github.com/susam/cfrs/commit/9bae21f">fixed an
      annoying bug</a> that caused the drawing canvas to overflow on
      some mobile web browsers.  A new demo also arrived from the
      community this year and has now been added to the community demo
      page.  See
      <a href="https://susam.github.io/cfrs/demo.html#glimmering-galaxy">Glimmering
      Galaxy</a> for the new demo.  If you want to play with CFRS[]
      now, visit <a href="cfrs.html">CFRS[]</a>.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      <a href="https://github.com/susam/fxyt">FXYT</a>: This is
      another esolang project of mine.  This too is a minimal drawing
      language, though not as minimal as CFRS[].  Instead, it is a
      stack-based, postfix canvas colouring language with only 36
      simple commands.  The canvas overflow bug described in the
      previous entry affected this project as well.  That has now been
      fixed.  Further, by popular demand, the maximum allowed code
      length has been increased from 256 bytes to 1024 bytes.  This
      means there is now more room for writing more complex FXYT
      programs.  Additionally, the maximum code length for
      distributable demo links has been increased from 64 bytes to 256
      bytes.  This allows several more impressive demos to have their
      own distributable links.  Visit <a href="fxyt.html">FXYT</a> to
      try it out now.  See also the
      <a href="https://susam.github.io/fxyt/demo.html">Community Demos</a> to
      view some fascinating artwork created by the community.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      <a href="https://github.com/susam/nq">Nerd Quiz</a>: This is a
      new project I created a couple of months ago.  It is a simple
      HTML tool that lets you test your nerdiness through short
      quizzes.  Each question is drawn from my everyday moments of
      reading, writing, thinking, learning and exploring.  The project
      is meant to serve as a repository of interesting facts I come
      across in daily life, captured in the form of quiz questions.
      Go here to try it out: <a href="nq.html">Nerd Quiz</a>.  I hope
      you will enjoy these little bits of knowledge as much as I
      enjoyed discovering them.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      <a href="primegrid.html">Prime Number Grid Explorer</a>: This is
      a simple prime number grid visualiser I wrote for fun.  It plots
      the prime numbers in a grid where you can set the number of rows
      and the number of columns.  It uses the Miller-Rabin primality
      test with bases drawn from
      <a href="https://oeis.org/A014233">oeis.org/A014233</a> to
      determine whether a number is prime.  This allows it to
      accurately test whether a number is prime up to
      3317044064679887385961980.  For example,
      <a href="primegrid.html#3317044064679887385961781-20-10">this
      grid</a> shows the upper limit of the numbers this tool can
      check.  The three circles displayed there represent the prime
      numbers 3317044064679887385961783, 3317044064679887385961801 and
      3317044064679887385961813.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      <a href="https://github.com/susam/mvs">Mark V. Shaney
      Junior</a>: Finally, I have my own Markov gibberish generator.
      Always wanted to have one.  The project is inspired by the
      legendary Usenet bot named Mark V. Shaney that used to post
      messages to various newsgroups in the 1980s.  My Markov chain
      program is written in about 30 lines of Python.  I ran it on my
      24 years of blog posts consisting of over 200 posts and about
      200,000 words and it generated some pretty interesting
      gibberish.  See my blog post
      <a href="fed-24-years-of-posts-to-markov-model.html">Fed 24
      Years of My Posts to Markov Model</a> to see the examples.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      <a href="elliptical-python-programming.html">Elliptical Python
      Programming</a>: If the previous item was not silly enough, this
      one surely is.  Earlier this year, I wrote a blog post
      describing the fine art of Python programming using copious
      amounts of ellipses.  I will not discuss it further here to
      avoid spoilers.  I'll just say that any day I'm able to do
      something pointless, whimsical and fun with computers is a good
      day for me.  And it was a good day when I wrote this post.
      Please visit the link above to read the post.  I hope you find
      it fun.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      <a href="fizz-buzz-with-cosines.html">Fizz Buzz with
      Cosines</a>: Another silly post in which I explain how to
      compute the discrete Fourier transform of the Fizz Buzz sequence
      and derive a closed-form expression that can be used to print
      the sequence.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      <a href="fizz-buzz-in-css.html">Fizz Buzz in CSS</a>: Yet
      another Fizz Buzz implementation, this time using just four
      lines of CSS.
    </p>
  </li>
</ul>
<p>
  That wraps up my coding adventures for this year.  There were fewer
  hobby projects than usual but I enjoyed spending more time learning
  new things and revisiting old ones.  One long-running project came
  to an end, another was cleaned up and a few small new ideas appeared
  along the way.  Looking forward to what the next year brings.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code-2025.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/retrospective.html">#retrospective</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nerd Quiz #3</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/nq/3.0.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqthr</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Nerd Quiz #3 is the third release of Nerd Quiz, a single-page HTML
  application that invites you to test your nerd level through a short
  quiz.  Each question is inspired by everyday moments of reading,
  writing, thinking, learning and exploring.
</p>
<p>
  This release introduces five new questions drawn from a range of
  topics, including computing history, graph theory and Unix.
  Visit <a href="../../../nq.html#3">Nerd Quiz</a> to try the quiz.
</p>
<p>
  A community discussion page is available at
  <a href="../../../comments/nq.html">Discuss Nerd Quiz</a>.  You are
  very welcome to share your score or discuss the questions there.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/nq/3.0.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/game.html">#game</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mark V. Shaney Junior 0.2.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/mvs/0.2.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">mvszt</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Mark V. Shaney Junior 0.2.0 is the second release of this little
  Markov gibberish generator.  This release brings two small changes.
  First, it now reads the training data from standard input instead of
  a hardcoded file.  Second, the program filename has been changed
  from <code>mvs.py</code> to <code>mvs</code> to reflect that it is
  an executable file and can be run as <code>./mvs</code> on most Unix
  and Linux systems.
</p>
<p>
  The source and a detailed documentation for this project are
  available at <a href="https://github.com/susam/mvs">github.com/susam/mvs</a>.
</p>
<p>
  See also
  <a href="https://susam.net/fed-24-years-of-posts-to-markov-model.html">this
  related blog post</a> and a
  <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46257607">discussion
  on Hacker News</a> about it.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/mvs/0.2.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/python.html">#python</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fed 24 Years of My Blog Posts to a Markov Model</title>
<link>https://susam.net/fed-24-years-of-posts-to-markov-model.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">mgtfy</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Yesterday I shared a little program called <em>Mark V. Shaney
  Junior</em> at
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mvs">github.com/susam/mvs</a>.  It
  is a minimal implementation of a Markov text generator inspired by
  the legendary Mark V. Shaney program from the 1980s.  Mark V. Shaney
  was a synthetic Usenet user that posted messages to various
  newsgroups using text generated by a Markov model.  See the
  Wikipedia article
  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_V._Shaney">Mark
  V. Shaney</a> for more details about it.  In this post, I will
  discuss my implementation of the model, explain how it works and
  share some of the results produced by it.
</p>
<h2 id="contents">Contents<a href="#contents"></a></h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#recreational-programming">Recreational Programming</a></li>
  <li><a href="#gibberish">Gibberish</a></li>
  <li><a href="#markov-property">The Markov Property</a></li>
  <li><a href="#some-more-gibberish">Some More Gibberish</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="recreational-programming">Recreational Programming<a href="#recreational-programming"></a></h2>
<p>
  The program I shared yesterday has only about
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mvs/blob/main/mvs">30 lines of
  Python</a> and favours simplicity over efficiency.  Even if you have
  never worked with Markov models before, as long as you know some
  Python programming, I am quite confident that it will take you less
  than 20 minutes to understand the whole program and make complete
  sense of it.  I also offer an explanation
  <a href="#the-markov-property">further below</a> in this post.
</p>
<p>
  As a hobby, I often engage in exploratory programming where I write
  computer programs not to solve a specific problem but simply to
  explore a particular idea or topic for the sole purpose of
  recreation.  I must have written small programs to explore Markov
  chains for various kinds of state spaces over a dozen times by now.
  Every time, I just pick my last experimental code and edit it to
  encode the new state space I am exploring.  That's usually my
  general approach to such one-off programs.  I have hundreds of tiny
  little experimental programs lying on my disk at any given time.
</p>
<p>
  Once in a while, I get the itch to take one of those exploratory
  programs, give it some finishing touches, wrap it up in a nice Git
  repo along with a <code>README.md</code>, <code>CHANGES.md</code>
  and the whole shebang and share it on
  <a href="https://github.com/susam">github.com/susam</a> and
  <a href="https://codeberg.org/susam">codeberg.org/susam</a>.  The
  Mark V. Shaney Junior program that I shared yesterday happened to be
  one such exercise.
</p>
<h2 id="gibberish">Gibberish<a href="#gibberish"></a></h2>
<p>
  If you scroll down the
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mvs#readme">README</a> of this
  project, you'll find some nice examples of the gibberish produced by
  this program.  The first few examples there are the result of
  training the model on <em>A Christmas Carol</em> by Charles Dickens,
  one of my favourite authors.  It is often said that Dickens never
  used fewer words when more would suffice.  So I thought there
  couldn't be a better piece of text when it comes to testing out my
  tiny Markov model.  I'll not reproduce the generated text examples
  here for the sake of brevity.  If you are interested to take a look,
  just head over to the
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mvs#gibberish">Gibberish</a>
  section of the README.
</p>
<p>
  Soon after sharing the project, I wondered what kind of gibberish it
  would produce if I fed all 24 years of my blog
  <a href="pages.html">posts and pages</a> into the program.
  Well, here's one of the results:
</p>
<pre>
<samp>$ <kbd>./mvs &lt; susam.txt</kbd>
while a query replace operation is approved by the user. The above
variable defines the build job. It can be incredibly useful while
working on assembly language and machine code. In fact, all internal
resources like the result to refine the search prompt changes from
bck-i-search: to fwd-i-search:. Now type C-SPC (i.e. ctrl+space) to
set a mark causes Emacs to use 32-bit registers like EBP, ESP,
etc. Thus the behaviour is undefined. Such code may behave differently
when compiled with the readily available GNU tools like the shape
of 8. Flipping "P" horizontally makes it a proper quine: cat $0</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  This is the text that comes out after the program consumes over 200
  posts consisting of about 200,000 words.  My blog also has
  a <a href="comments/">comments section</a> with over 500
  comments consisting of about 40,000 words.  All comments were
  excluded while training the model.  Here is another output example:
</p>
<pre>
<samp>$ <kbd>./mvs &lt; susam.txt</kbd>
enjoy asking "what happens if" and then type M-x zap-up-to-char RET
b. The buffer for this specific video, the actual fare for 8.3 km and
11 are all written from scratch. No prior knowledge is expected to
slow down in future. For now, I will add a statement like x =
0.999..., the inner corner square as discussed in the code segment
into the REPL window. Unlike Slimv, Vlime can work with and debug
executable files, it can be more convenient. M-x: Execute Extended
Command The key sequence M-q invokes the command cat and type TAB to
indent the current</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  Here is a particularly incoherent but amusing one:
</p>
<pre>
<samp>$ <kbd>./mvs &lt; susam.txt</kbd>
Then open a new Lisp source file and the exact answer could harm
students' self-esteem. Scientists have arbitrarily assumed that an
integral domain. However, the string and comment text. To demonstrate
how a build job can trigger itself, pass input to standard output or
standard error), Eshell automatically runs the following command in
Vim and Emacs will copy the message length limit of 512 characters,
etc. For example, while learning to play the game between normal mode
to move the point is on an old dictionary lying around our house and
that is moving to the small and supportive community</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  No, I have never said anywhere that opening a Lisp source file could
  harm anyone's self-esteem.  The text generator has picked up the
  'Lisp source file' phrase from my
  <a href="lisp-in-vim.html">Lisp in Vim</a> post and the
  'self-esteem' bit from the <a href="from-perl-to-pi.html">From Perl
  to Pi</a> post.
</p>
<h2 id="markov-property">The Markov Property<a href="#markov-property"></a></h2>
<p>
  By default, this program looks at trigrams (all sequences of three
  adjacent words) and creates a map where the first two words of the
  trigram are inserted as the key and the third word is appended to
  its list value.  This map is the model.  In this way, the model
  captures each pair of adjacent words along with the words that
  immediately follow each pair.  The text generator first chooses a
  key (a pair of words) at random and selects a word that follows.  If
  there are multiple followers, it picks one uniformly at random.  It
  then repeats this process with the most recent pair of words,
  consisting of one word from the previous pair and the word that was
  just picked.  It continues to do this until it can no longer find a
  follower or a fixed word limit (100 by default) is reached.  That is
  pretty much the whole algorithm.  There isn't much more to it.  It
  is as simple as it gets.  For that reason, I often describe a simple
  Markov model like this as the 'hello, world' for language models.
</p>
<p>
  If the same trigram occurs multiple times in the training data, the
  model records the follower word (the third word) multiple times in
  the list associated with the key (the first two words).  This
  representation can be optimised, of course, by keeping frequencies
  of the follower words rather than duplicating them in the list, but
  that is left as an exercise to the reader.  In any case, when the
  text generator chooses a follower for a given pair of words, a
  follower that occurs more frequently after that pair has a higher
  probability of being chosen.  In effect, the next word is sampled
  based only on the previous two words and not on the full history of
  the generated text.  This memoryless dependence on the current state
  is what makes the generator Markov.  Formally, for a discrete-time
  stochastic process, the Markov property can be expressed as

  \[
    P(X_{n+1} \mid X_n, X_{n-1}, \ldots, X_1) = P(X_{n+1} \mid X_n).
  \]

  where \( X_n \) represents the \( n \)th state.  In our case, each
  state \( X_n \) is a pair of words \( (w_{n-1}, w_{n}) \) but the
  state space could just as well consist of other objects, such as a
  pair of characters, pixel values or musical notes.  The sequence of
  states \( (X_1, X_2, \dots) \) visited by the program forms a Markov
  chain.  The left-hand side of the equation denotes the conditional
  distribution of the next state \( X_{n+1} \) given the entire
  history of states \( X_1, X_2, \dots, X_n, \) while the right-hand
  side conditions only on the current state \( X_n.  \)  When both are
  equal, it means that the probability of the next state depends only
  on the current state and not on the earlier states.  This is the
  Markov property.  It applies to the text generation process only,
  not the training data.  The training data is used only to estimate
  the transition probabilities of the model.
</p>
<h2 id="some-more-gibberish">Some More Gibberish<a href="#some-more-gibberish"></a></h2>
<p>
  In 2025, given the overwhelming popularity of large language models
  (LLMs), Markov models like this look unimpressive.  Unlike LLMs, a
  simple Markov model cannot capture global structure or long-range
  dependencies within the text.  It relies entirely on local word
  transition statistics.  Also, these days, one hardly needs a Markov
  model to generate gibberish; social media provides an ample supply.
  Nevertheless, I think the simplicity of its design and
  implementation serves as a good entry point into language models.
</p>
<p>
  In my implementation, the number of words in the key of the map can
  be set via command line arguments.  By default, it is 2 as described
  above.  This value is also known as the order of the model.  So by
  default the order is 2.  If we increase it to, say, 3 or 4, the
  generated text becomes a little more coherent.  Here is one such
  example:
</p>
<pre>
<samp>$ <kbd>./mvs 4 &lt; susam.txt</kbd>
It is also possible to search for channels by channel names. For
example, on Libera Chat, to search for all channels with 'python' in
its name, enter the IRC command: /msg alis list python. Although I
have used Libera Chat in the examples above, there are plenty of
infinite fields, so they must all be integral domains too. Consider
the field of rational numbers Q. Another quick way to arrive at this
fact is to observe that when one knight is placed on a type D square,
only two positions for the second knight such that the two knights
attack</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  Except for a couple of abrupt and meaningless transitions, the text
  is mostly coherent.  We need to be careful about not increasing the
  order too much.  In fact, if we increase the order of the model to
  5, the generated text becomes very dry and factual because it begins
  to quote large portions of the blog posts verbatim.  Not much fun
  can be had with that.
</p>
<p>
  Before I end this post, let me present one final example where I ask
  it to generate text from an initial prompt:
</p>
<pre>
<samp>$ <kbd>./mvs 2 100 'Finally we' &lt; susam.txt</kbd>
Finally we divide this number by a feed aggregrator for Emacs-related
blogs. The following complete key sequences describe the effects of
previous evaluations shall have taken a simple and small to contain
bad content. This provides an interactive byte-compiled Lisp function
in MATLAB and GNU bash 5.1.4 on Debian is easily reproducible in
Windows XP. Older versions might be able to run that server for me it
played a significant burden on me as soon as possible. C-u F: Visit
the marked files or directories in the sense that it was already
initiated and we were to complete the proof.</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  Apparently, this is how I would sound if I ever took up speaking
  gibberish!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/fed-24-years-of-posts-to-markov-model.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/python.html">#python</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Mark V. Shaney Junior 0.1.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/mvs/0.1.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">mvszo</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Mark V. Shaney Junior is a minimal implementation of a Markov
  gibberish generator inspired by the legendary Mark V. Shaney program
  from the 1980s.  Mark V. Shaney was a synthetic Usenet user in the
  1980s that posted messages to newsgroups using text generated by a
  Markov chain program.  See the Wikipedia
  article <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_V._Shaney">Mark
  V. Shaney</a> for more details.
</p>
<p>
  This release introduces the program
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mvs/blob/main/mvs.py">mvs.py</a>
  that implements a similar Markov text generator.  It reads a text
  corpus of text from standard input, build an internal Markov model
  and then generate text using the model.
</p>
<p>
  Please visit
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mvs">github.com/susam/mvs</a>
  for the source code and some output examples.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/mvs/0.1.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/python.html">#python</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fizz Buzz in CSS</title>
<link>https://susam.net/fizz-buzz-in-css.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">fzcps</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  How many CSS selectors and declarations do we need to produce the
  Fizz Buzz sequence?  Of course we could do this with no CSS at all
  simply by placing the entire sequence as text in the HTML body.  So
  to make the problem precise as well as to keep it interesting, we
  require that all text that appears in the Fizz Buzz sequence comes
  directly from the CSS.  Placing any part of the output numbers or
  words outside the stylesheet is not allowed.  JavaScript is not
  allowed either.  With these constraints, I think we need at least
  four CSS selectors along with four declarations to solve this
  puzzle, as shown below:
</p>
<pre>
<code>li { counter-increment: n }
li:not(:nth-child(5n))::before { content: counter(n) }
li:nth-child(3n)::before { content: "Fizz" }
li:nth-child(5n)::after { content: "Buzz" }</code>
</pre>
<p>
  Here is a complete working example:
  <a href="css-fizz-buzz.html">css-fizz-buzz.html</a>.
</p>
<p>
  The above solution contains four CSS rules with one selector and one
  declaration in each rule.  For example,
  <code>li { counter-increment: n }</code> is one rule consisting of
  the selector <code>li</code> and the declaration
  <code>counter-increment: n</code>.
</p>
<p>
  Seasoned code golfers looking for a challenge can probably shrink
  this solution further.  A common trick to solve this problem is to
  use an ordered list (<code>&lt;ol&gt;</code>) which provides the
  integers in the form of list markers automatically, thereby
  eliminating the need to maintain a counter in the stylesheet.
  However, this violates the requirement set out in the introduction.
  We want every integer to be produced directly by the stylesheet.
  Treating the integers in the list markers as part of the output
  sequence breaks this rule.  Not to mention the output looks untidy
  because of the unnecessary dot after each marker and also because
  the numbers and words appear misaligned.  See an example of that
  trick here:
  <a href="code/web/css-fizz-buzz-ol.html">css-fizz-buzz-ol.html</a>.
  Correcting the misaligned output calls for extra code that cancels
  out the number of declarations saved.  In any case, the requirement
  that all integers of the output must come directly from the
  stylesheet prevents untidy solutions like this and also forces us to
  rely on the capabilities of CSS to solve this puzzle.
</p>
<p>
  The intention here was to obtain the smallest possible code in terms
  of the number of CSS declarations.  This example is not crafted to
  minimise bytes, but for code golfers who enjoy reducing byte count,
  here is the number of bytes this solution consumes after removing
  all whitespace:
</p>
<pre><code>$ curl -sS https://susam.net/css-fizz-buzz.html | sed -n '/counter/,/after/p' | tr -d '[:space:]' | wc -c
152</code></pre>
<p>
  Further reduction in byte count can be achieved by using the
  <code>&lt;p&gt;</code> element instead of <code>&lt;li&gt;</code>,
  nesting CSS selectors, etc.  I'll leave that as an exercise for the
  reader.  Returning to the focus of this post as well as to summarise
  it, the solution here uses four CSS rules consisting of four
  selectors and four declarations to render the Fizz Buzz sequence.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/fizz-buzz-in-css.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/absurd.html">#absurd</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/css.html">#css</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/puzzle.html">#puzzle</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>CSS Fizz Buzz with Ordered List</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/web/css-fizz-buzz-ol.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">fzolc</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A version of my CSS Fizz Buzz that uses ordered list
  (<code>&lt;ol&gt;</code>) to reduce code.  However, I don't quite
  like how misaligned the numbers and the words look.  Correcting that
  would call for extra code that would cancel out the bytes saved.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/web/css-fizz-buzz-ol.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Emacs Info Expressions</title>
<link>https://susam.net/emacs-info-expression.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">eminf</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  On <code>#emacs</code> IRC or Matrix channels, we often share
  references to the built-in Emacs documentation as Elisp expressions
  that look like this:
</p>
<pre><code>(info "(emacs) Basic Undo")</code></pre>
<p>
  Here is another example:
</p>
<pre><code>(info "(emacs) Word Search")</code></pre>
<p>
  This is a common practice in the Emacs community even though all of
  the Emacs manual is available on the World Wide Web too.  For
  example, the section referred to in the above expression eis
  available
  here: <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/manual/html_node/emacs/Word-Search.html">GNU
  Emacs Manual: Word Search</a>.  The reason for sharing Elisp
  expressions like this is likely partly tradition and partly
  convenience.  Many Emacs users are logged into IRC networks via
  Emacs itself, so once the recipient sees an Elisp expression like
  the above one in their chat buffer, visiting the corresponding
  manual page is a simple matter of placing the cursor right after the
  closing parenthesis and typing <code>C-x C-e</code>.
</p>
<p>
  But isn't it clumsy for the sender to type Elisp expressions like
  this merely to share a pointer to a section of a manual with others?
  Turns out, it is not.  This is Emacs!  So of course there are
  key-bindings to do this.
</p>
<p>
  Say, while helping another Emacs user we type <code>M-x info-apropos
  RET version control RET</code> and land on the section "Branches"
  and realise that this is the section that the person we are trying
  to help should read.  Now when we are on this section, we can simply
  type <code>c</code> and Emacs will copy the name of the current Info
  node to the kill ring.  The name looks like this:
</p>
<pre><code>(emacs) Branches</code></pre>
<p>
  While this is handy in some situations, it isn't the
  <code>info</code> expression we want.  It's just the Info node name.
  To copy the complete <code>info</code> expression with the node
  name, we need to use the zero prefix argument with
  the <code>c</code> key.  So when we are on the section "Branches",
  if we type <code>C-0 c</code>, the following expression is copied to
  the kill ring:
</p>
<pre><code>(info "(emacs) Branches")</code></pre>
<p>
  The person who receives this <code>info</code> expression can visit
  the corresponding section of the manual simply by evaluating it.
  For example, after copying the expression in Emacs, they could
  type <code>C-y C-x C-e</code> to paste the expression into a buffer
  and evaluate it immediately.  Alternatively, they might want to
  type <code>M-: C-y RET</code> to bring the
  <code>eval-expression</code> minibuffer, paste the expression there
  and evaluate it.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/emacs-info-expression.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/emacs.html">#emacs</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Triangle-Free Cayley Graph</title>
<link>https://susam.net/triangle-free-cayley-graph.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">cgwnt</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  In this note I elaborate the proof of a claim regarding Cayley
  graphs of symmetric groups with transpositions as generators that I
  found in the book <em>Algebraic Graph Theory</em> by Chris Godsil
  and Gordon Royle.  This claim appears as commentary in Section 3.10
  about <em>Transpositions</em>.  Here I present it in the form of a
  theorem along with a complete proof.
</p>
<p>
  <strong>Theorem.</strong>
  <em>
    If \( \mathcal{T} \) is a set of transpositions, then the Cayley
    graph \( X(\operatorname{Sym}(n), \mathcal{T}) \) has no triangles.
  </em>
</p>
<p>
  <em>Proof.</em>  Suppose the vertices \( a, b, c \in
  \operatorname{Sym}(n) \) form a triangle in the Cayley graph \(
  X(\operatorname{Sym}(n), \mathcal{T}).  \)  Since multiplication by
  \( a^{-1} \) is an automorphism of the Cayley graph (by the proof of
  Theorem 3.1.2 that comes earlier), the vertices \( e, ba^{-1},
  ca^{-1} \) form a triangle too.  Let us label them as \( e, b', c'
  \) respectively.
</p>
<p>
  Now by the definition of a Cayley graph, for any two vertices \( a,
  b \in \operatorname{Sym}(n), \) we have

  \begin{align*}
    a \sim b
    &amp; \iff ba^{-1} \in \mathcal{T} \\
    &amp; \iff ba^{-1} = g \\
    &amp; \iff b = ga
  \end{align*}

  for some \( g \in \mathcal{T}.  \)  Therefore

  \begin{align*}
    e \sim b'  &amp; \iff b' = ge = g, \\
    e \sim c'  &amp; \iff c' = he = h, \\
    b' \sim c' &amp; \iff c' = lb'
  \end{align*}

  for some \( g, h, l \in \mathcal{T}.  \)  Note that the last equality gives

  \[
    l =c'b'^{-1} = hg^{-1} = hg \in \mathcal{T}
  \]

  Therefore \( g, h, hg \in \mathcal{T}.  \)  However, this is
  impossible since the product of two transpositions is \( e, \) a \(
  3 \)-cycle or a product of two disjoint transpositions.  For
  example, \( (12)(12) = e, \) \( (12)(13) = (123) \) and \( (12)(24)
  = (12)(24).  \)  Therefore \( hg \) cannot be a transposition,
  i.e. \( hg \notin \mathcal{T}.  \)  This is a contradiction.
  Therefore the vertices \( a, b, c \) cannot form a triangle.  We
  conclude that the Cayley graph \( X(\operatorname{Sym}(n),
  \mathcal{T}) \) has no triangles.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/triangle-free-cayley-graph.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/mathematics.html">#mathematics</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>CSS Fizz Buzz</title>
<link>https://susam.net/css-fizz-buzz.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">fzcss</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  An implementation of Fizz Buzz in four lines of CSS.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/css-fizz-buzz.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fizz Buzz with Cosines</title>
<link>https://susam.net/fizz-buzz-with-cosines.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">fzbzz</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Fizz Buzz is a counting game that has become oddly popular in the
  world of computer programming as a simple test of basic programming
  skills.  The rules of the game are straightforward.  Players say the
  numbers aloud in order beginning with one.  Whenever a number is
  divisible by 3, they say 'Fizz' instead.  If it is divisible by 5,
  they say 'Buzz'.  If it is divisible by both 3 and 5, the player
  says both 'Fizz' and 'Buzz'.  Here is a typical Python program that
  prints this sequence:
</p>
<pre><code>for n in range(1, 101):
    if n % 15 == 0:
        print('FizzBuzz')
    elif n % 3 == 0:
        print('Fizz')
    elif n % 5 == 0:
        print('Buzz')
    else:
        print(n)</code>
</pre>
<p>
  Here is the output:
  <a href="files/blog/fizz-buzz.txt">fizz-buzz.txt</a>.  Can we make
  the program more complicated?  The words 'Fizz', 'Buzz' and
  'FizzBuzz' repeat in a periodic manner throughout the sequence.
  What else is periodic?  Trigonometric functions!  Perhaps we can use
  trigonometric functions to encode all four rules of the sequence in
  a single closed-form expression.  That is what we are going to
  explore in this article, for fun and no profit.
</p>
<p>
  By the end, we will obtain a discrete Fourier series that can take
  any integer \( n \) and select the corresponding text to be printed.
  In fact, we will derive it using two different methods.  First, we
  will follow a long-winded but hopefully enjoyable approach that
  relies on a basic understanding of complex exponentiation, geometric
  series and trigonometric functions.  Then, we will obtain the same
  result through a direct application of the discrete Fourier
  transform.
</p>
<h2 id="contents">Contents<a href="#contents"></a></h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#definitions">Definitions</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#symbol-functions">Symbol Functions</a></li>
      <li><a href="#index-function">Index Function</a></li>
      <li><a href="#fizz-buzz-sequence">Fizz Buzz Sequence</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#from-indicator-functions-to-cosines">From Indicator Functions to Cosines</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#indicator-functions">Indicator Functions</a></li>
      <li><a href="#complex-exponentials">Complex Exponentials</a></li>
      <li><a href="#cosines">Cosines</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#dft">Discrete Fourier Transform</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#one-period-of-fizz-buzz">One Period of Fizz Buzz</a></li>
      <li><a href="#fourier-coefficients">Fourier Coefficients</a></li>
      <li><a href="#inverse-transform">Inverse Transform</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="definitions">Definitions<a href="#definitions"></a></h2>
<p>
  Before going any further, we establish a precise mathematical
  definition for the Fizz Buzz sequence.  We begin by introducing a
  few functions that will help us define the Fizz Buzz sequence later.
</p>
<h3 id="symbol-functions">Symbol Functions<a href="#symbol-functions"></a></h3>
<p>
  We define a set of four functions \( \{ s_0, s_1, s_2, s_3 \} \) for
  integers \( n \) by:

  \begin{align*}
    s_0(n) &amp;= n, \\
    s_1(n) &amp;= \mathtt{Fizz}, \\
    s_2(n) &amp;= \mathtt{Buzz}, \\
    s_3(n) &amp;= \mathtt{FizzBuzz}.
  \end{align*}

  We call these the symbol functions because they produce every term
  that appears in the Fizz Buzz sequence.  The symbol function \( s_0
  \) returns \( n \) itself.  The functions \( s_1, \) \( s_2 \) and
  \( s_3 \) are constant functions that always return the literal
  words \( \mathtt{Fizz}, \) \( \mathtt{Buzz} \) and \(
  \mathtt{FizzBuzz} \) respectively, no matter what the value of \( n
  \) is.
</p>
<h3 id="index-function">Index Function<a href="#index-function"></a></h3>
<p>
  We define a function \( f(n) \) for integer \( n \) by

  \[
    f(n) = \begin{cases}
      1 &amp; \text{if } 3 \mid n \text{ and } 5 \nmid n, \\
      2 &amp; \text{if } 3 \nmid n \text{ and } 5 \mid n, \\
      3 &amp; \text{if } 3 \mid n \text{ and } 5 \mid n, \\
      0 &amp; \text{otherwise}.
    \end{cases}
  \]

  The notation \( m \mid n \) means that the integer \( m \) divides
  the integer \( n, \) i.e. \( n \) is a multiple of \( m.  \)
  Equivalently, there exists an integer \( c \) such that \( n = cm
 .  \)  Similarly, \( m \nmid n \) means that \( m \) does not divide
  \( n, \) i.e. \( n \) is not a multiple of \( m.  \)
</p>
<p>
  This function covers all four conditions involved in choosing the \(
  n \)th item of the Fizz Buzz sequence.  As we will soon see, this
  function tells us which of the four symbol functions produces the \(
  n \)th item of the Fizz Buzz sequence.  For this reason, we call \(
  f(n) \) the index function.
</p>
<h3 id="fizz-buzz-sequence">Fizz Buzz Sequence<a href="#fizz-buzz-sequence"></a></h3>
<p>
  We now define the Fizz Buzz sequence as the sequence

  \[
    (s_{f(n)}(n))_{n = 1}^{\infty}
  \]

  We can expand the first few terms of the sequence explicitly as
  follows:

  \begin{align*}
    (s_{f(n)}(n))_{n = 1}^{\infty}
    &amp;= (s_{f(1)}(1), \; s_{f(2)}(2), \; s_{f(3)}(3), \; s_{f(4)}(4), \;
            s_{f(5)}(5), \; s_{f(6)}(6), \; s_{f(7)}(7), \; \dots) \\
    &amp;= (s_0(1), \; s_0(2), \; s_1(3), \; s_0(4),
            s_2(5), \; s_1(6), \; s_0(7), \; \dots) \\
    &amp;= (1, \; 2, \; \mathtt{Fizz}, \; 4, \;
            \mathtt{Buzz}, \; \mathtt{Fizz}, \; 7, \; \dots).
  \end{align*}

  Note how the function \( f(n) \) produces an index \( i \) which we
  then use to select the symbol function \( s_i(n) \) to produce the
  \( n \)th term of the sequence.  This is precisely why we decided to
  call \( f(n) \) the index function while defining it in the previous
  section.
</p>
<h2 id="from-indicator-functions-to-cosines">From Indicator Functions to Cosines<a href="#from-indicator-functions-to-cosines"></a></h2>
<p>
  Here we discuss the first method of deriving our closed form
  expression, starting with indicator functions and rewriting them
  using complex exponentials and cosines.
</p>
<h3 id="indicator-functions">Indicator Functions<a href="#indicator-functions"></a></h3>
<p>
  Here is the index function \( f(n) \) from the previous section with
  its cases and conditions rearranged to make it easier to spot
  interesting patterns:

  \[
    f(n) = \begin{cases}
      0 &amp; \text{if } 5 \nmid n \text{ and } 3 \nmid n, \\
      1 &amp; \text{if } 5 \nmid n \text{ and } 3 \mid n, \\
      2 &amp; \text{if } 5 \mid n \text{ and } 3 \nmid n, \\
      3 &amp; \text{if } 5 \mid n \text{ and } 3 \mid n.
    \end{cases}
  \]

  This function helps us select another function \( s_{f(n)}(n) \)
  which in turn determines the \( n \)th term of the Fizz Buzz
  sequence.  Our goal now is to replace this piecewise formula with a
  single closed-form expression.  To do so, we first define indicator
  functions \( I_m(n) \) as follows:

  \[
    I_m(n) = \begin{cases}
      1 &amp; \text{if } m \mid n, \\
      0 &amp; \text{if } m \nmid n.
    \end{cases}
  \]

  The formula for \( f(n) \) can now be written as:

  \[
    f(n) = \begin{cases}
      0 &amp; \text{if } I_5(n) = 0 \text{ and } I_3(n) = 0, \\
      1 &amp; \text{if } I_5(n) = 0 \text{ and } I_3(n) = 1, \\
      2 &amp; \text{if } I_5(n) = 1 \text{ and } I_3(n) = 0, \\
      3 &amp; \text{if } I_5(n) = 1 \text{ and } I_3(n) = 1.
    \end{cases}
  \]

  Do you see a pattern?  Here is the same function written as a table:
</p>
<table class="grid center textcenter">
  <tr>
    <th>\( I_5(n) \)</th>
    <th>\( I_3(n) \)</th>
    <th>\( f(n) \)</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>\( 0 \)</td>
    <td>\( 0 \)</td>
    <td>\( 0 \)</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>\( 0 \)</td>
    <td>\( 1 \)</td>
    <td>\( 1 \)</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>\( 1 \)</td>
    <td>\( 0 \)</td>
    <td>\( 2 \)</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>\( 1 \)</td>
    <td>\( 1 \)</td>
    <td>\( 3 \)</td>
  </tr>
</table>
<p>
  Do you see it now?  If we treat the values in the first two columns
  as binary digits and the values in the third column as decimal
  numbers, then in each row the first two columns give the binary
  representation of the number in the third column.  For example, \(
  3_{10} = 11_2 \) and indeed in the last row of the table, we see the
  bits \( 1 \) and \( 1 \) in the first two columns and the number \(
  3 \) in the last column.  In other words, writing the binary digits
  \( I_5(n) \) and \( I_3(n) \) side by side gives us the binary
  representation of \( f(n).  \)  Therefore

  \[
    f(n) = 2 \, I_5(n) + I_3(n).
  \]

  We can now write a small program to demonstrate this formula:
</p>
<pre>
<code>for n in range(1, 101):
    s = [n, 'Fizz', 'Buzz', 'FizzBuzz']
    i = (n % 3 == 0) + 2 * (n % 5 == 0)
    print(s[i])</code>
</pre>
<p>
  We can make it even shorter at the cost of some clarity:
</p>
<pre>
<code>for n in range(1, 101):
    print([n, 'Fizz', 'Buzz', 'FizzBuzz'][(n % 3 == 0) + 2 * (n % 5 == 0)])</code>
</pre>
<p>
  What we have obtained so far is pretty good.  While there is no
  universal definition of a closed-form expression, I think most
  people would agree that the indicator functions as defined above are
  simple enough to be permitted in a closed-form expression.
</p>
<h3 id="complex-exponentials">Complex Exponentials<a href="#complex-exponentials"></a></h3>
<p>
  In the previous section, we obtained the formula

  \[
    f(n) = I_3(n) + 2 \, I_5(n)
  \]

  which we then used as an index to look up the text to be printed.
  We also argued that this is a pretty good closed-form expression
  already.
</p>
<p>
  However, in the interest of making things more complicated, we must
  ask ourselves: What if we are not allowed to use the indicator
  functions?  What if we must adhere to the commonly accepted meaning
  of a closed-form expression which allows only finite combinations of
  basic operations such as addition, subtraction, multiplication,
  division, integer exponents and roots with integer index as well as
  functions such as exponentials, logarithms and trigonometric
  functions.  It turns out that the above formula can be rewritten
  using only addition, multiplication, division and the cosine
  function.  Let us begin the translation.  Consider the sum

  \[
    S_m(n) = \sum_{k = 0}^{m - 1} e^{i 2 \pi k n / m},
  \]

  where \( i \) is the imaginary unit and \( n \) and \( m \) are
  integers.  This is a geometric series in the complex plane with
  ratio \( r = e^{i 2 \pi n / m}.  \)  If \( n \) is a multiple of \( m
 , \) then \( n = cm \) for some integer \( c \) and we get

  \[
    r
    = e^{i 2 \pi n / m}
    = e^{i 2 \pi c}
    = 1.
  \]

  Therefore, when \( n \) is a multiple of \( m, \) we get

  \[
    S_m(n)
    = \sum_{k = 0}^{m - 1} e^{i 2 \pi k n / m}
    = \sum_{k = 0}^{m - 1} 1^k
    = m.
  \]

  If \( n \) is not a multiple of \( m, \) then \( r \ne 1 \) and the
  geometric series becomes

  \[
    S_m(n)
    = \frac{r^m - 1}{r - 1}
    = \frac{e^{i 2 \pi n} - 1}{e^{i 2 \pi n / m} - 1}
    = 0.
  \]

  Therefore,

  \[
    S_m(n) = \begin{cases}
      m &amp; \text{if } m \mid n, \\
      0 &amp; \text{if } m \nmid n.
    \end{cases}
  \]

  Dividing both sides by \( m, \) we get

  \[
    \frac{S_m(n)}{m} = \begin{cases}
      1 &amp; \text{if } m \mid n, \\
      0 &amp; \text{if } m \nmid n.
    \end{cases}
  \]

  But the right-hand side is \( I_m(n).  \)  Therefore

  \[
    I_m(n)
    = \frac{S_m(n)}{m}
    = \frac{1}{m} \sum_{k = 0}^{m - 1} e^{i 2 \pi k n / m}.
  \]
</p>
<h3 id="cosines">Cosines<a href="#cosines"></a></h3>
<p>
  We begin with Euler's formula

  \[
    e^{i x} = \cos x + i \sin x
  \]

  where \( x \) is a real number.  From this formula, we get

  \[
    e^{i x} + e^{-i x} = 2 \cos x.
  \]

  Therefore

  \begin{align*}
    I_3(n)
    &amp;= \frac{1}{3} \sum_{k = 0}^2 e^{i 2 \pi k n / 3} \\
    &amp;= \frac{1}{3} \left( 1 + e^{i 2 \pi n / 3} +
                                  e^{i 4 \pi n / 3} \right) \\
    &amp;= \frac{1}{3} \left( 1 + e^{i 2 \pi n / 3} +
                                  e^{-i 2 \pi n / 3} \right) \\
    &amp;= \frac{1}{3} + \frac{2}{3} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{3} \right).
  \end{align*}

  The third equality above follows from the fact that \( e^{i 4 \pi n
  / 3} = e^{i 6 \pi n / 3} e^{-i 2 \pi n / 3} = e^{i 2 \pi n} e^{-i 2
  \pi n/3} = e^{-i 2 \pi n / 3} \) when \( n \) is an integer.
</p>
<p>
  The function above is defined for integer values of \( n \) but we
  can extend its formula to real \( x \) and plot it to observe its
  shape between integers.  As expected, the function takes the value
  \( 1 \) whenever \( x \) is an integer multiple of \( 3 \) and \( 0
  \) whenever \( x \) is an integer not divisible by \( 3.  \)
</p>
<figure class="soft">
  <img src="files/blog/fizz-buzz-i3.png" alt="Graph">
  <figcaption>
    Graph of \( \frac{1}{3} + \frac{2}{3} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi x}{3} \right) \)
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  Similarly,

  \begin{align*}
    I_5(n)
    &amp;= \frac{1}{5} \sum_{k = 0}^4 e^{i 2 \pi k n / 5} \\
    &amp;= \frac{1}{5} \left( 1 + e^{i 2 \pi n / 5}
                                + e^{i 4 \pi n / 5}
                                + e^{i 6 \pi n / 5}
                                + e^{i 8 \pi n / 5} \right) \\
    &amp;= \frac{1}{5} \left( 1 + e^{i 2 \pi n / 5}
                                + e^{i 4 \pi n / 5}
                                + e^{-i 4 \pi n / 5}
                                + e^{-i 2 \pi n / 5} \right) \\
    &amp;= \frac{1}{5} + \frac{2}{5} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{5} \right)
                       + \frac{2}{5} \cos \left( \frac{4 \pi n}{5} \right).
  \end{align*}

  Extending this expression to real values of \( x \) allows us to
  plot its shape as well.  Once again, the function takes the value \(
  1 \) at integer multiples of \( 5 \) and \( 0 \) at integers not
  divisible by \( 5.  \)
</p>
<figure class="soft">
  <img src="files/blog/fizz-buzz-i5.png" alt="Graph">
  <figcaption>
    Graph of \(
      \frac{1}{5}
      + \frac{2}{5} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi x}{5} \right)
      + \frac{2}{5} \cos \left( \frac{4 \pi x}{5} \right)
    \)
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  Recall that we expressed \( f(n) \) as

  \[
    f(n) = I_3(n) + 2 \, I_5(n).
  \]

  Substituting these trigonometric expressions yields

  \[
    f(n)
    = \frac{1}{3}
      + \frac{2}{3} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{3} \right)
      + 2 \cdot \left(
        \frac{1}{5}
        + \frac{2}{5} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{5} \right)
        + \frac{2}{5} \cos \left( \frac{4 \pi n}{5} \right)
      \right).
  \]

  A straightforward simplification gives

  \[
    f(n)
    = \frac{11}{15}
      + \frac{2}{3} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{3} \right)
      + \frac{4}{5} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{5} \right)
      + \frac{4}{5} \cos \left( \frac{4 \pi n}{5} \right).
  \]

  We can extend this expression to real \( x \) and plot it as well.
  The resulting curve takes the values \( 0, 1, 2 \) and \( 3 \) at
  integer points, as desired.
</p>
<figure class="soft">
  <img src="files/blog/fizz-buzz-f.png" alt="Graph">
  <figcaption>
    Graph of \(
      \frac{11}{15} +
      \frac{2}{3} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi x}{3} \right) +
      \frac{4}{5} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi x}{5} \right) +
      \frac{4}{5} \cos \left( \frac{4 \pi x}{5} \right)
    \)
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  Now we can write our Python program as follows:
</p>
<pre>
<code>from math import cos, pi
for n in range(1, 101):
    s = [n, 'Fizz', 'Buzz', 'FizzBuzz']
    i = round(11 / 15 + (2 / 3) * cos(2 * pi * n / 3)
                      + (4 / 5) * cos(2 * pi * n / 5)
                      + (4 / 5) * cos(4 * pi * n / 5))
    print(s[i])</code>
</pre>
<h2 id="dft">Discrete Fourier Transform<a href="#dft"></a></h2>
<p>
  The keen-eyed might notice that the expression we obtained for \(
  f(n) \) is a discrete Fourier series.  This is not surprising, since
  the output of a Fizz Buzz program depends only on \( n \bmod 15.  \)
  Any function on a finite cyclic group can be written exactly as a
  finite Fourier expansion.  In this section, we obtain \( f(n) \)
  using the discrete Fourier transform.  It is worth mentioning that
  the calculations presented here are quite tedious to do by hand.
  Nevertheless, this section offers a glimpse of how such calculations
  are performed.  By the end, we will arrive at exactly the same \(
  f(n) \) as before.  There is nothing new to discover here.  We
  simply obtain the same result by a more direct but more laborious
  method.  If this doesn't sound interesting, you may safely skip the
  subsections that follow.
</p>
<h3 id="one-period-of-fizz-buzz">One Period of Fizz Buzz<a href="#one-period-of-fizz-buzz"></a></h3>
<div style="display: none">\( \gdef\arraystretch{1.2} \)</div>
<p>
  We know that \( f(n) \) is a periodic function with period \( 15.  \)
  To apply the discrete Fourier transform, we look at one complete
  period of the function using the values \( n = 0, 1, \dots, 14.  \)
  Over this period, we have:

  \begin{array}{c|ccccccccccccccc}
      n &amp;  0 &amp;  1 &amp;  2 &amp;  3 &amp;  4
        &amp;  5 &amp;  6 &amp;  7 &amp;  8 &amp;  9
        &amp; 10 &amp; 11 &amp; 12 &amp; 13 &amp; 14 \\
    \hline
    f(n) &amp; 3 &amp;  0 &amp;  0 &amp;  1 &amp;  0
         &amp; 2 &amp;  1 &amp;  0 &amp;  0 &amp;  1
         &amp; 2 &amp;  0 &amp;  1 &amp;  0 &amp;  0
  \end{array}

  The discrete Fourier series of \( f(n) \) is

  \[
    f(n) = \sum_{k = 0}^{14} c_k \, e^{i 2 \pi k n / 15}
  \]

  where the Fourier coefficients \( c_k \) are given by the discrete
  Fourier transform

  \[
    c_k = \frac{1}{15} \sum_{n = 0}^{14} f(n) e^{-i 2 \pi k n / 15}.
  \]

  for \( k = 0, 1, \dots, 14.  \)  The formula for \( c_k \) is called
  the discrete Fourier transform (DFT).  The formula for \( f(n) \) is
  called the inverse discrete Fourier transform (IDFT).
</p>
<h3 id="fourier-coefficients">Fourier Coefficients<a href="#fourier-coefficients"></a></h3>
<p>
  Let \( \omega = e^{-i 2 \pi / 15}.  \)  Then using the values of \(
  f(n) \) from the table above, the DFT becomes:

  \[
    c_k = \frac{3 + \omega^{3k} + 2 \omega^{5k} + \omega^{6k}
                  + \omega^{9k} + 2 \omega^{10k} + \omega^{12k}}{15}.
  \]

  Substituting \( k = 0, 1, 2, \dots, 14 \) into the above equation
  gives us the following Fourier coefficients:

  \begin{align*}
    c_{0}  &amp;= \frac{11}{15}, \\
    c_{3}  &amp;= c_{6} = c_{9} = c_{12} = \frac{2}{5}, \\
    c_{5}  &amp;= c_{10} = \frac{1}{3}, \\
    c_{1}  &amp;= c_{2} = c_{4} = c_{7} = c_{8} = c_{11} = c_{13} = c_{14} = 0.
  \end{align*}

  Calculating these Fourier coefficients by hand can be rather
  tedious.  In practice they are almost always calculated using
  numerical software, computer algebra systems or even simple code
  such as the example here:
  <a href="code/fizz-buzz-fourier/fizz-buzz-fourier.py">fizz-buzz-fourier.py</a>.
</p>
<h3 id="inverse-transform">Inverse Transform<a href="#inverse-transform"></a></h3>
<p>
  Once the coefficients are known, we can substitute them into the
  inverse transform introduced earlier to obtain

  \begin{align*}
    f(n)
    &amp;= \sum_{k = 0}^{14} c_k \, e^{i 2 \pi k n / 15} \\[1.5em]
    &amp;= \frac{11}{15}
           + \frac{2}{5} \left(
             e^{i 2 \pi \cdot 3n / 15}
             + e^{i 2 \pi \cdot 6n / 15}
             + e^{i 2 \pi \cdot 9n / 15}
             + e^{i 2 \pi \cdot 12n / 15}
           \right) \\
           &amp; \phantom{=\frac{11}{15}}
           + \frac{1}{3} \left(
             e^{i 2 \pi \cdot 5n / 15}
             + e^{i 2 \pi \cdot 10n / 15}
           \right) \\[1em]
    &amp;= \frac{11}{15}
           + \frac{2}{5} \left(
             e^{i 2 \pi \cdot 3n / 15}
             + e^{i 2 \pi \cdot 6n / 15}
             + e^{-i 2 \pi \cdot 6n / 15}
             + e^{-i 2 \pi \cdot 3n / 15}
           \right) \\
           &amp; \phantom{=\frac{11}{15}}
           + \frac{1}{3} \left(
             e^{i 2 \pi \cdot 5n / 15}
             + e^{-i 2 \pi \cdot 5n / 15}
           \right) \\[1em]
    &amp;= \frac{11}{15}
       + \frac{2}{5} \left(
         2 \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{5} \right)
         + 2 \cos \left( \frac{4 \pi n}{5} \right)
       \right) \\
       &amp; \phantom{=\frac{11}{15}}
       + \frac{1}{3} \left(
         2 \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{3} \right)
       \right) \\[1em]
    &amp;= \frac{11}{15} +
       \frac{4}{5} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{5} \right) +
       \frac{4}{5} \cos \left( \frac{4 \pi n}{5} \right) +
       \frac{2}{3} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{3} \right).
  \end{align*}

  This is exactly the same expression for \( f(n) \) we obtained in
  the previous section.  We see that the Fizz Buzz index function \(
  f(n) \) can be expressed precisely using the machinery of Fourier
  analysis.
</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion"></a></h2>
<p>
  To summarise, we have defined the Fizz Buzz sequence as

  \[
    (s_{f(n)}(n))_{n = 1}^{\infty}
  \]

  where

  \[
    f(n)
    = \frac{11}{15} +
      \frac{2}{3} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{3} \right) +
      \frac{4}{5} \cos \left( \frac{2 \pi n}{5} \right) +
      \frac{4}{5} \cos \left( \frac{4 \pi n}{5} \right).
  \]

  and \( s_0(n) = n, \) \( s_1(n) = \mathtt{Fizz}, \) \( s_2(n) =
  \mathtt{Buzz} \) and \( s_3(n) = \mathtt{FizzBuzz}.  \)  A Python
  program to print the Fizz Buzz sequence based on this definition was
  presented earlier.  That program can be written more succinctly as
  follows:
</p>
<pre>
<code>from math import cos, pi
for n in range(1, 101):
    print([n, 'Fizz', 'Buzz', 'FizzBuzz'][round(11 / 15 + (2 / 3) * cos(2 * pi * n / 3) + (4 / 5) * (cos(2 * pi * n / 5) + cos(4 * pi * n / 5)))])</code>
</pre>
<p>
  We can also wrap this up nicely in a shell one-liner, in case you
  want to share it with your friends and family and surprise them:
</p>
<pre><code>python3 -c 'from math import cos, pi; [print([n, "Fizz", "Buzz", "FizzBuzz"][round(11/15 + (2/3) * cos(2*pi*n/3) + (4/5) * (cos(2*pi*n/5) + cos(4*pi*n/5)))]) for n in range(1, 101)]'</code></pre>
<p>
  We have taken a simple counting game and turned it into a
  trigonometric construction consisting of a discrete Fourier series
  with three cosine terms and four coefficients.  None of this makes
  Fizz Buzz any easier.  Quite the contrary.  But it does show that
  every \( \mathtt{Fizz} \) and \( \mathtt{Buzz} \) now owes its
  existence to a particular set of Fourier coefficients.  We began
  with the modest goal of making this simple problem more complicated.
  I think it is safe to say that we did not fall short.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/fizz-buzz-with-cosines.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/absurd.html">#absurd</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/python.html">#python</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/mathematics.html">#mathematics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/puzzle.html">#puzzle</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nerd Quiz #2</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/nq/2.0.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqtwo</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Nerd Quiz #2 is the second release of Nerd Quiz, a single-page HTML
  application that invites you to gauge your nerd level through short,
  focused quiz sets.  Each question is carefully crafted from everyday
  moments of reading, writing, thinking, learning and exploring.
</p>
<p>
  This release introduces five new questions drawn from a range of
  topics such as chess, graph theory and linguistics.  To try the
  quiz, visit <a href="../../../nq.html#2">nq.html</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/nq/2.0.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/game.html">#game</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Discuss Nerd Quiz</title>
<link>https://susam.net/comments/nq.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqztk</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 01:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A comments page to discuss Nerd Quiz.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/comments/nq.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nerd Quiz #1</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/nq/1.0.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqone</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Nerd Quiz #1 is the first release of Nerd Quiz, a single-page HTML
  application that lets you test your nerd level through short,
  focused quiz sets.  Each question in the quiz is handcrafted from
  everyday moments of reading, writing, thinking, learning and
  exploring.
</p>
<p>
  To try the quiz now, visit <a href="../../../nq.html">nq.html</a>.
</p>
<p>
  The source code of Nerd Quiz is available at
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/nq#readme">github.com/susam/nq</a>
  under the terms of the MIT licence.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/nq/1.0.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/game.html">#game</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nerd Quiz</title>
<link>https://susam.net/nq.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqhtm</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A nerdy, handcrafted quiz built from everyday moments of reading,
  writing, thinking, learning and exploring.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/nq.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>QuickQWERTY 1.2.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/1.2.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">qqotz</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  QuickQWERTY 1.2.0 is now available.  QuickQWERTY is a web-based
  touch typing tutor for QWERTY keyboards that runs directly in the
  web browser.
</p>
<p>
  This release brings small improvements to make the typing tutor
  smoother and the lessons more accurate.  When you return to the
  application, it no longer needlessly redirects you back to Unit 1.1
  if that was the last lesson you practised.
</p>
<p>
  Several lessons have received minor corrections.  Units 7.2 and 7.3
  no longer include the word "tyre", avoiding a preference for either
  British or American spelling.  Units 9.2 and 9.3 now spell
  "orwellian" correctly.  A factual error in Unit 17.4 has been fixed
  too.  It previously said "89 is one more than 99", which now
  correctly reads "89 is one more than 88".
</p>
<p>
  Finally, switching between the 5-6 and 6-7 split layouts is now more
  reliable.  In the previous release, pressing <kbd>Esc</kbd> to
  cancel the confirmation dialogue still caused the switch to go
  through.  Now pressing <kbd>Esc</kbd> properly cancels the switch as
  expected.
</p>
<p>
  To try out the new release of QuickQWERTY, go to
  <a href="../../../quickqwerty.html">quickqwerty.html</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/1.2.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Reinstated My Guestbook After 20 Years</title>
<link>https://susam.net/reinstated-guestbook.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">gbret</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  I have reinstated the <a href="comments/guestbook.html">guestbook</a>
  on this website after 20 years!  As I have written in the
  <a href="about.html">About</a> page, this website began its life as
  an intranet portal in my university network back in 20012005.  That
  portal first ran on Microsoft Personal Web Server (PWS) and later on
  Microsoft Internet Information Services (IIS), with the guestbook
  data stored in a Microsoft Access database.  At the same time, I
  also maintained a small public website on the Internet, hosted on a
  subdomain provided by a free hosting service, where I published a
  subset of the articles from the intranet portal.  Both the intranet
  portal and the public website had guestbooks.  The guestbook on the
  public website was powered by a CGI script provided by the hosting
  service, which inserted each comment directly into the guestbook
  HTML page.  As some of you might guess, yes, it was vulnerable to
  cross-site scripting, but that's beside the point.
</p>
<p>
  After leaving the university, I registered my own domain name and
  set up my current website on the World Wide Web and included some of
  the content from both the original intranet portal and the old
  public website.  For some reason, though, I never thought to include
  a guestbook.  And so this website went on without a guestbook for
  the next 20 years.  Finally, in June 2025, I decided to bring the
  guestbook back.  I already had a commenting system implemented for
  this website using Common Lisp and Hunchentoot, so I simply reused
  it for the guestbook.  The
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/susam.net/blob/0.3.0/form.lisp">server program</a>
  accepts POST requests to receive comments and writes them to text
  files on the web server for manual review.  The comments are then
  rendered as static HTML pages by my static site generator.  In a
  way, it is less a comment system and more a static comment pages
  generator.
</p>
<p>
  Unfortunately, I could not restore all the comments from the
  original guestbooks.  The ASP source code of my intranet portal as
  well as the guestbook database are now lost to time.  Note that what
  I refer to as ASP here is now known as Classic ASP, to avoid
  confusion with ASP.NET.  A CD-ROM backup eventually succumbed to
  disc rot and with it vanished the source code and the database.  But
  a handful of comments had survived because they had found their way
  into other files and correspondence and I have now included them
  here.  I had better luck with the guestbook of the old public
  website, from which I was able to recover a greater number of
  comments.  It is still only a small fraction of what once existed,
  but it feels good to have even those fragments preserved.  The new
  guestbook is now available here:
  <a href="comments/guestbook.html">Guestbook</a>.
</p>
<p>
  I wasn't expecting anybody to notice the new guestbook.  It is only
  mentioned in the <a href="about.html">About</a> and
  <a href="links.html">Links</a> pages, neither of which see much
  traffic.  Here are a few examples:
</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>
    I love that your website has a guestbook!  :D
  </p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
  <p>
    Love the guestbook!  We need more of these.  Makes you feel
    invited.
  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>
  It's a small addition to my website, but after two decades, it feels
  good to see the guestbook alive again and even better to see
  visitors enjoying it!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/reinstated-guestbook.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>
