<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

<channel>
<title>Susam's Meta Pages</title>
<link>https://susam.net/tag/meta.html</link>
<atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.xml"/>
<description>Feed for Susam's Meta Pages</description>

<item>
<title>Ideas</title>
<link>https://susam.net/ideas.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">ideas</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>Ideas</h1>
<p>
  Hello!  This is my <a href="https://aboutideasnow.com/about">ideas
  page</a> where I keep a brief record of some ideas I might want to
  explore in the near future.  For ideas I have already begun
  exploring, please see my <a href="now.html">now page</a> or
  my <a href="pages.html">web log</a> instead.
</p>
<p>
  As of 03 Jan 2026, I have the following ideas in mind that I might
  want to explore in future:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Explore the problem of checking whether two self-complementary
    graphs are isomorphic.
  </li>
  <li>
    Learn why \( s \)-arc transitive graph must have \( s \le 7.  \)
  </li>
</ul>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/ideas.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Now</title>
<link>https://susam.net/now.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nowpg</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 02 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>Now</h1>
<p>
  Hello!  This is my <a href="https://nownownow.com/about">now
  page</a> where I keep a brief record of what I am up to these days.
</p>
<p>
  As of 03 Jan 2026, I am:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Studying the book <em>Algebraic Graph Theory</em> by Godsil and
    Royle.
  </li>
  <li>
    Learning about the Coxeter graph and Tutte's 8-cage.
  </li>
  <li>
    Learning about distance-transitive graphs, in general.
  </li>
  <li>
    Maintaining this website.
  </li>
  <li>
    Occasionally posting comments to Hacker News
    (<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/threads?id=susam">see here</a>).
  </li>
</ul>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/now.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Discuss Nerd Quiz</title>
<link>https://susam.net/comments/nq.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqztk</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2025 01:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A comments page to discuss Nerd Quiz.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/comments/nq.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Blogroll</title>
<link>https://susam.net/roll.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">bgrll</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>Blogroll</h1>
<p>
  The blogroll is available in the online copy of this website at
  <a href="https://susam.net/roll.html">susam.net/roll.html</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/roll.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Colophon</title>
<link>https://susam.net/colophon.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">djhst</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>Colophon</h1>
<p>
  Here are some details about how this website is maintained and
  published:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>
      This website runs on a <a href="https://www.debian.org/">Debian</a> system.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      This website is served
      using <a href="https://packages.debian.org/stable/nginx">Nginx</a>.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      This website is generated statically using a small
      <a href="https://github.com/susam/susam.net/blob/main/site.lisp">Common
        Lisp program</a>.  This program is available under the terms of
      the MIT licence.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      Every line of HTML and CSS that makes this website is
      handcrafted.  The final HTML pages, however, are generated using
      a Common Lisp program.  This program merely combines the
      handcrafted HTML content with a handcrafted HTML layout to
      generate the pages that are served over the web.  The content
      HTML, layout HTML and the Common Lisp program were all written
      from scratch.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      All web pages on this website are
      <a href="https://github.com/susam/susam.net/blob/08a2d7b/Makefile#L372-L377">validated
      using HTML Tidy</a>.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      While most of this website is made of static HTML pages served
      via Nginx, the pages for the comment and subscriber forms are
      dynamic in nature.  They are implemented using Common Lisp and
      Hunchentoot.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      This website has a <a href="pages.html">site-wide page list</a>
      that includes every page on this website.  It doesn't matter if
      the page is part of a blog, a standalone HTML tool or an HTML
      game.  Every single web page on this website occurs in this
      list.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      This website has a <a href="links.html">links page</a> that has
      pointers to various sections of my website.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      This website has a <a href="tag/">tag list page</a>
      that can be used to browse this website by topics.  Clicking on
      any tag on the tag list page, presents a list of all web pages
      that have been marked with that tag.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      This website provides a consolidated <a href="feed.xml">web feed
      (RSS)</a>.  The Common Lisp program mentioned earlier ensures
      that every new web page that appears on this website also
      appears in this web feed.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      Every tag has its own web feed.  For example,
      see <a href="tag/technology.html">tag/technology.html</a> for a
      list of all pages tagged "Technology" and then
      see <a href="tag/technology.xml">tag/technology.xml</a> for the
      corresponding web feed.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      The web feeds are sparingly styled with
      <a href="feed.xsl">XSLT</a>.  Web browsers that support XSL
      transformation for web feeds render the feeds as HTML (rather
      than raw XML) as determined by the stylesheet.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      This website has an old-fashioned
      <a href="comments/guestbook.html">guestbook</a>.  Feel free to
      leave a message there if you would like to say hello or share a
      thought.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      This website includes a <a href="roll.html">blogroll</a>
      generated by a small Common Lisp program.  It reads the RSS and
      Atom feeds of my favourite blogs and generates a page with links
      to recent entries.  This has turned out to be a pleasant and
      effective way to keep up with my feeds, so much so that I no
      longer use any dedicated feed reader software or aggregator
      services.  See also: <a href="blogroll-as-feed-reader.html">My
      Blogroll Is My Feed Reader</a>.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      Every directory and subdirectory on this website has a directory
      listing page that lists all its files and subdirectories.
      See <a href="ls.html">ls.html</a> for an example.  Subdirectory
      names are marked with a trailing slash.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      This website loads KaTeX to render LaTeX snippets on web pages
      that contain mathematical formulas.  For example, see the page
      <a href="integrating-factor.html">integrating-factor.html</a>.
      KaTeX is not loaded on other web pages.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      All internal links on this website are relative links.  In fact,
      all internal resources like the stylesheet, KaTeX, etc. too are
      loaded using relative links.  Doing so allows me to browse this
      website locally from my local drive without having to run a web
      server on my development system.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    All web pages on this website have been
    <a href="https://github.com/susam/susam.net/blob/0.3.0/Makefile#L486-L490">validated
    to ensure that there are no broken internal links</a>.
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      When you visit any web page on this website, all resources are
      loaded from this website and only this website.  No external
      resources are loaded.  This ensures that when you visit this
      website, no data about your client is transmitted to another web
      server.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      This website does not load analytics scripts.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      This website does not use cookies.
    </p>
  </li>
</ul>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/colophon.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Quick Links</title>
<link>https://susam.net/links.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">pmryq</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>Quick Links</h1>
<p>
  This page contains quick links to various sections of this website.
</p>
<h2 id="main">Main Sections<a href="#main"></a></h2>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="./">Blog Posts</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="maze.html">Quick Notes</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="pages.html">All Pages</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="comments/">All Comments</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="tag/">Tags</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="comments/guestbook.html">Guestbook</a>
  </li>
</ul>
<h2 id="more">Additional Sections<a href="#more"></a></h2>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="backlinks.html">Backlinks</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="roll.html">Blogroll</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="comments/bug.html">Bug Reports</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="colophon.html">Colophon</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="cc/">Computation Club</a>
  </li>
</ul>
<h2 id="fun">Fun Pages<a href="#fun"></a></h2>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="contrast.html">Contrast Calculator</a> &mdash; Calculate contrast between two colours per WCAG formula
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="cfrs.html">CFRS[]</a> &mdash; Minimal drawing language with only six commands
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="css-fizz-buzz.html">CSS Fizz Buzz</a> &mdash; Fizz Buzz in four lines of CSS
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="fxyt.html">FXYT</a> &mdash; Tiny, stack-based, postfix canvas colouring language
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="myrgb.html">Guess My RGB</a> &mdash; RGB colour guessing game
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="invaders.html">Invaders</a> &mdash; 1980s-arcade-style invaders game
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="jokes.html">Jokes</a> &mdash; My favourite jokes
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="nq.html">Nerd Quiz</a> &mdash; Built from everyday moments of exploration
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="primegrid.html">Prime Number Grid Explorer</a> &mdash; Explore prime numbers in a grid
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="quickqwerty.html">QuickQWERTY</a> &mdash; Touch typing tutor for QWERTY keyboard
  </li>
</ul>
<h2 id="demos">Fun Demos<a href="#demos"></a></h2>
<ul>
  <li>
    CFRS[] Demos:
    <a href="cfrs.html#1">#1</a>,
    <a href="cfrs.html#2">#2</a>,
    <a href="cfrs.html#3">#3</a>,
    <a href="cfrs.html#4">#4</a>,
    <a href="cfrs.html#5">#5</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    FXYT Demos:
    <a href="fxyt.html#XYxTN1srN255pTN1sqD">#1</a>,
    <a href="fxyt.html#XYaTN1srN255pTN1sqN0">#2</a>,
    <a href="fxyt.html#XYoTN1srN255pTN1sqDN0S">#3</a>,
    <a href="fxyt.html#XYpTN1srN255pTN1sqD">#4</a>,
    <a href="fxyt.html#XYN256sTdrD">#5</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    Invaders: <a href="invaders.html#auto">Autopilot</a>
  </li>
</ul>
<h2 id="quirky">Quirky Pages<a href="#quirky"></a></h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="pc.html">ASCII PC</a></li>
  <li><a href="assoc.html">Associations</a></li>
  <li><a href="eql.html">Equal Length Words</a></li>
  <li><a href="0573e7473.html">SHA256 Hash of Self-Referential Message</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="sections">Subscribe<a href="#sections"></a></h2>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="feed.xml">By RSS Feed</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="form/subscribe/">By Email Newsletter</a>
  </li>
</ul>
<h2 id="social">Social<a href="#social"></a></h2>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="https://codeberg.org/susam">Codeberg</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://github.com/susam">GitHub</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://mastodon.social/@susam">Mastodon</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://twitch.tv/susampal">Twitch</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://web.libera.chat/#susam">IRC</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://app.element.io/#/room/#susam:matrix.org">Matrix</a>
  </li>
</ul>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/links.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Report Bug</title>
<link>https://susam.net/comments/bug.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">bugtk</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 19:09:23 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A comments page to report bugs, typos and errors found on this
  website.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/comments/bug.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Computation Club Meeting</title>
<link>https://susam.net/meet/</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">qfehz</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Meeting link for computation club.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/meet/">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Privacy Notice</title>
<link>https://susam.net/privacy.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">lfqtp</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>Privacy Notice</h1>
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/">Susam.Net</a> (this website) is a
  personal website maintained by Susam Pal.  This privacy notice
  explains how this website uses the data it collects from you when
  you use this website.
</p>
<h2 id="data-items">Data Items<a href="#data-items"></a></h2>
<p>
  This website collects the following data:
</p>
<ol>
  <li>
    <p>
      The text submitted by you if you submit a new comment to this
      website.  This text submitted by you may contain your name, a
      URL to your profile on the world wide web and a comment.  This
      text is written by you, so you are in complete control of what
      you submit in the text.  You must not submit sensitive personal
      data to this website.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      Your email address submitted by you if you submit a subscribe or
      unsubscribe request to this website.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      Your Internet Protocol (IP) address used to visit this website.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      HTTP referrer URL sent by your web browser or client software
      while connecting to this website.  A web browser or a client
      software typically, but not necessarily, sends the URL of the
      web page or website where you clicked on a link to visit this
      website as the HTTP referrer value.  If this website is visited
      directly without clicking on any link, then a web browser or
      client does not typically send any HTTP referrer data.
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      User agent string sent by your web browser or client software
      while visiting this website.  A web browser or a client software
      typically, but not necessarily, includes the names and versions
      of your device and operating system as well as the name and
      version of your web browser or client software in the user agent
      string.
    </p>
  </li>
</ol>
<h2 id="data-collection">Data Collection<a href="#data-collection"></a></h2>
<p>
  When you visit this website, your IP address, referrer data and user
  agent string are automatically recorded in web server log files.
</p>
<p>
  When you submit a new comment to this website successfully, your
  text is written to a file on the web server.  If the comment
  submission fails due to errors, then your text is neither saved nor
  published.  If the comment submission succeeds, the text submitted
  by you is reviewed within 30 days.  If your comment is found to be
  suitable for this website, then the text you have submitted is
  published on the website.  If the comment is found to be unsuitable
  for this website, then the text file containing your submitted text
  is deleted.
</p>
<p>
  When you submit a new subscribe or unsubscribe request to this
  website successfully, your email address is written to a file on the
  web server.  If the request submission fails due to errors, then
  your email address is not saved.  If the subscribe or unsubscribe
  request succeeds, the email address submitted by you is added to a
  Google Groups mailing list that is used to send email newsletters.
  The use of your email address by Google Groups is covered by
  Google's privacy policy.
</p>
<h2 id="data-usage">Data Usage<a href="#data-usage"></a></h2>
<p>
  The IP address, referrer data and user agent string is used to
  monitor abuse of this website such as submitting spam comments,
  sending too many requests to reduce the availability of this
  website, etc.  This data is also used to mitigate abuse of this
  website by blocking certain combinations of IP address, referrer
  data and/or user agent from accessing this website or by limiting
  the number of requests such a combination may send to this website.
</p>
<p>
  If you submit a comment to this website successfully and if the
  comment is found to be suitable for this website during review, the
  comment text is published at a comments page on this website.
  Whether a comment is published or not is at the discretion of the
  maintainer of this website.  When your comment text is published on
  this website, it becomes available publicly to anyone who visits the
  comments page.  You must not submit sensitive personal data to this
  website.
</p>
<p>
  If you submit a subscribe request to this website successfully, then
  at the discretion of the maintainer of this website, your email
  address may be added to the email newsletter recipient list.  The
  recipient list is maintained in Google Groups, a third-party service
  provided by Google LLC.  This website uses Google Groups mailing
  list to send email newsletters.  The mailing list is configured to
  not expose your email address to other subscribers.  The use of your
  email address by Google Groups is covered by Google's privacy
  policy.
</p>
<p>
  If you submit an unsubscribe request to this website successfully,
  then your email address is removed from the Google Groups mailing
  list within 30 days if the email address exists in the mailing list.
  You can remove your email address immediately from the Google Groups
  mailing list by sending an email
  to <code>susampal+unsubscribe@googlegroups.com</code>.
</p>
<h2 id="data-storage">Data Storage<a href="#data-storage"></a></h2>
<p>
  The IP address, referrer data and user agent string are stored in
  web server log files.  This data is retained for 15 days.  After 15
  days, this data is deleted automatically.
</p>
<p>
  A successfully submitted comment text is first stored in a text file
  on the web server.  The comment text is reviewed within 30 days.  If
  the comment is found to be suitable for this website, the comment
  text is copied to a comments page where the comment becomes
  available publicly on the world wide web.  If the comment is found
  to be unsuitable for this website, then the text file containing
  your submitted text is deleted from the web server.  You must never
  submit sensitive personal data to this website.
</p>
<p>
  A successfully submitted email address in a subscribe or unsubscribe
  request is first stored in a text file on the web server.  The email
  address is reviewed within 30 days.  At the discretion of the
  maintainer of this website, a successfully submitted subscription
  request is either accepted or rejected.  When a subscription request
  is accepted, the email address is added to a Google Groups mailing
  list that is used to send email newsletters.  After adding your
  email address to the mailing list, the text file containing your
  email address is deleted from the web server.  The mailing list is
  configured to not expose your email address to other subscribers.
  When a subscription request is rejected, the text file containing
  your email address is deleted from the web server.  A successfully
  submitted unsubscribe request is always accepted within 30 days.
  The email address submitted in an unsubscribe request is removed
  from the Google Groups mailing list within 30 days if it exists in
  the mailing list.  Then the text file containing the email address
  is deleted.  The use of your email address by Google Groups is
  covered by Google's privacy policy.
</p>
<h2 id="third-party-services">Third-Party Services<a href="#third-party-services"></a></h2>
<p>
  If and only if you successfully submit a request to subscribe to the
  email newsletters of this website and your subscription requested is
  accepted, your email address is added to a Google Groups mailing
  list used to send email newsletters.  Google Groups is a third-party
  service provided by Google LLC.  The use of your email address by
  Google Groups is covered by Google's privacy policy.  Google's
  privacy policy is available
  at <a href="https://policies.google.com/privacy">policies.google.com/privacy</a>.
</p>
<h2 id="third-party-analytics">Third-Party Analytics<a href="#third-party-analytics"></a></h2>
<p>
  This website does not use third-party analytics.
</p>
<h2 id="cookies">Cookies<a href="#cookies"></a></h2>
<p>
  This website does not use cookies.
</p>
<h2 id="marketing">Marketing<a href="#marketing"></a></h2>
<p>
  This website does not use your data for marketing purpose.
</p>
<h2 id="contact">Contact<a href="#contact"></a></h2>
<p>
  If you have any questions about the data collected by this website,
  please contact susam (dot) pal (at) gmail (dot) com.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/privacy.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Forms</title>
<link>https://susam.net/form/</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">jqqvx</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>Forms</h1>
<ul style="font-family: monospace,monospace; list-style-type: none; padding: 0">
  <li style="margin-top: 1em">
    <a href="comment/">comment/</a>
  </li>
  <li style="margin-top: 1em">
    <a href="subscribe/">subscribe/</a>
  </li>
  <li style="margin-top: 1em">
    <a href="unsubscribe/">unsubscribe/</a>
  </li>
</ul>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/form/">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Subscribe</title>
<link>https://susam.net/form/subscribe/</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">ysyly</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>Subscribe</h1>
<p>
  The subscription form is not available in this local copy of the
  website.  To access it, please visit the online version at
  <a href="https://susam.net/form/subscribe/">susam.net/form/subscribe/</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/form/subscribe/">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Unsubscribe</title>
<link>https://susam.net/form/unsubscribe/</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">johoc</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>Unsubscribe</h1>
<p>
  The unsubscription form is not available in this local copy of the
  website.  To access it, please visit the online version at
  <a href="https://susam.net/form/unsubscribe/">susam.net/form/unsubscribe/</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/form/unsubscribe/">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Comment</title>
<link>https://susam.net/form/comment/</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">czzkw</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 15 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>Comment</h1>
<p>
  The comment form is not available in this local copy of the website.
  To access it, please visit the online version at
  <a href="https://susam.net/form/comment/">susam.net/form/comment/</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/form/comment/">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>About Me</title>
<link>https://susam.net/about.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">llwsv</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h1>About Me</h1>
<p>
  Hi!  I am Susam Pal.  Welcome to my website.  This page provides a
  brief introduction about me and this website.
</p>
<p>
  I am a software engineer by profession.  I have a keen interest in
  free and open source software.  My first non-trivial contribution to
  open source was
  <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/NUTCH-559">NUTCH-559</a>
  in 2007.  That contribution added support for various authentication
  schemes to Apache Nutch, an open source web crawler.  I have
  remained active in the open source communities since then.  I also
  develop and maintain a few open source projects of my own at
  <a href="https://github.com/susam">github.com/susam</a>.  For a list
  of my projects, see my <a href="foss.html">open source work
  details</a>.
</p>
<p>
  When not involved with technology, I like reading books, playing the
  piano and travelling.
</p>
<h2 id="irc">IRC<a href="#irc"></a></h2>
<p>
  I am usually online as my IRC nick <em>susam</em> on
  <a href="https://web.libera.chat/">Libera IRC</a>.  I hang out at
  various channels like #algorithms, #commonlisp, #emacs, #python,
  etc.
</p>
<p>
  The #algorithms channel was founded by me first on Freenode in 2007
  when there was no such channel dedicated to the subject of
  algorithms.  It started as a tiny community of about 10 members from
  the ##math channel and then gradually grew to have over 200 members
  within a few years.  The channel was then
  <a href="algorithms-channel-migrates-to-libera-chat.html">migrated</a>
  to Libera in 2021.
</p>
<h2 id="website">Website<a href="#website"></a></h2>
<p>
  This website is generated using a Common Lisp program.  Most of this
  website is static in nature.  The
  <a href="form/comment/?p=about">comment form</a> on this
  website is served dynamically using a tiny web server program
  written in Common Lisp.  See
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/susam.net">github.com/susam/susam.net</a>
  for the source code of this website.
</p>
<p>
  Every line of HTML and CSS that makes this website is handcrafted.
  See <a href="colophon.html">colophon.html</a> for more details about
  how this website is written and run.
</p>
<p>
  The primary copy of this website is hosted at
  <a href="https://susam.net/">susam.net</a>.  A mirror of the
  website is hosted at
  <a href="https://susam.github.io/">susam.github.io</a>.
</p>
<p>
  This website began its life as an intranet portal running on an
  intranet server out of my dorm room during my university days back
  in 2001-2005.  That intranet server was named <code>maze</code>.  I
  used to run that server for my fellow students in our university's
  computer network.  The server used to host an FTP server and an HTTP
  portal for mathematical puzzles, technical articles, free software
  downloads and audio/video streaming.  While that intranet portal and
  its source code written in Classic ASP are now long gone, some of
  its content still survives on this website.
</p>
<h2 id="browse">Browse<a href="#browse"></a></h2>
<p>
  The <a href="./">home page</a> of this website presents
  my primary blog.  I write about technology, mathematics and other
  miscellaneous topics on this blog.  The posts on my primary blog
  often tend to be long-form, involved and detailed.  They sometimes
  take considerable time to write and publish.  As a result, the
  interval between two posts on this blog can range from several weeks
  to months.
</p>
<p>
  I also archive notes, code and various miscellaneous files on other
  sections of this website that I update more frequently than my
  primary blog.  Visit <a href="links.html">links.html</a> to find
  quick links to my primary blog as well as other sections of this
  website.
</p>
<h2 id="guestbook">Guestbook<a href="#guestbook"></a></h2>
<p>
  This website has a simple, old-fashioned guestbook.  Please
  visit <a href="comments/guestbook.html">guestbook.html</a> if you
  would like to leave a comment.
</p>
<h2 id="blogroll">Blogroll<a href="#blogroll"></a></h2>
<p>
  This website has a blogroll.  On a particularly hot summer day in
  June 2025, with temperatures soaring to 31&nbsp;&deg;C, I decided to
  write a small Common Lisp program that generates a page with links
  to recent entries from my favourite blogs.  To check my blogroll,
  please visit <a href="roll.html">roll.html</a>.
</p>
<p>
  I have found this to be a great way to keep up with my feeds.
  Thanks to this section of my website, I no longer use feed readers
  or aggregators.  I could never quite make a habit of using them
  regularly anyway.
</p>
<p>
  Credit for this nifty and very effective idea of using my blogroll
  as my feed reader goes to Alex Kladov!  It was Alex's
  website, <a href="https://matklad.github.io/">matklad.github.io</a>,
  that inspired me to implement <a href="roll.html">my own
  blogroll</a>.
</p>
<h2 id="colours">Colours<a href="#colours"></a></h2>
<p>
  This website supports both light and dark colour schemes.  The
  information box below shows the colour scheme selected right now.
</p>
<p class="light highlight">
  The <strong>light colour scheme</strong> is active currently.
</p>
<p class="dark highlight">
  The <strong>dark colour scheme</strong> is active currently.
</p>
<p>
  If you would like to browse this website using the opposite colour
  scheme, please check if your operating system or web browser
  supports changing the preferred colour scheme.  Most modern
  operating systems do support it.
</p>
<h2 id="name">Name<a href="#name"></a></h2>
<p>
  I have been told many times that my name, <em>"Susam"</em>, is a
  little unusual which makes it difficult for others to figure how to
  pronounce it.  It is pronounced almost like the English
  words <em>"sue sum"</em> (/suːsʌm/).  However you may call my name
  however you find most natural, convenient or intuitive.  I do not
  mind mispronunciations of my name at all whatsoever.
</p>
<h2 id="bugs">Bugs<a href="#bugs"></a></h2>
<p>
  If you find any bugs, typos or errors on this website, please report
  them to me by <a href="form/comment/?p=bug">sending a
  comment here</a>.  See also <a href="comments/bug.html">the bug
  report page</a> for previously reported issues.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/about.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Talks</title>
<link>https://susam.net/talks.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">uyaqd</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  My talks.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/talks.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>FOSS</title>
<link>https://susam.net/foss.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">spwvm</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2006 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Free and open source contributions.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/foss.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>CV</title>
<link>https://susam.net/cv.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">vvxyz</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Curriculum vitae.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/cv.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Guestbook</title>
<link>https://susam.net/comments/guestbook.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">igzli</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2002 16:06:29 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Guestbook
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/comments/guestbook.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/meta.html">#meta</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>
