<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

<channel>
<title>Susam's Miscellaneous Pages</title>
<link>https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html</link>
<atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.xml"/>
<description>Feed for Susam's Miscellaneous Pages</description>

<item>
<title>Circular Recursive Negating Acronyms</title>
<link>https://susam.net/circular-recursive-negating-acronynms.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">crnax</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  One of my favourite acronyms from the world of computing and
  technology is XINU.  It stands for 'XINU Is Not Unix'.  The
  delightful thing about this acronym is that XINU is also UNIX
  spelled backwards.
</p>
<p>
  For a given word <em>W</em>, a recursive acronym that both
  negates <em>W</em> and reverses it is possible when <em>W</em> has
  the form <em>W</em> = '?NI?' where each '?' denotes a distinct
  letter.  Some fictitious examples make this clearer:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>LINA Is Not ANIL.</li>
  <li>TINK Is Not KNIT.</li>
</ul>
<p>
  Words of the form '?N?' also work if we are happy to contract the
  word 'is' in the acronym.  In fact, in this case we can even obtain
  circular recursive acronyms:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>ANI's Not INA.  INA's Not ANI.</li>
  <li>ONE's Not ENO.  ENO's Not ONE.</li>
</ul>
<p>
  In each pair, the two acronyms negate each other, making them
  circular while also being reverses of one another.  Such acronyms
  could serve as amusing names for expressing friendly banter between
  rival projects.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/circular-recursive-negating-acronynms.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nerd Quiz #3</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/nq/3.0.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqthr</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Nerd Quiz #3 is the third release of Nerd Quiz, a single-page HTML
  application that invites you to test your nerd level through a short
  quiz.  Each question is inspired by everyday moments of reading,
  writing, thinking, learning and exploring.
</p>
<p>
  This release introduces five new questions drawn from a range of
  topics, including computing history, graph theory and Unix.
  Visit <a href="../../../nq.html#3">Nerd Quiz</a> to try the quiz.
</p>
<p>
  A community discussion page is available at
  <a href="../../../comments/nq.html">Discuss Nerd Quiz</a>.  You are
  very welcome to share your score or discuss the questions there.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/nq/3.0.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/game.html">#game</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nerd Quiz #2</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/nq/2.0.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqtwo</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Nerd Quiz #2 is the second release of Nerd Quiz, a single-page HTML
  application that invites you to gauge your nerd level through short,
  focused quiz sets.  Each question is carefully crafted from everyday
  moments of reading, writing, thinking, learning and exploring.
</p>
<p>
  This release introduces five new questions drawn from a range of
  topics such as chess, graph theory and linguistics.  To try the
  quiz, visit <a href="../../../nq.html#2">nq.html</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/nq/2.0.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/game.html">#game</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nerd Quiz #1</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/nq/1.0.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqone</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Nerd Quiz #1 is the first release of Nerd Quiz, a single-page HTML
  application that lets you test your nerd level through short,
  focused quiz sets.  Each question in the quiz is handcrafted from
  everyday moments of reading, writing, thinking, learning and
  exploring.
</p>
<p>
  To try the quiz now, visit <a href="../../../nq.html">nq.html</a>.
</p>
<p>
  The source code of Nerd Quiz is available at
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/nq#readme">github.com/susam/nq</a>
  under the terms of the MIT licence.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/nq/1.0.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/game.html">#game</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Million Times Million</title>
<link>https://susam.net/million-times-million.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">milln</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Is a million times a million a <em>billion</em> or is it
  a <em>trillion</em>?  For my entire childhood, it was a billion,
  only for me to grow up and realise, as an adult, that it had better
  be a trillion!
</p>
<h2 id="growing-up-with-the-long-scale">Growing Up With the Long Scale<a href="#growing-up-with-the-long-scale"></a></h2>
<p>
  As a child, I stumbled upon an old dictionary lying around our house
  and that was where I discovered the names of large numbers.  The
  dictionary used the long scale system, which is based on powers of a
  million.  According to the long scale system,
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    a million times a million is a billion,
  </li>
  <li>
    a million times a million times a million is a trillion,
  </li>
  <li>
    a million multiplied by itself four times is a quadrillion,
  </li>
  <li>
    multiply it five times and we get a quintillion
  </li>
  <li>
    and so on.
  </li>
</ul>
<p>
  These long scale names made a lot of sense to me.  Each name told us
  exactly how many times we multiplied a million by itself.  The
  little prefix at the start, like <em>bi-</em>, <em>tri-</em>,
  <em>quadri-</em>, <em>quinti-</em>, etc. matched the number of times
  a million appeared in the multiplication: twice for a billion, three
  times for a trillion and so on.  If I came across a number like
  quintillion, I immediately knew it meant a million multiplied by
  itself five times, so a quintillion had to be \( (10^6)^5 =
  10^{30}.  \)  It was simple and intuitive.
</p>
<p>
  Now imagine my disappointment when I left home for university, got
  access to computers and the World Wide Web and discovered that the
  names I had learnt were off by several orders of magnitude compared
  with what everyone else was using.  The long scale names I had grown
  up with were irrelevant in this new world I was stepping into.  It
  was the short scale that had taken over most of the technology
  world, especially in computing.  In the short scale, a million times
  a million is no longer a billion.  Instead, somehow, it is a
  trillion!  Similarly, a million multiplied three times is no longer
  a trillion.  It is a quintillion!  What on earth was going on?
</p>
<p>
  Naturally, I had to go through a period of adjustment, letting go of
  my old intuition for the long scale names and getting used to the
  short scale ones.  At the same time, I found a way to trick my mind
  into making sense of the short scale.  Before I get into the mental
  gymnastics that made the short scale click for me, let us first take
  a quick look at the long scale and short scale names side by side.
</p>
<h2 id="same-names-different-numbers">Same Names, Different Numbers<a href="#same-names-different-numbers"></a></h2>
<p>
  The long scale and short scale are simply two different ways of
  naming large numbers.  To see how they differ, here is a table
  showing what each name corresponds to in the two systems.
</p>
<table class="grid center">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Number</th>
      <th>Long Scale</th>
      <th>Short Scale</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>\( 10^6 \)</td>
      <td>Million</td>
      <td>Million</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>\( 10^9 \)</td>
      <td>Milliard</td>
      <td>Billion</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>\( 10^{12} \)</td>
      <td>Billion</td>
      <td>Trillion</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>\( 10^{15} \)</td>
      <td>Billiard</td>
      <td>Quadrillion</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>\( 10^{18} \)</td>
      <td>Trillion</td>
      <td>Quintillion</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>\( 10^{21} \)</td>
      <td>Trilliard</td>
      <td>Sextillion</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>\( 10^{24} \)</td>
      <td>Quadrillion</td>
      <td>Septillion</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>\( 10^{27} \)</td>
      <td>Quadrilliard</td>
      <td>Octillion</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>\( 10^{30} \)</td>
      <td>Quintillion</td>
      <td>Nonillion</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>\( 10^{33} \)</td>
      <td>Quintilliard</td>
      <td>Decillion</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>
  As the table shows, the two systems agree on the value of a million,
  but diverge immediately after.  From that point on, the same names
  represent increasingly different magnitudes.
</p>
<h2 id="making-sense-of-the-short-scale">Making Sense of the Short Scale<a href="#making-sense-of-the-short-scale"></a></h2>
<p>
  I used to quite like the long scale names because the prefix in each
  name is determined by how many times we multiply a million by
  itself.  Each prefix reflects the value of \( n \) in the number \(
  10^{6n}, \) where \( n \) is a positive integer.  For example, if \(
  n = 3, \) we get \( 10^{18}, \) which in the long scale is called
  a <em>trillion</em>.  But in the short scale, the same number is
  called a <em>quintillion</em>.  How can we make sense of it?
</p>
<p>
  One way to interpret the short scale is to count how many additional
  thousands are multiplied onto one thousand.  A thousand is, of
  course, just <em>one thousand</em>.  Multiply it by another thousand
  and we get a <em>million</em>.  Multiply that by another thousand
  and we get a <em>billion</em>.  One more multiplication gives us
  a <em>trillion</em> and so on.  I do not find this quite as neat as
  the long scale but it works.
</p>
<p>
  In effect, the prefix in the short scale corresponds to \( n \) of
  the integer \( 1000 \times 1000^n, \) where \( n \) is a positive
  integer.  Stated more succinctly, it represents \( n \) of \(
  10^{3(n + 1)}.  \)  So for example, if \( n = 5, \) then

  \[
    10^{3(n + 1)} = 10^{18},
  \]

  which is called a <em>quintillion</em> in the short scale.  The
  <em>quinti-</em> prefix still represents five but now it is tied to
  the number of additional thousands we multiplied to the first
  thousand.  It is not quite the elegant pattern I grew up with but
  this is the convention that dominates today.  In the world of
  technology, computing and finance, as well as in most
  English-speaking contexts, the short scale has prevailed.
</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion"></a></h2>
<p>
  Today, of course, I use only the short scale, because that is the
  convention adopted by the part of the world relevant to me.  I no
  longer use the long scale.  But it remains in memory, simply because
  I spent a large part of my early life with it.  It still lives in
  some corner of my heart, partly out of nostalgia and partly due to
  its elegance.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/million-times-million.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>ASCII PC</title>
<link>https://susam.net/pc.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">mpqts</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 15 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  An ASCII art depiction of a PC resting on a computer case, with a
  classic Model M keyboard placed in front.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/pc.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Associations</title>
<link>https://susam.net/assoc.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">rjffu</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A record of some associations between various numbers, sounds and
  colours that occur in my mind.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/assoc.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Equal Length Words</title>
<link>https://susam.net/eql.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">mzqnx</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  I have an unusual hobby.  I collect related words of equal length.
  This page lists my collection of related words that are all the same
  length and connected to one another in some way.  This particular
  fascination with related words of equal length originated as a
  result of computer programming.  While developing software, I often
  need to name variables, functions and other elements in a way that
  reflect the concepts I am working with.  Occasionally, I end up
  choosing names for related elements that are the same length, which
  becomes visually striking when these names align neatly in the text
  editor.
</p>
<p>
  Each group of words is presented in monospaced font so that the
  equal length of the words in each group is visually evident.  Blank
  spaces separate the groups.  The groups are sorted alphabetically
  according to the first word in each group.  The words in each group
  are sorted alphabetically too.
</p>

<pre>
allow
block
</pre>

<pre>
begin
pause
start
</pre>

<pre>
beverage
doughnut
</pre>

<pre>
black
white
</pre>

<pre>
bottom
middle
prefix
suffix
</pre>

<pre>
broadcast
syndicate
</pre>

<pre>
cancel
resume
</pre>

<pre>
client
server
</pre>

<pre>
correct
mistake
</pre>

<pre>
create
delete
remove
update
</pre>

<pre>
error
right
wrong
</pre>

<pre>
fail
okay
pass
</pre>

<pre>
failure
success
</pre>

<pre>
head
tail
</pre>

<pre>
index
value
</pre>

<pre>
inner
outer
</pre>

<pre>
input
radio
range
reset
</pre>

<pre>
look
peek
</pre>

<pre>
password
username
</pre>

<pre>
permit
forbid
</pre>

<pre>
pull
push
</pre>

<p>
  Note that some of the word groups here have been contributed by
  visitors to this page.  Please visit the
  <a href="comments/eql.html">comments section</a> to see the original
  contributions.
</p>

<p>
  In case you are wondering why I would need words like
  <code>beverage</code> or <code>doughnut</code> in computer
  programming, I use them in my little game called
  <a href="nq.html">Nerd Quiz</a> to display a doughnut or beverage symbol
  (<a href="https://github.com/susam/nq/blob/3.0.0/nq.html#L645-L646">view
  source</a>) depending on the points scored.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/eql.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Thurston's Paean</title>
<link>https://susam.net/thurstons-paean.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">iipnj</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  I recently came across a beautiful and thoughtful answer on
  MathOverflow by the late mathematician William Thurston.  A brief
  background about him from
  the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Thurston">Wikipedia
  article</a> about him:
</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>
    William Paul Thurston (October 30, 1946 &ndash; August 21, 2012)
    was an American mathematician.  He was a pioneer in the field of
    low-dimensional topology and was awarded the Fields Medal in 1982
    for his contributions to the study of 3-manifolds.
  </p>
  <p>
    Thurston was a professor of mathematics at Princeton University,
    University of California at Davis and Cornell University.  He was
    also a director of the Mathematical Sciences Research Institute.
  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>
  MathOverflow makes all answers posted to the website available under
  a Creative Commons licence.  In particular, all answers posted
  before 08 Apr 2011 (UTC) are available under the terms of the
  Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 2.5 Generic (CC BY-SA 2.5)
  licence.  Thurston wrote the answer I am about to share on 30 Oct
  2010.  Due to the licence terms, this post too is available under
  the terms of the same licence.
</p>
<p>
  Thurston posted his answer while replying to a MathOverflow
  question:
  <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/q/43690"><em>What's a
  mathematician to do?</em></a>.  The question enquires about how an
  ordinary mathematician can contribute to mathematics.  Thurston's
  answer
  from <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/a/44213">mathoverflow.net/a/44213</a>
  is reproduced below:
</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>
    It's not <em>mathematics</em> that you need to contribute to.
    It's deeper than that: how might you contribute to humanity, and
    even deeper, to the well-being of the world, by pursuing
    mathematics?  Such a question is not possible to answer in a
    purely intellectual way, because the effects of our actions go far
    beyond our understanding.  We are deeply social and deeply
    instinctual animals, so much that our well-being depends on many
    things we do that are hard to explain in an intellectual way.
    That is why you do well to follow your heart and your passion.
    Bare reason is likely to lead you astray.  None of us are smart
    and wise enough to figure it out intellectually.
  </p>
  <p>
    The product of mathematics is clarity and understanding.  Not
    theorems, by themselves.  Is there, for example any real reason
    that even such famous results as Fermat's Last Theorem, or the
    Poincar&eacute; conjecture, really matter?  Their real importance
    is not in their specific statements, but their role in challenging
    our understanding, presenting challenges that led to mathematical
    developments that increased our understanding.
  </p>
  <p>
    The world does not suffer from an oversupply of clarity and
    understanding (to put it mildly).  How and whether specific
    mathematics might lead to improving the world (whatever that
    means) is usually impossible to tease out, but mathematics
    collectively is extremely important.
  </p>
  <p>
    I think of mathematics as having a large component of psychology,
    because of its strong dependence on human minds.  Dehumanized
    mathematics would be more like computer code, which is very
    different.  Mathematical ideas, even simple ideas, are often hard
    to transplant from mind to mind.  There are many ideas in
    mathematics that may be hard to get, but are easy once you get
    them.  Because of this, mathematical understanding does not expand
    in a monotone direction.  Our understanding frequently
    deteriorates as well.  There are several obvious mechanisms of
    decay.  The experts in a subject retire and die, or simply move on
    to other subjects and forget.  Mathematics is commonly explained
    and recorded in symbolic and concrete forms that are easy to
    communicate, rather than in conceptual forms that are easy to
    understand once communicated.  Translation in the direction
    conceptual -&gt; concrete and symbolic is much easier than
    translation in the reverse direction, and symbolic forms often
    replaces the conceptual forms of understanding.  And mathematical
    conventions and taken-for-granted knowledge change, so older texts
    may become hard to understand.
  </p>
  <p>
    In short, mathematics only exists in a living community of
    mathematicians that spreads understanding and breaths life into
    ideas both old and new.  The real satisfaction from mathematics is
    in learning from others and sharing with others.  All of us have
    clear understanding of a few things and murky concepts of many
    more.  There is no way to run out of ideas in need of
    clarification.  The question of who is the first person to ever
    set foot on some square meter of land is really secondary.
    Revolutionary change does matter, but revolutions are few, and
    they are not self-sustaining --- they depend very heavily on the
    community of mathematicians.
  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>
  In the comments to the answer, one of the commenters
  was <a href="https://users.cs.utah.edu/~suresh/">Suresh
  Venkatasubramanian</a> who was a professor in the School of
  Computing at the University of Utah back then.  He
  is <a href="https://vivo.brown.edu/display/suresh">now</a> a
  professor of Computer Science and Data Science at Brown University.
  In his <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/43690/whats-a-mathematician-to-do/44213#comment271029_44213">comment</a>,
  Suresh proposed that this answer be called <em>Thurston's
  Paean</em>.  Here is his complete comment:
</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>
    This seems like an ideal counterpoint to Hardy's Lament.  I'm
    calling it Thurston's Paean :).  Seems poignant now that he has
    passed.
  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>
  Thurston's answer does appear to be a perfect complement to Hardy's
  lament in the 1940 essay <em>A Mathematician's Apology</em>.  While
  Hardy's lament is remarkably beautiful and introspective, it may
  also feel a little depressing at places.  Thurston's post on the
  other hand is full of hope and purpose that goes beyond the actual
  work of doing mathematics.  Indeed <em>Thurston's Paean</em> is a
  befitting title for his answer.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/thurstons-paean.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/mathematics.html">#mathematics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/quote.html">#quote</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>No Beam From the Eye</title>
<link>https://susam.net/no-beam-from-the-eye.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">ufrdz</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  <a href="https://mathshistory.st-andrews.ac.uk/HistTopics/Light_1/">Light
  Through the Ages: Ancient Greece to Maxwell</a> is a very
  fascinating article written by J J O'Connor and E F Robertson in
  2002 that takes us through a journey of how our understanding of
  light has evolved over the last few millennia.  Here is an excerpt
  from the article:
</p>
<blockquote>
  The biggest breakthrough in ancient times was made by al-Haytham
  around 1000 AD.  He argued that sight is due only to light entering
  the eye from an outside source and there is no beam from the eye
  itself.
</blockquote>
<p>
  The article then goes on to say:
</p>
<blockquote>
  He gave a number of arguments to support this claim, the most
  persuasive being the camera obscura, or pinhole camera.  Here light
  passes through a pinhole shining on a screen where an inverted image
  is observed.  Anyone visiting Edinburgh in Scotland should go to see
  the camera obscura there near the top of the Royal Mile and marvel
  at just how effective the camera obscura is in this enjoyable
  tourist attraction.
</blockquote>
<p>
  By the way, there is a camera obscura in the London too at Royal
  Observatory, Greenwich which offers pretty good view of the
  surroundings that includes Greenwich Park, the University of
  Greenwich, the River Thames, etc.  Here is a picture I took the last
  time I was there:
  <a href="https://susam.github.io/blob/pix/2023-12-camera-obscura.jpg">Camera Obscura, Royal Observatory, Greenwich</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/no-beam-from-the-eye.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Dark Night Skies</title>
<link>https://susam.net/dark-night-skies.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">jbrpx</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Having grown up in a small town in the 1990s, I was fortunate to
  experience pretty dark skies at night.  The combination of a clear
  night sky and a few books on amateur astronomy from our school's
  library fuelled my desire to understand the universe and our place
  in it.
</p>
<p>
  I made photocopies of two star charts (one for each hemisphere) from
  a book I found in our school library and began using the northern
  hemisphere chart to study the night sky.  The winter sky was and
  still is my favourite.  Spotting the easily recognisable Orion
  constellation and knowing that its second-brightest star, with its
  distinctly reddish hue, is a red supergiant that could explode at
  any moment was quite fascinating.
</p>
<p>
  The 1990s were also a great time to grow up as an astronomy
  enthusiast.  Two bright comets graced our skies in 1996 and 1997.
  First, Comet Hyakutake appeared in March 1996, followed by Comet
  Hale-Bopp, which became spectacularly bright in April 1997.
</p>
<p>
  Now, 23 years later, as an adult living in a severely light-polluted
  city, the recent Geminids meteor shower was rather disappointing.
  After midnight, my wife and I stepped outside to watch it.  Under a
  truly dark sky, we could have seen two to four meteors streaking
  across the sky every minute.  But instead, the entire sky glowed
  orange and we managed to spot only one or two meteors every five to
  ten minutes.
</p>
<p>
  I think it's very unfortunate that children growing up in cities
  today don't have the opportunity to experience the beauty of the
  night sky the way I did during my childhood.  A clear, dark night
  sky can be a powerful source of inspiration and wonder for young
  minds.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/dark-night-skies.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Microcentury</title>
<link>https://susam.net/microcentury.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">upszl</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h2 id="optimal-lecture-time">Optimal Lecture Time<a href="#optimal-lecture-time"></a></h2>
<p>
  I recently found this interesting paragraph from an article titled
  <a href="https://www.ams.org/notices/199701/comm-rota.pdf">Ten
  Lessons I Wish I Had Been Taught</a> that is based on a talk
  presented by Gian-Carlo Rota in Apr 1996:
</p>
<blockquote>
  Running overtime is the one unforgivable error a lecturer can make.
  After fifty minutes (one microcentury as von Neumann used to say)
  everybody's attention will turn elsewhere even if we are trying to
  prove the Riemann hypothesis.  One minute overtime can destroy the
  best of lectures.
</blockquote>
<p>
  That's fine advice.  In fact, the whole article is full of good
  advice like this.  Although it was written primarily for
  mathematicians, a lot of what is said in the article applies quite
  well to professionals in other fields too.
</p>
<p>
  The excerpt I have quoted above got me thinking about exactly how
  long a microcentury is.  It couldn't be exactly 50 minutes, could
  it?
</p>
<h2 id="wiktionary-on-microcentury">Wiktionary on Microcentury<a href="#wiktionary-on-microcentury"></a></h2>
<p>
  The English Wiktionary entry for
  <a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/microcentury">microcentury</a>
  (as of
  <a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/w/index.php?title=microcentury&amp;oldid=59316064">revision
  59316064</a> on 7 May 2020) mentions:
</p>
<blockquote>
  A time period of a millionth of a century, equal to 52 minutes and
  34 seconds.
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
  Not a standard unit of measurement and used mostly humorously to
  denote the maximum length of a lecture.
</blockquote>
<p>
  This looks incorrect to me.  This is based on the oversimplified
  assumption that a century contains 36500 days, that is, it assumes
  that a century is a span of 100 years where each year has exactly
  365 days.  If a century were to have exactly 36500 days, then indeed
  it would have 3&#8239;153&#8239;600&#8239;000 seconds and one
  millionth of it would be 3153.6 seconds which is equivalent to 52
  minutes 33.6 seconds.  This looks consistent with the Wiktionary
  entry.  However, an actual century on the calendar does not have
  exactly 36500 days.  Some years are leap years, so the actual number
  of days in a century is more than that.
</p>
<h2 id="assumptions">Assumptions<a href="#assumptions"></a></h2>
<p>
  Let us find out how long a microcentury is as accurately as
  possible.  We will count the leap years.  We will ignore leap
  seconds because they are irregularly spaced and unpredictable.  We
  will also ignore the following gap between 2 Sep 1752 and 14 Sep
  1752 when the British Empire switched from the Julian calendar to
  the Gregorian calendar:
</p>
<pre>
<samp>$ <kbd>cal 9 1752</kbd>
   September 1752
Su Mo Tu We Th Fr Sa
       1  2 14 15 16
17 18 19 20 21 22 23
24 25 26 27 28 29 30</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  The above output can be obtained by running the <code>cal</code>
  command as shown above on a Unix or Linux system.  Ignoring this gap
  is equivalent to assuming that we are working with the Gregorian
  calender since the year 1 AD.
</p>
<p>
  We will call a year that is a multiple of 100 to be a <em>centurial
  year</em>.  Further, we will not debate whether a centurial year
  begins a new century or ends one, that is, we don't care whether the
  current century runs from 2001 to 2100 or if it runs from 2000 to
  2099.  The computation presented in the next section works equally
  well for any span of 100 years.
</p>
<h2 id="computation">Computation<a href="#computation"></a></h2>
<p>
  Any span of 100 years contains exactly one centurial year, that is,
  a year that is a multiple of 100.  A centurial year is a leap
  year <em>if and only if</em> it is also a multiple of 400.  Apart
  from the centurial year, a century contains 24 occurrences of years
  that are multiples of 4 and these are all leap years.  From these
  facts, we can conclude that a span of 100 years contains:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    Exactly 25 leap years if the centurial year within the span is a
    multiple of 400.
  </li>
  <li>
    Exactly 24 leap years, otherwise.
  </li>
</ul>
<p>
  Therefore a century has either 36524 days or 36525 days.  In other
  words, a century has either 3&#8239;155&#8239;673&#8239;600 seconds
  or 3&#8239;155&#8239;760&#8239;000 seconds.  Here is a quick
  demonstration of this with a simple Python program:
</p>
<pre>
<code>#!/usr/bin/env python3

import datetime

for year in range(1, 2400, 100):
    delta = datetime.date(year + 100, 1, 1) - datetime.date(year, 1, 1)
    print('{:04}-{:04}: {} d = {} s'
          .format(year, year + 99, delta.days, delta.total_seconds()))</code>
</pre>
<p>
  Here is the output of this program:
</p>
<pre>
<samp>0001-0100: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
0101-0200: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
0201-0300: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
0301-0400: 36525 d = 3155760000.0 s
0401-0500: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
0501-0600: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
0601-0700: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
0701-0800: 36525 d = 3155760000.0 s
0801-0900: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
0901-1000: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
1001-1100: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
1101-1200: 36525 d = 3155760000.0 s
1201-1300: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
1301-1400: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
1401-1500: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
1501-1600: 36525 d = 3155760000.0 s
1601-1700: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
1701-1800: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
1801-1900: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
1901-2000: 36525 d = 3155760000.0 s
2001-2100: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
2101-2200: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
2201-2300: 36524 d = 3155673600.0 s
2301-2400: 36525 d = 3155760000.0 s</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  Thus one millionth of a century has 3155.6736 or 3155.7600 seconds,
  that is 52 minutes 35.6736 seconds or 52 minutes 35.7600 seconds.
</p>
<h2 id="Conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#Conclusion"></a></h2>
<p>
  If we round off the number of seconds in a microcentury to one
  decimal place, we can say that a microcentury has 52 minutes 35.7
  seconds.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/microcentury.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/quote.html">#quote</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Global Palindrome Day</title>
<link>https://susam.net/global-palindrome-day.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">lqecc</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h2 id="date-formats">Date Formats<a href="#date-formats"></a></h2>
<p>
  There are three popular date formats followed worldwide: big-endian,
  little-endian and middle-endian.  Here is how today's date looks
  like in these formats if the year is written out in full:
</p>
<table class="grid center">
  <tr>
    <th>Endianness</th>
    <th>Format</th>
    <th>Date</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Big-endian</td>
    <td>YYYY-MM-DD</td>
    <td>2020-02-02</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Little-endian</td>
    <td>DD-MM-YYYY</td>
    <td>02-02-2020</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>Middle-endian</td>
    <td>MM-DD-YYYY</td>
    <td>02-02-2020</td>
  </tr>
</table>
<p>
  The ISO 8601 standard specifies the big-endian date format.  The
  big-endian format is popular in Canada, China, Japan, Lithuania,
  etc.  The little-endian format is used by the majority of the world
  including countries like Brazil, Egypt, Germany, India, Italy,
  United Kingdom, etc.  The middle-endian date format is primarily
  used in the Philippines and the United States.
</p>
<p>
  The preferred choice of delimiter between the date components (day,
  month and year) varies from country to country.  In this post, we
  use hyphen (i.e. "-") as the delimiter.
</p>
<h2 id="palindromes">Palindromes<a href="#palindromes"></a></h2>
<p>
  Today's date is a palindrome in all three date formats, i.e. it
  reads the same backward as forward in all three formats.  It
  is <em>globally palindromic</em>.  Note that we ignore the hyphens
  or any other delimiters while deciding if a date is palindrome or
  not.  In fact, in general, punctuation, capitalisation and spaces
  are usually ignored while deciding if a given text is palindrome or
  not.
</p>
<p>
  Let me define <em>global palindrome day</em> to be a day when its
  date is a palindrome in all three date formats (YYYY-MM-DD,
  DD-MM-YYYY and MM-DD-YYYY).  Then today is a global palindrome day!
</p>
<p>
  There are only eleven such global palindrome days between the years
  1000 and 9999.  Here is a list that enumerates all of them:
</p>
<p style="font-family: monospace,monospace" class="textcenter">
1010-01-01<br>
1111-11-11<br>
2020-02-02<br>
2121-12-12<br>
3030-03-03<br>
4040-04-04<br>
5050-05-05<br>
6060-06-06<br>
7070-07-07<br>
8080-08-08<br>
9090-09-09<br>
</p>
<p>
  The previous global palindrome day was over 908 years ago!  The next
  such day is over 101 years away!
</p>
<p>
  Today is special in another way.  It is day 33 (a palindrome) of the
  current year and 333 (also a palindrome) days remain in the year.
</p>
<h2 id="ambigrams">Ambigrams<a href="#ambigrams"></a></h2>
<p>
  As a bonus, today is also a <em>global strobogrammatic day</em> when
  viewed on a seven-segment display, i.e. for all three date formats,
  today's date when shown, without the delimiters, on a seven-segment
  display appears the same when rotated by 180&deg;.  A
  strobogrammatic sequence of digits like this is also a type of
  ambigram.  Here is how today's date looks in YYYYMMDD, DDMMYYYY and
  MMDDYYYY formats on a seven-segment display:
</p>
<!-- These images were generated using http://avtanski.net/projects/lcd/ -->
<figure class="soft textcenter">
  <img style="height: 2em"
       src="files/blog/palindrome-day-1.png"
       alt="Date 2020-20-20 (YYYY-MM-DD) shown in a seven-segment display">
  <br>
  <img style="height: 2em"
       src="files/blog/palindrome-day-2.png"
       alt="Date 02-02-2020 (DD-MM-YYYY) shown in a seven-segment display">
  <br>
  <img style="height: 2em"
       src="files/blog/palindrome-day-2.png"
       alt="Date 02-02-2020 (MM-DD-YYYY) shown in a seven-segment display">
</figure>
<p>
  In the list of global palindrome days provided in the previous
  section, six of the eleven days are global strobogrammatic days too.
  Only the ones that belong to the years 3030, 4040, 6060, 7070 and
  9090 are not strobogrammatic on a seven-segment display; the rest
  all are.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/global-palindrome-day.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Good Blessings</title>
<link>https://susam.net/good-blessings.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">tbvps</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Back in 2009, I had completed a year working for RSA Security.  I
  was then looking for more intellectually stimulating work where I
  could work on projects involving mathematics and algorithms.  While
  I had talked to senior leaders of the organisation about my
  aspirations, nothing concrete had materialised for several weeks.
  Then something interesting happened.  One fine Monday morning, as I
  walked into the office and began to settle at my desk, the head of
  our research and development division came to my desk looking for
  me.  He said, "Burt is here.  He wants to talk to you."
</p>
<p>
  There was no Burt in that office as far as I knew, so I became a
  little confused.  I was led into a conference room where I could
  meet him.  Mildly disoriented, I opened the conference room door.
  Then I saw Burt, the person I was about to meet.  As soon as I saw
  him, I immediately recognised who he was.  He was Dr Burt Kaliski,
  the Chief Scientist of RSA Laboratories.  He had flown in that
  morning to meet certain teams in our office.  During his visit, he
  had carved out some time from his schedule to meet me.
</p>
<p>
  I had never met or talked to Dr Kaliski before.  But I was very well
  aware of his work and his accomplishments many years before joining
  RSA.  At a previous job, while implementing digital signatures for a
  banking product, I had spent a lot of time reading the RFCs for
  <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc3447">PKCS #1</a>,
  <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2898">PKCS #5</a> and
  <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2315">PKCS #7</a>,
  which were all authored by Dr Kaliski.  It was an honour to
  meet the person whose work had taught me a lot and helped me begin
  my career as a software developer in the area of information
  security.
</p>
<p>
  He began the meeting by explaining that he happened to learn about
  my wish to work on more challenging projects.  He enquired about the
  type of projects I desired to work on.  He listened to my thoughts
  patiently.  He offered some advice and then wished me the best for
  my future.  Little did I know back then that the short 30 minute
  interaction I had with him would end up changing the trajectory of
  my career.
</p>
<p>
  Soon after the meeting, I followed his advice, talked to several
  teams, found out what they were working on and finally decided to
  join a team that worked on a network security product.  It turned
  out to be the best decision of my career!  While working on that
  product, I learnt to design and implement efficient algorithms for
  petabytes of data.  Some parts of the project relied heavily on
  probability theory, so it was a joy to be able to take a subject
  that was a hobby until then and apply it to solve actual real-world
  problems.  Working on that product offered the intellectual
  challenges that my younger self yearned for back then.  I think the
  most interesting experience there was my work on parser generators.
  It involved writing algorithms in C++ to parse a formally specified
  language which in turn was used to generate in-memory FSMs to parse
  and analyse network packets and events.  Parsing one language and
  generating in-memory parsers for another language proved to be
  intellectually demanding as well as satisfying.  I have fond
  memories of my time there working on parser generators alongside
  remarkably skilled engineers from whom I learnt a lot.
</p>
<p>
  All of that happened seven years ago.  A couple of months ago, while
  recounting that 30 minute meeting with Dr Kaliski, I could not
  recall if I had ever thanked him properly for his kindness and
  generosity.  Seven years ago, there was no compelling reason for him
  to meet me.  I was then just a regular software engineer who was
  hired into the company a year ago.  We had never talked before.  But
  he took the time to offer me help, suggestions and advice on how I
  could make a good career.  Unsure if I had expressed my gratitude to
  him for how he helped me sculpt my career, I wrote to him recently
  to thank him and explain how that one meeting had a large and
  positive impact on my life.
</p>
<p>
  Dr Kaliski replied a few days later and he expressed his happiness
  to know that the steps I took in the subsequent years worked out
  well for me.  Before ending his message, he wrote a little
  heart-warming note that I am going to remember forever.  Quoting it
  verbatim here:
</p>
<blockquote>
  &ldquo;One of my goals is to be able to provide encouragement to
  others who are developing their careers, just as others have
  invested in mine, passing good blessings from one generation to
  another.&rdquo;
</blockquote>
<!-- Quote from 11 Oct 2016 03:50  UTC -->
<p>
  Thank you, Burt!  I will do likewise.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/good-blessings.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/quote.html">#quote</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Illiteracy and Digital Weighing Scale</title>
<link>https://susam.net/illiteracy-and-digital-weighing-scale.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">wrcsp</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Here is a real life problem from a silica bricks factory in a small
  industrial town in India.  There are illiterate workers who cannot
  identify decimal digits.  The management team of the factory is
  trying to figure if there is a way for these workers to operate a
  digital weighing scale to fill buckets with a certain mass of a
  given material.  For example, they may be asked to fill 5.3&nbsp;kg
  of a certain material in the bucket, i.e. decimal fractions are
  involved.
</p>
<p>
  If the factory were using a beam balance, this would have been an
  easy problem to solve.  The workers could then place the required
  weight in one pan and keep pouring the material in the other pan
  until the beam appears to be balanced.
</p>
<p>
  However this factory uses a digital weighing scale which involves
  recognising decimal digits to read the measurement.  What do you
  think is the easiest way to train the workers to do their job
  without having to teach them how to count?
</p>
<p>
  I have a solution in mind which would involve configuring the
  digital weighing scale in a certain way for every measurement the
  workers have to make.  I will propose this solution to the
  management team of the factory.  But I would like to know any
  suggestions you have and take them into account as well before
  proposing my solution.  I will also share the solution I have in
  mind after learning about your suggestions.
</p>
<hr>
<p>
  <strong>Update on 08&nbsp;July&nbsp;2010:</strong> Prunthaban has
  suggested a solution in the
  <a href="comments/illiteracy-and-digital-weighing-scale.html#5">comments</a>
  section which is pretty much what I had in mind too.  I will propose
  this solution to the factory.  The solution works like this: Say the
  worker has to fill 5.3 kg of a certain material into the bucket.  A
  literate supervisor first places 5.3&nbsp;kg of that material on the
  weighing scale.  The instrument now shows "5.3&nbsp;kg" on its
  display.  Now the remainder of the solution assumes that the digital
  weighing balance has a calibration wheel to calibrate the
  instrument.  The supervisor turns the calibration wheel until the
  display shows "0.0"&nbsp;kg while the 5.3&nbsp;kg of material is
  still placed on it.  Now the material is removed from the balance and
  the display shows "-5.3&nbsp;kg".  Now all a worker needs to do is
  pour the given material on this calibrated balance until the display
  shows "0.0&nbsp;kg".  As long as the workers can be taught to
  recognise the digit "0", this solution should work fine.
</p>
<hr>
<p>
  <strong>Update on 05&nbsp;Aug&nbsp;2010:</strong> The above solution
  was successfully implemented in OCL India Limited, the silica bricks
  factory where this problem was faced.  The digital weighing balance
  involved in the problem indeed had a calibration wheel, so the above
  solution worked for them.  Thank you, Prunthaban and others who
  participated in this discussion.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/illiteracy-and-digital-weighing-scale.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/puzzle.html">#puzzle</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Laws of Correction</title>
<link>https://susam.net/laws-of-correction.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">klmqy</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<h2 id="mckean-law">McKean's Law<a href="#mckean-law"></a></h2>
<blockquote>
  Any correction of the speech or writing of others will contain at
  least one grammatical, spelling, or typographical error.
</blockquote>

<h2 id="skitt-law">Skitt's Law<a href="#skitt-law"></a></h2>
<blockquote>
  Any post correcting an error in another post will contain at least
  one error itself.
</blockquote>

<h2 id="muphry-law">Muphry's Law<a href="#muphry-law"></a></h2>
<blockquote>
  If you write anything criticising editing or proofreading, there
  will be a fault of some kind in what you have written.
</blockquote>

<h2 id="hartman-law">Hartman's Law of Prescriptivist Retaliation<a href="#hartman-law"></a></h2>
<blockquote>
  Any article or statement about correct grammar, punctuation, or
  spelling is bound to contain at least one eror.
</blockquote>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/laws-of-correction.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>A Kid Who Could Read My Mind</title>
<link>https://susam.net/a-kid-who-could-read-my-mind.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">vmlcw</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Last night, I found myself in the midst of a peculiar group of
  strangers.  Among them was a mysterious kid who made an astonishing
  claim&mdash;he possessed the ability to read minds.  With utter
  disbelief, I approached him.  He covered both my ears with his palms
  and asked me to think of something.  I thought of the number 5 and
  he immediately said aloud, '5'.  I was astonished.  How could the
  kid read my mind?  To ensure that he did not simply get lucky, I
  thought of another number, 7.  Again, he immediately declared, '7'.
  I thought of a few more numbers and he correctly announced all the
  numbers.  I was completely bewildered.  The people around were
  equally perplexed.  They felt that both of us were working together
  to hoodwink others.  An old man in the group who seemed intrigued by
  all this approached us and asked us to perform more experiments in a
  structured manner.  He proposed that the numbers be generated using
  a pseudorandom number generator of a scientific calculator and
  written down on a paper.  He asked me to silently read the numbers
  on each paper, then think of those numbers and see whether the kid
  could then read my mind.
</p>
<p>
  While he was preparing a list of random numbers, I was trying to
  understand how on earth the kid could be reading my mind.  He could
  not be have got lucky every single time.  He seemed to have direct
  access to my mind.  However that would be a miracle, maybe not in
  future, but it is a miracle at least today in the year 2009.  I kept
  thinking, coming up with various hypotheses and discarding them.  By
  sheer luck, I thought of a contraption involving one random number
  generator (RNG) connected to two displays.  In this apparatus, the
  output of the RNG appeared immediately on the first display, but
  only after a delay of 1 second on the second display.  Now it would
  seem that the first display was predicting the output of the second
  display.  I continued thinking more in that direction.  What could
  possibly be the source of the thoughts that was accessible to both?
</p>
<p>
  After a little thought, it occurred to me that it could be my own
  mind.  Probably the kid and the people I could see were simply
  creations of my mind.  Perhaps, I was asleep and dreaming.  I wanted
  to test the hypothesis.  If it was only a dream and my mind was
  creating all the experience, I should have been able to read the
  minds of others.  I had no clue how the experience of reading
  others' minds would feel like but I went ahead to test the
  hypothesis.  I asked another person to be a volunteer.  He agreed.
  I covered his ears with my palms and asked him to think of a number
  and suddenly the number "17" echoed in my mind.  I was thrilled.  I
  asked him whether "17" was the number.  He confirmed that it was
  indeed the number he had thought of.
</p>
<p>
  Unfortunately, I could not stay in this state of
  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lucid_dream">lucid dream</a>
  for long.  I woke up soon after realising that I was in a lucid
  dream.  If you find lucid dreaming intriguing I recommend
  <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0243017/">Waking Life</a> to
  you, a very thought provoking movie that shows the experience of a
  man trapped in a persistent lucid dream state.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/a-kid-who-could-read-my-mind.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>ADAC and HE Puzzles from GEB</title>
<link>https://susam.net/adac-and-he-puzzles-from-geb.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">yjsjz</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  I have been reading
  <em><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6del,_Escher,_Bach"
  class="title">G&ouml;del, Escher, Bach: An Eternal Golden
  Braid</a></em> by Douglas R. Hofstadter for a few weeks.  The book
  follows an interesting format of alternating between chapters and
  dialogues between imaginary charaters.  In the words of the author:
</p>
<blockquote>
  The long and the short of it is that I eventually decided - but this
  took many months - that the optimal structure would be a strict
  alternation between chapters and dialogues.  Once that was clear,
  then I had the joyous task of trying to pinpoint the most crucial
  ideas that I wanted to get across to my readers and then somehow
  embodying them in both the form and the content of fanciful, often
  punning dialogues between Achilles and the Tortoise (plus a few new
  friends).
</blockquote>
<p>
  After the second chapter (Chapter II: Meaning and Form in
  Mathematics) there is a dialogue between Achilles and the Tortoise
  on telephone.  The title of the dialogue is <em>Sonata for
  Unaccompanied Achilles</em>.  The text shows the transcript of only
  one end of the call, only what Achilles speaks.  The Tortoise is at
  the far end of the call.  The sentences spoken by the Tortoise at
  the other end are not present in the text.  This makes the reading
  experience very interesting as we keep guessing about what is going
  on at the other end.
</p>
<p>
  It starts in this manner:
</p>
<blockquote>
  <em>Achilles:</em> Hello, this is Achilles.<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> Oh, hello, Mr. T. How are you?<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> A torticollis?  Oh, I'm sorry to hear it.  Do you
  have any idea what caused it?
</blockquote>
<p>
  As the dialogue proceeds, they share a few puzzles.  Here is the
  first one from the Tortoise.
</p>
<blockquote>
  <em>Achilles:</em> A word with the letters 'A', 'D', 'A', 'C'
  consecutively inside it &hellip; Hmm &hellip; What about
  "abracadabra"?<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> True, "ADAC" occurs backwards, not forwards, in
  that word.<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> Hours and hours?  It sounds like I'm in for a
  long puzzle, then.  Where did you hear this infernal riddle?
</blockquote>
<p>
  Here is the second puzzle from Achilles:
</p>
<blockquote>
  <em>Achilles:</em> Say, I once heard a word puzzle a little bit like
  this one.  Do you want to hear it?  Or would it just drive you
  further into distraction?<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> I agree - can't do any harm.  Here it is: What's
  a word that begins with the letters "HE" and also ends with
  "HE"?<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> Very ingenious - but that's almost cheating.
  It's certainly not what I meant!<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> Of course you're right - it fulfills the
  conditions, but it's a sort of "degenerate" solution.  There's
  another solution which I had in mind.<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> That's exactly it!  How did you come up with it
  so fast?<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> So here's a case where having a headache actually
  might have helped you, rather than hindering you.  Excellent!  But
  I'm still in the dark on your "ADAC" puzzle.
</blockquote>
<p>
  <em>If you want to think about these puzzles, this is a good time to
  pause and think about them.  There are spoilers ahead.</em>
</p>
<p>
  It did not take much time for me to solve the puzzle because I
  cheated with the word list file available on Linux distributions.
  Here is what I found with my Debian 5.0 (lenny) system:
</p>
<pre>
<samp>$ <kbd>grep 'adac' /usr/share/dict/words</kbd>
headache
headache's
headaches
$ <kbd>grep '^he.*he$' /usr/share/dict/words</kbd>
headache
heartache</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  The answers to both puzzles seem to be "HEADACHE".  Take another
  look at the last sentence in the dialogue above.  It makes sense now
  as Achilles says that having a <em>headache</em> might have helped
  the Tortoise.
</p>
<p>
  Later in the dialogue the Tortoise offers <em>figure</em> and
  <em>ground</em> as hints to the "ADAC" puzzle.
</p>
<blockquote>
  <em>Achilles:</em> Well, normally I don't like hints, but all right.
  What's your hint?<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> I don't know what you mean by "figure" and
  "ground" in this case.<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> Certainly I know Mosaic II!  I know ALL of
  Escher's works.  After all, he's my favorite artist.  In any case,
  I've got a print of Mosaic II hanging on my wall, in plain view from
  here.<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> Yes, I see all the black animals.<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> Yes, I also see how their "negative" space -
  what's left out - defines the white animals.<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> So THAT's what you mean by "figure" and "ground".
  But what does that have to do with the "ADAC" puzzle?<br>
  <em>Achilles:</em> Oh, this is too tricky to me.  I think I'M
  starting to get a headache.
</blockquote>
<p>
  The famous painting discussed in the dialogue can be found
  here: <a href="https://www.wikiart.org/en/m-c-escher/mosaic-ii">https://www.wikiart.org/en/m-c-escher/mosaic-ii</a>.
  We can see how the black animals form the <em>figure</em> (the
  positive space) and how the background or <em>ground</em> (the
  negative space) beautifully fits all the white animals.
</p>
<p>
  The <em>figure</em> and <em>ground</em> in hints make sense now.
  The first puzzle has "ADAC" in the question.  Let us consider "ADAC"
  as the figure or the positive space.  If we remove "ADAC" from
  "HEADACHE", we are left with the ground or negative space, which
  consists of "HE" and "HE" at the beginning and the end of the word.
  The <em>figure</em> is used in the first puzzle and
  the <em>ground</em> is used in the second puzzle.
</p>
<p>
  By the way, what is the first answer from the Tortoise that Achilles
  finds very ingenious but degenerate?  I believe, it is "HE" as this
  word both begins and ends with "HE".
</p>
<p>
  The funny thing about this dialogue is that both of them asked two
  puzzles to each other without knowing that the answers to them were
  the same.  A similar thing happened to me when a colleague of mine
  and I challenged each other with combinatorics puzzles.  See this
  blog post for the story:
  <a href="combinatorics-coincidence.html">Combinatorics Coincidence</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/adac-and-he-puzzles-from-geb.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/book.html">#book</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/puzzle.html">#puzzle</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>
