<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

<channel>
<title>Susam's Music Pages</title>
<link>https://susam.net/tag/music.html</link>
<atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="https://susam.net/tag/music-full.xml"/>
<description>Feed for Susam's Music Pages</description>

<item>
<title>Twinkle Twinkle Little Star</title>
<link>https://susam.net/music/twinkle-twinkle-little-star.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">lmouw</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  This is a short musical piece consisting of 56 measures.  It is 1
  minute 52 seconds long.  The music is composed of four tracks.
</p>
<div class="widget">
  <audio controls preload="none" src="../files/music/twinkle-twinkle-little-star/twinkle-twinkle-little-star.mp3"></audio>
  <div>
    <a href="../files/music/twinkle-twinkle-little-star/twinkle-twinkle-little-star.mp3">MP3</a>
    <a href="../files/music/twinkle-twinkle-little-star/twinkle-twinkle-little-star.pdf">Score</a>
    <a href="../files/music/twinkle-twinkle-little-star/twinkle-twinkle-little-star.ly">Lilypond</a>
    <a href="../music/twinkle-twinkle-little-star.html">Details</a>
  </div>
</div>

<p>
  The four tracks in this piece are: grand piano, slow strings, xenon
  pad and music box.
</p>
<p>
  This arrangement is based on the popular melody of the nursery rhyme
  called <em>Twinkle, twinkle, little star</em>.  The melody is played
  with the treble notes of the piano.  I wrote the bass notes for the
  piano and strings.  The high notes for the pad and music box bring
  in the emotions of love and happiness.  I recorded this after about
  two hours of practice.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/music/twinkle-twinkle-little-star.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/music.html">#music</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Flowers</title>
<link>https://susam.net/music/flowers.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">hcchk</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  This is my third attempt at composing music.  I composed, played and
  recorded it almost a year before publishing it.  It took about a
  year to publish it because it took me time to write the sheet music.
</p>
<p>
  This piece consists of 161 measures.  It is approximately 3 minutes
  8 seconds long.
</p>
<div class="widget">
  <audio controls preload="none" src="../files/music/flowers/flowers.mp3"></audio>
  <div>
    <a href="../files/music/flowers/flowers.mp3">MP3</a>
    <a href="../files/music/flowers/flowers.pdf">Score</a>
    <a href="../files/music/flowers/flowers.ly">Lilypond</a>
    <a href="../music/flowers.html">Details</a>
  </div>
</div>

<p>
  Most of the music emerged naturally from my mind while thinking
  about roadside fields with wild plants and flowers.  Some of the
  bass notes did not come out naturally and I decided them, quite
  artificially, to fill the music with a pleasant and peaceful mood.
  It took me a couple of days to compose this.  I played and recorded
  this after a day of practice.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/music/flowers.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/music.html">#music</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Waiting for Dawn</title>
<link>https://susam.net/music/waiting-for-dawn.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">arzla</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 24 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  This is my second attempt at composing music.  This piece consists
  of 147 measures.  It is approximately 4 minutes 28 seconds long.
</p>
<div class="widget">
  <audio controls preload="none" src="../files/music/waiting-for-dawn/waiting-for-dawn.mp3"></audio>
  <div>
    <a href="../files/music/waiting-for-dawn/waiting-for-dawn.mp3">MP3</a>
    <a href="../files/music/waiting-for-dawn/waiting-for-dawn.pdf">Score</a>
    <a href="../files/music/waiting-for-dawn/waiting-for-dawn.ly">Lilypond</a>
    <a href="../music/waiting-for-dawn.html">Details</a>
  </div>
</div>

<p>
  The mental image I had while composing this piece was that of a guy,
  sitting alone in a dark night, waiting for the night to pass and the
  dawn to arrive.  0:00&ndash;1:30 of the piece represents the night.
  1:30&ndash;2:15 is the time when the darkness starts fading away and
  the sky turns red.  Everything after 2:15 is about welcoming and
  enjoying the dawn.
</p>
<p>
  For me this mental image doesn't just represent a particular night
  passing away due to the rotation of our planet.  It represents how
  we should handle tough times, heartbreaks, loss, etc. in our
  personal lives.  We should remain calm, wait for tough times to pass
  and good times to come and when the bad times give way to good times
  again, we should welcome and enjoy the good times.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/music/waiting-for-dawn.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/music.html">#music</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>A Few Notes</title>
<link>https://susam.net/music/a-few-notes.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nesjc</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  This is a very short piece I composed in December 2009 when I began
  learning to play musical keyboard.  After about 3 hours of music
  lessons, I came up with a very simple single track piece.  In the
  next few days, I added more tracks to the piece which resulted in
  this piece.
</p>
<p>
  The composition is very short and simple.  It consists of 29
  measures.  The duration of this piece is 53 seconds approximately.
  It is composed of 5 tracks.  I played and recorded the 5 tracks
  separately on my Yamaha keyboard.  The tracks are: piano (hypetine),
  harp, strings, nylon guitar and standard percussion kit.
</p>
<p>
  The music was recorded as an MP3 file with
  <a href="http://audacity.sourceforge.net/">Audacity</a> after
  connecting the musical keyboard's output jack to the laptop's
  line-in jack using a cable with 3.5 mm stereo plug at both ends.  A
  3.5 mm stereo jack to 6.35 mm stereo adapter was used to connect the
  3.5 mm (approximately &#x215b;") stereo plug to the keyboard's 6.35
  mm (&frac14;") stereo jack.
</p>
<div class="widget">
  <audio controls preload="none" src="../files/music/a-few-notes/a-few-notes.mp3"></audio>
  <div>
    <a href="../files/music/a-few-notes/a-few-notes.mp3">MP3</a>
    <a href="../files/music/a-few-notes/a-few-notes.pdf">Score</a>
    <a href="../files/music/a-few-notes/a-few-notes.ly">Lilypond</a>
    <a href="../music/a-few-notes.html">Details</a>
  </div>
</div>

<p>
  Most of the piece was written as a learning exercise for myself.
  The 4th track containing arpeggios from nylon guitar is meant to
  play hide and seek with the main track and sound happy.
</p>
<p>
  The 2nd (harp) and 5th (percussion) tracks are missing from the
  sheet music because I couldn't find a way to add a track for harp in
  LilyPond and I don't know the music notation for percussion kit.
  I'm not very good at music notation.  So, there may be notation
  errors in the sheet music but it is good enough to remind me the
  notes of this piece in case I ever forget them.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/music/a-few-notes.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/music.html">#music</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>
