<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

<channel>
<title>Susam's Web Pages</title>
<link>https://susam.net/tag/web.html</link>
<atom:link rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" href="https://susam.net/tag/web-full.xml"/>
<description>Feed for Susam's Web Pages</description>

<item>
<title>Nerd Quiz #3</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/nq/3.0.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqthr</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Nerd Quiz #3 is the third release of Nerd Quiz, a single-page HTML
  application that invites you to test your nerd level through a short
  quiz.  Each question is inspired by everyday moments of reading,
  writing, thinking, learning and exploring.
</p>
<p>
  This release introduces five new questions drawn from a range of
  topics, including computing history, graph theory and Unix.
  Visit <a href="../../../nq.html#3">Nerd Quiz</a> to try the quiz.
</p>
<p>
  A community discussion page is available at
  <a href="../../../comments/nq.html">Discuss Nerd Quiz</a>.  You are
  very welcome to share your score or discuss the questions there.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/nq/3.0.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/game.html">#game</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Fizz Buzz in CSS</title>
<link>https://susam.net/fizz-buzz-in-css.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">fzcps</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  How many CSS selectors and declarations do we need to produce the
  Fizz Buzz sequence?  Of course we could do this with no CSS at all
  simply by placing the entire sequence as text in the HTML body.  So
  to make the problem precise as well as to keep it interesting, we
  require that all text that appears in the Fizz Buzz sequence comes
  directly from the CSS.  Placing any part of the output numbers or
  words outside the stylesheet is not allowed.  JavaScript is not
  allowed either.  With these constraints, I think we need at least
  four CSS selectors along with four declarations to solve this
  puzzle, as shown below:
</p>
<pre>
<code>li { counter-increment: n }
li:not(:nth-child(5n))::before { content: counter(n) }
li:nth-child(3n)::before { content: "Fizz" }
li:nth-child(5n)::after { content: "Buzz" }</code>
</pre>
<p>
  Here is a complete working example:
  <a href="css-fizz-buzz.html">css-fizz-buzz.html</a>.
</p>
<p>
  The above solution contains four CSS rules with one selector and one
  declaration in each rule.  For example,
  <code>li { counter-increment: n }</code> is one rule consisting of
  the selector <code>li</code> and the declaration
  <code>counter-increment: n</code>.
</p>
<p>
  Seasoned code golfers looking for a challenge can probably shrink
  this solution further.  A common trick to solve this problem is to
  use an ordered list (<code>&lt;ol&gt;</code>) which provides the
  integers in the form of list markers automatically, thereby
  eliminating the need to maintain a counter in the stylesheet.
  However, this violates the requirement set out in the introduction.
  We want every integer to be produced directly by the stylesheet.
  Treating the integers in the list markers as part of the output
  sequence breaks this rule.  Not to mention the output looks untidy
  because of the unnecessary dot after each marker and also because
  the numbers and words appear misaligned.  See an example of that
  trick here:
  <a href="code/web/css-fizz-buzz-ol.html">css-fizz-buzz-ol.html</a>.
  Correcting the misaligned output calls for extra code that cancels
  out the number of declarations saved.  In any case, the requirement
  that all integers of the output must come directly from the
  stylesheet prevents untidy solutions like this and also forces us to
  rely on the capabilities of CSS to solve this puzzle.
</p>
<p>
  The intention here was to obtain the smallest possible code in terms
  of the number of CSS declarations.  This example is not crafted to
  minimise bytes, but for code golfers who enjoy reducing byte count,
  here is the number of bytes this solution consumes after removing
  all whitespace:
</p>
<pre><code>$ curl -sS https://susam.net/css-fizz-buzz.html | sed -n '/counter/,/after/p' | tr -d '[:space:]' | wc -c
152</code></pre>
<p>
  Further reduction in byte count can be achieved by using the
  <code>&lt;p&gt;</code> element instead of <code>&lt;li&gt;</code>,
  nesting CSS selectors, etc.  I'll leave that as an exercise for the
  reader.  Returning to the focus of this post as well as to summarise
  it, the solution here uses four CSS rules consisting of four
  selectors and four declarations to render the Fizz Buzz sequence.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/fizz-buzz-in-css.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/absurd.html">#absurd</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/css.html">#css</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/puzzle.html">#puzzle</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>CSS Fizz Buzz with Ordered List</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/web/css-fizz-buzz-ol.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">fzolc</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A version of my CSS Fizz Buzz that uses ordered list
  (<code>&lt;ol&gt;</code>) to reduce code.  However, I don't quite
  like how misaligned the numbers and the words look.  Correcting that
  would call for extra code that would cancel out the bytes saved.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/web/css-fizz-buzz-ol.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>CSS Fizz Buzz</title>
<link>https://susam.net/css-fizz-buzz.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">fzcss</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  An implementation of Fizz Buzz in four lines of CSS.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/css-fizz-buzz.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nerd Quiz #2</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/nq/2.0.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqtwo</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Nerd Quiz #2 is the second release of Nerd Quiz, a single-page HTML
  application that invites you to gauge your nerd level through short,
  focused quiz sets.  Each question is carefully crafted from everyday
  moments of reading, writing, thinking, learning and exploring.
</p>
<p>
  This release introduces five new questions drawn from a range of
  topics such as chess, graph theory and linguistics.  To try the
  quiz, visit <a href="../../../nq.html#2">nq.html</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/nq/2.0.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/game.html">#game</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nerd Quiz</title>
<link>https://susam.net/nq.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqhtm</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A nerdy, handcrafted quiz built from everyday moments of reading,
  writing, thinking, learning and exploring.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/nq.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Nerd Quiz #1</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/nq/1.0.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nqone</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Nerd Quiz #1 is the first release of Nerd Quiz, a single-page HTML
  application that lets you test your nerd level through short,
  focused quiz sets.  Each question in the quiz is handcrafted from
  everyday moments of reading, writing, thinking, learning and
  exploring.
</p>
<p>
  To try the quiz now, visit <a href="../../../nq.html">nq.html</a>.
</p>
<p>
  The source code of Nerd Quiz is available at
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/nq#readme">github.com/susam/nq</a>
  under the terms of the MIT licence.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/nq/1.0.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/miscellaneous.html">#miscellaneous</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/game.html">#game</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>QuickQWERTY 1.2.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/1.2.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">qqotz</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  QuickQWERTY 1.2.0 is now available.  QuickQWERTY is a web-based
  touch typing tutor for QWERTY keyboards that runs directly in the
  web browser.
</p>
<p>
  This release brings small improvements to make the typing tutor
  smoother and the lessons more accurate.  When you return to the
  application, it no longer needlessly redirects you back to Unit 1.1
  if that was the last lesson you practised.
</p>
<p>
  Several lessons have received minor corrections.  Units 7.2 and 7.3
  no longer include the word "tyre", avoiding a preference for either
  British or American spelling.  Units 9.2 and 9.3 now spell
  "orwellian" correctly.  A factual error in Unit 17.4 has been fixed
  too.  It previously said "89 is one more than 99", which now
  correctly reads "89 is one more than 88".
</p>
<p>
  Finally, switching between the 5-6 and 6-7 split layouts is now more
  reliable.  In the previous release, pressing <kbd>Esc</kbd> to
  cancel the confirmation dialogue still caused the switch to go
  through.  Now pressing <kbd>Esc</kbd> properly cancels the switch as
  expected.
</p>
<p>
  To try out the new release of QuickQWERTY, go to
  <a href="../../../quickqwerty.html">quickqwerty.html</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/1.2.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Reinstated My Guestbook After 20 Years</title>
<link>https://susam.net/reinstated-guestbook.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">gbret</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  I have reinstated the <a href="comments/guestbook.html">guestbook</a>
  on this website after 20 years!  As I have written in the
  <a href="about.html">About</a> page, this website began its life as
  an intranet portal in my university network back in 2001–2005.  That
  portal first ran on Microsoft Personal Web Server (PWS) and later on
  Microsoft Internet Information Services (IIS), with the guestbook
  data stored in a Microsoft Access database.  At the same time, I
  also maintained a small public website on the Internet, hosted on a
  subdomain provided by a free hosting service, where I published a
  subset of the articles from the intranet portal.  Both the intranet
  portal and the public website had guestbooks.  The guestbook on the
  public website was powered by a CGI script provided by the hosting
  service, which inserted each comment directly into the guestbook
  HTML page.  As some of you might guess, yes, it was vulnerable to
  cross-site scripting, but that's beside the point.
</p>
<p>
  After leaving the university, I registered my own domain name and
  set up my current website on the World Wide Web and included some of
  the content from both the original intranet portal and the old
  public website.  For some reason, though, I never thought to include
  a guestbook.  And so this website went on without a guestbook for
  the next 20 years.  Finally, in June 2025, I decided to bring the
  guestbook back.  I already had a commenting system implemented for
  this website using Common Lisp and Hunchentoot, so I simply reused
  it for the guestbook.  The
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/susam.net/blob/0.3.0/form.lisp">server program</a>
  accepts POST requests to receive comments and writes them to text
  files on the web server for manual review.  The comments are then
  rendered as static HTML pages by my static site generator.  In a
  way, it is less a comment system and more a static comment pages
  generator.
</p>
<p>
  Unfortunately, I could not restore all the comments from the
  original guestbooks.  The ASP source code of my intranet portal as
  well as the guestbook database are now lost to time.  Note that what
  I refer to as ASP here is now known as Classic ASP, to avoid
  confusion with ASP.NET.  A CD-ROM backup eventually succumbed to
  disc rot and with it vanished the source code and the database.  But
  a handful of comments had survived because they had found their way
  into other files and correspondence and I have now included them
  here.  I had better luck with the guestbook of the old public
  website, from which I was able to recover a greater number of
  comments.  It is still only a small fraction of what once existed,
  but it feels good to have even those fragments preserved.  The new
  guestbook is now available here:
  <a href="comments/guestbook.html">Guestbook</a>.
</p>
<p>
  I wasn't expecting anybody to notice the new guestbook.  It is only
  mentioned in the <a href="about.html">About</a> and
  <a href="links.html">Links</a> pages, neither of which see much
  traffic.  Here are a few examples:
</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>
    I love that your website has a guestbook!  :D
  </p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
  <p>
    Love the guestbook!  We need more of these.  Makes you feel
    invited.
  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>
  It's a small addition to my website, but after two decades, it feels
  good to see the guestbook alive again and even better to see
  visitors enjoying it!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/reinstated-guestbook.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>QuickQWERTY 1.1.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/1.1.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">qqooz</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 28 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  There has been a new release of QuickQWERTY after over 10 years!
  QuickQWERTY is a web-based touch typing tutor for QWERTY keyboards
  that runs directly in the web browser.  You can try it out
  here: <a href="../../../quickqwerty.html">quickqwerty.html</a>.
</p>
<p>
  The new release, version 1.1.0 of QuickQWERTY, introduces a new
  input command named <code>reset</code>, which is a synoymn for the
  existing commands <code>restart</code> and <code>rst</code> used to
  restart the current lesson.  Another input command
  named <code>test</code> runs an internal suite of tests to validate
  that no lesson involves keys that have not been introduced in the
  current or prior lessons.  Further, in this release, the application
  has been fully rewritten as a single standalone HTML file with no
  external dependencies and the source code has been greatly
  simplified.
</p>
<p>
  There are a number of other changes too.  Words per minute (WPM)
  calculation has been refined so the first character, which starts
  the timer, is not counted.  The guides have been enhanced.  Keys to
  be pressed are now highlighted more clearly and reminders to return
  fingers to their home positions have been added to each guide.  The
  confirmation dialogue for switching between 6-7 split and 5-6 split
  styles now uses the HTML <code>&lt;dialog&gt;</code> element,
  replacing the dated <code>window.confirm()</code> prompt.  In
  addition, when the application is opened without a fragment
  identifier in the URL, the most recently practised lesson loads
  automatically.
</p>
<p>
  The user interface has been simplified.  The previous and next links
  (<code>&laquo;</code> and <code>&raquo;</code>) for navigating
  lessons have been removed, as they added little value and made the
  layout of the various user interface components more complex.  The
  "Next lesson" advice link remains for moving to the next lesson when
  the current one is completed successfully.  Tooltips showing
  additional typing metrics have also been removed due to limited
  usefulness.
</p>
<p>
  The lessons have been updated to remove spellings specific to
  American English.  Care has been taken to use only words that are
  spelled the same in American and British English with one exception.
  The word "tyre", in its British English spelling, was mistakenly
  left in the lesson.  That will be fixed in the next release.
</p>
<p>
  Finally, QuickQWERTY's licence has changed from the BSD-2-Clause
  licence to the MIT licence.  The source code is available at
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/quickqwerty">github.com/susam/quickqwerty</a>.
  To run this release and learn touch typing on a QWERTY keyboard, go
  to <a href="../../../quickqwerty.html">quickqwerty.html</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/1.1.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Prime Number Grid Explorer</title>
<link>https://susam.net/primegrid.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">pghtm</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A simple single-page HTML application to explore the distribution of
  prime numbers in a grid.  Choose a starting number along with the
  number of rows and columns and the page generates the corresponding
  grid.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/primegrid.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/mathematics.html">#mathematics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Miller-Rabin Speed Test</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/web/miller-rabin-speed-test.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">mrpst</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 16 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A demo page that implements the Miller-Rabin primality test to
  accurately detect primes for all numbers less than
  318665857834031151167461 and compare its speed against a simple
  division based primality test algorithm.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/web/miller-rabin-speed-test.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/mathematics.html">#mathematics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>My Blogroll Is Now My Feed Reader</title>
<link>https://susam.net/blogroll-as-feed-reader.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">mbmfr</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  On a particularly hot summer weekend last month, I implemented a new
  feature for this website: a blogroll that lists recent entries from
  my favourite blogs.  Check it out here: <a href="roll.html">roll.html</a>.
</p>
<p>
  It has been nearly two weeks since I set up this blogroll and it has
  already changed how I keep up with my feeds.  I no longer bother
  with feed readers or aggregators.  I could never quite make a habit
  of using them regularly anyway.  Thanks to this simple addition to
  my website, I find myself visiting my blogroll often.  It has earned
  a permanent place in my bookmarks.  When I have some spare time, I
  click on the bookmark, visit my blogroll and, when I find new posts
  appear there, I click through and read the full blog posts.
</p>
<p>
  Credit for this nifty and surprisingly effective idea goes to Alex
  Kladov.  It was Alex's website,
  <a href="https://matklad.github.io/">matklad.github.io</a>, that
  inspired me to implement my own blogroll.  It showed me that a
  blogroll can be more than just a static list of links.  It can be a
  regularly updated page that highlights new posts from the blogs I
  follow.
</p>
<p>
  I suspect the fact that my blogroll is generated by my own
  handcrafted <a href="https://github.com/susam/susam.net/blob/main/roll.lisp">Common
  Lisp program</a> plays a part in why I enjoy using it.  There is a
  certain joy in using something you have built yourself.  At last, I
  feel I can stay on top of my feeds!  If you maintain a personal
  website and struggle to keep up with your feeds, I recommend this
  approach.  Writing the blogroll generator was a fun weekend project
  and it has greatly improved how I spend my spare time online!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/blogroll-as-feed-reader.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>CSS Experiments: overflow-wrap vs word-break</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/web/overflow-wrap-vs-word-break.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">owvwb</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  An example page demonstrating experiments with the
  CSS <code>overflow-wrap</code> and <code>word-break</code>
  properties.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/web/overflow-wrap-vs-word-break.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/css.html">#css</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Noise From My Feeds</title>
<link>https://susam.net/feed-noise.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">xjdrj</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Hello!  If you are subscribed to this website's feeds, you may have
  noticed something odd recently.  Your feed reader might have shown a
  bunch of old posts as if they were published today.  If that
  happened with your feed reader, I apologise for the noise.  I hope
  this post will give you some clarity on why this happened.  The
  reason for this noise is a change to the way the RSS feeds are
  generated for this website.  Each post in the feeds includes a GUID,
  which is used by many feed readers to decide whether a post is new
  or if it has been seen already.  Until now, the GUID was simply the
  post's URL, like this:
</p>
<pre>
<code>&lt;url&gt;https://susam.net/product-of-additive-inverses.html&lt;/url&gt;
&lt;guid&gt;https://susam.net/product-of-additive-inverses.html&lt;/guid&gt;</code>
</pre>
<p>
  However, today this has changed to a short unique string, like so:
</p>
<pre>
<code>&lt;url&gt;https://susam.net/product-of-additive-inverses.html&lt;/url&gt;
&lt;guid isPermaLink="false"&gt;rxpnz&lt;/guid&gt;</code>
</pre>
<p>
  If your feed reader looks at this GUID value to decide whether a new
  post has been published, it will show you a whole bunch of old posts
  once again in your reader, as if they were new.  These GUIDs won't
  change again in the future, so this is a one-time problem.  The full
  URL of the post is still present in the feeds, as you can see in the
  example above, so your feed reader still knows where to take you if
  you wish to visit this website to read a post.  The short string
  serves as a unique identifier for each post.
</p>
<p>
  This website is a passion project I work on in my spare time.
  Sometimes, after publishing a post, I realise the title could be
  sharper or the URL could be cleaner.  I make the necessary changes
  and set up HTTP redirects on my web server, so that visitors using
  the old URL are still taken to the updated location of the post.
  Previously, however, the GUID (being the URL) changed too, which
  caused many feed readers to treat the updated post as a new one even
  when it wasn't.  Switching to stable GUIDs prevents this problem
  from occurring again.  The GUIDs now stay the same no matter what
  changes I make behind the scenes, which means no more unnecessary
  noise in your feed reader.
</p>
<p>
  I am sorry if this caused any confusion or clutter.  If your feed
  reader is currently flooded with old posts appearing as new, the
  best solution is to mark those items as read.  Thank you for your
  patience with this issue.  I hope to keep future surprises limited
  to content, not configuration.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/feed-noise.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>More Contrast, Please</title>
<link>https://susam.net/more-contrast-please.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">ygqwk</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  So you have decided to go with a dark theme for your website.  Great
  choice!  I love dark themes too!  My journey with computers began
  with monochrome CRT monitors, where white text was displayed on dark
  background.  I am still very fond of that colour scheme.  Done well,
  dark themes can be elegant and easy on the eyes.  But there is a
  common pitfall that I see all too often in modern web design: the
  overuse of low-contrast colour schemes.  This is something worth
  keeping in mind while crafting a new theme.
</p>
<p>
  Take a look at this example where the text colour
  is <code>#777</code> and the background is <code>#222</code>:
</p>
<p style="background: #222; color: #777; padding: 1em; text-align: center; font-size: 1rem; font-family: helvetica, sans-serif">
  The five boxing wizards jump quickly.
</p>
<p>
  I am hoping that most people would agree that the colour contrast
  above is too low.  I certainly find it uncomfortable to read.
  However, the situation becomes a bit less clear with the following
  example, where the text colour is set to <code>#999</code> and the
  background is <code>#222</code>:
</p>
<p style="background: #222; color: #999; padding: 1em; text-align: center; font-size: 1rem; font-family: helvetica, sans-serif">
  The five boxing wizards jump quickly.
</p>
<p>
  The above example is, in fact, based on a real website I came across
  today.  Now this is definitely better than the first example and I
  am sure some people would find this perfectly acceptable.  However,
  I still find this uncomfortable to read.  In fact, I have realised
  that as I get older, I need a higher contrast ratio to make the text
  more comfortable to read.
</p>
<p>
  I would suggest that any colour choices for foreground text and
  background page colours should, at the very least, meet
  the <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG22/#contrast-enhanced">Web
  Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG) Level AAA</a>
  recommendations.  This means the contrast ratio for normal-sized
  text against the background should be at least 7:1.  There are also
  the slightly weaker Level AA guidelines, which require that
  normal-sized text have a contrast ratio of at least 4.5:1.  That
  said, I personally recommend aiming for a 7:1 contrast ratio
  regardless.
</p>
<p>
  The first example above has a contrast ratio of just 3.6:1, meaning
  it fails to meet both the Level AA and Level AAA requirements.  The
  second example, on the other hand, has a contrast ratio of 5.6:1.
  While it satisfies the Level AA requirements, it still falls short
  of meeting the Level AAA standards.
</p>
<p>
  To calculate the contrast ratio according to
  the <a href="https://www.w3.org/WAI/WCAG22/Techniques/general/G17.html#tests">WCAG
  contrast formula</a>, use one of these tools:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="contrast.html">My Colour Contrast Calculator</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://webaim.org/resources/contrastchecker/">WebAIM Contrast Checker</a>
  </li>
</ul>
<p>
  If we improve the contrast for the second example above, we would
  need to choose a brighter shade for the text, such as
  <code>#BBB</code>.  On the dark background <code>#222</code>, this
  results in a contrast ratio of 8.3:1.  Here is how it looks:
</p>
<p style="background: #222; color: #bbb; padding: 1em; text-align: center; font-size: 1rem; font-family: helvetica, sans-serif">
  The five boxing wizards jump quickly.
</p>
<p>
  I definitely find this much easier to read.  If you are developing a
  dark colour theme for your web page or software, I request you to
  run your colours through a contrast calculator tool and ensure the
  contrast ratio is greater than 7:1.  Anything less and the theme
  might become uncomfortable for people like me.  Small adjustments
  like this can significantly improve readability and comfort for your
  readers.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/more-contrast-please.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Colour Contrast Calculator</title>
<link>https://susam.net/contrast.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">xmajx</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A simple web-based tool to calculate the contrast between two
  colours according to WCAG contrast formula.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/contrast.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>More Purple Links, Please</title>
<link>https://susam.net/more-purple-links-please.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">gyrti</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  While I am browsing the Web, one thing I always like to see is a
  page with purple links.  Since the early days of the Web, purple has
  has become the default colour for visited links.  Here's a relevant
  note from the
  <a href="https://ksi.cpsc.ucalgary.ca/archives/WWW-TALK/www-talk-1993q2.messages/47.html">changelog</a>
  of NCSA Mosaic 0.13 (1993):
</p>
<blockquote>
  Changed default anchor representations: blue and single solid
  underline for unvisited, dark purple and single dashed underline for
  visited.
</blockquote>
<p>
  Visiting a web page and finding purple links brings a sense of ease.
  The purple links indicate that I am familiar with some of the
  references the web page makes to other articles.  Each purple link
  serves as a small marker of a prior journey, a reminder that I've
  explored certain paths before.  To me, purple links are like
  well-worn books with faded covers and creased spines.  Blue links,
  on the other hand, are like new books, to be opened and explored.
</p>
<p>
  Although I'm quite fond of purple links, I know that not everyone
  shares this sentiment.  Modern web design trends have moved away
  from this tradition, favouring sleek, minimalist aesthetics where
  visited and unvisisted links look nearly the same.  While this can
  be visually appealing, in my opinion, it detracts from the
  experience of using the Web as a source of knowledge.  When links
  look indistinguishable or unconventional, it can be hard to tell
  what I've already read, especially when I am revisiting a topic and
  want to easily spot the links that are new.
</p>
<p>
  Now it is not hard to change the visited link style with a little
  userscript.  For example the following userscript can override the
  website's stylesheet to colour visited links purple again:
</p>
<pre>
<code>// ==UserScript==
// @name Purple Links
// @match *://*/*
// ==/UserScript==
document.head.appendChild(document.createElement('style'))
document.head.lastElementChild.innerHTML = 'a:visited {color: #518}'</code>
</pre>
<p>
  This little userscript should work well on most web pages with light
  backgrounds.  But if a web page uses a dark theme or a custom colour
  scheme, then the above userscript may need adjustments to either
  handle other colour schemes gracefully.
</p>
<p>
  To me, the purple links serve as small reminders of all the digital
  paths I've already walked.  I wish more websites would honour this
  convention.  More purple links, please.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/more-purple-links-please.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>PDF Dimmer Bookmarklet</title>
<link>https://susam.net/pdf-dimmer-bookmarklet.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">bgigh</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  I often read PDF documents in Firefox and sometimes I prefer to work
  in dark mode, especially at night when the room lights are dimmed.
  However, the bright white background of the Firefox PDF viewer can
  be glaring and uncomfortable when dark mode is enabled.
  Additionally, writing a userscript to invert the background and text
  colours in the PDF viewer does not work.  I have confirmed with
  Firefox version 137.0 that userscripts do not run within the PDF
  viewer.
</p>
<p>
  For example, consider this simple userscript that just prints a
  "hello" message when a web page loads:
  <a href="code/lab/userscript/hello.js">hello.js</a>.  This script
  works on regular web pages but does not execute when viewing a PDF
  file in Firefox.
  See <a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1454760">Bug
  1454760</a> for more details about this restriction.
</p>
<p>
  While userscripts are often my go-to solution for customisations
  like this, for this particular problem, I resorted to writing a tiny
  bookmarklet to work around the above limitation.  Here is the
  bookmarklet:
</p>
<pre><code>javascript:(()=&gt;{['thumbnailView','viewer'].map(id=&gt;document.getElementById(id).style.filter='invert(0.9)saturate(0)')})()</code></pre>
<p>
  To add this to Firefox, from the Firefox menu, select "Bookmarks".
  Then in the left sidebar, right click on either "Bookmarks Toolbar"
  or "Bookmarks Menu", depending on where you want to add the
  bookmarklet and select "Add Bookmark".  Enter some name in the
  "Name" field and then in the "URL" field, enter the above line of
  code.  Click "Save" and you are done.  The next time you open a PDF
  file in Firefox, find the bookmark in the bookmarks menu or toolbar,
  click on it and it should instantly invert the colour scheme of the
  PDF viewer.
</p>
<p>
  Alternatively, simply drag the following link and drop it onto your
  Firefox toolbar:
</p>
<p class="textcenter">
  <a href="javascript:(()=%3e%7b%5b'thumbnailView','viewer'%5d.map(id=%3edocument.getElementById(id).style.filter='invert(0.9)saturate(0)')%7d)()">Dim PDF</a>
</p>
<p>
  While the default PDF viewer of Firefox does not support
  userscripts, this bookmarklet is a simple, effective way to give
  PDFs a darker look.  If you're like me and often read books and
  papers in PDF format at night, you might find this handy.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/pdf-dimmer-bookmarklet.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>MathB 1.3.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/mathb/1.3.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">lpjpy</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  MathB 1.3.0 is likely the final update of MathB, a web-based
  mathematics pastebin service.  The online mathematics pastebin
  service previously hosted at <code>https://mathb.in/</code> has been
  shut down today after 13 years of continuous service.  See the post
  <a href="../../../mathbin-is-shutting-down.html">MathB.in Is
  Shutting Down</a> for more details about this.  This release
  captures the state of this project as it was today at the time of
  shutting down the online service.
</p>
<p>
  This update includes a few new features.  For example, there is now
  a configurable runtime property named <code>:expect</code> that can
  be used to enforce the presence of certain tokens in the posts
  submitted by the users.  This feature was used to enforce the
  presence of LaTeX delimiters in the online service, a measure that
  was instrumental in reducing spam to a great extent in the last few
  years.  There are a few other minor changes too.
  See <a href="https://github.com/susam/mathb/blob/main/CHANGES.md">CHANGES.md</a>
  for a detailed changelog.
</p>
<p>
  The source code of MathB remains free and open-source, so anyone
  interested in hosting their own instance can still do so.  To access
  the source code of MathB, please visit
  <a href="http://github.com/susam/mathb">github.com/susam/mathb</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/mathb/1.3.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>XOR Map</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/web/xormap.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">pevyd</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A simple HTML page that plots bitwise-XOR <em>x</em> and <em>y</em>
  for each coordinate (<em>x</em>, <em>y</em>)</em> with the
  coordinate (0, 0) at the bottom-left corner.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/web/xormap.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>MathB.in Is Shutting Down</title>
<link>https://susam.net/mathbin-is-shutting-down.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">rrbdk</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Thirteen years ago, on a quiet Saturday night, I sat down and began
  developing MathB.in.  After coding all through the night, as the sun
  rose on Sunday, 25 March 2012, the website was ready.  I registered
  a new domain name and shared it with a few friends who loved
  mathematics.  Back then, we spent hours discussing fascinating
  mathematics problems and this website became a simple way for us to
  share snippets with each other.  Word spread quickly.  My friends
  shared it with their friends, who passed it along to others.  The
  community grew organically.  Then, one day, I announced the project
  on the MathJax mailing list and its reach expanded even further.
  Within a year, this mathematics pastebin service had users from
  around the world.  Watching the usage of this little project grow
  was an incredibly rewarding experience.
</p>
<figure class="soft">
  <a href="files/blog/mathbin.png"><img
     src="files/blog/mathbin.png"
     alt="A screenshot of a mathematics pastebin service displaying Markdown and LaTeX code in the left pane and the rendered content in the right pane."></a>
  <figcaption>
    A screenshot of MathB.in, a mathematics pastebin service
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>
  The world has changed a lot since I first published MathB.in.  The
  internet has evolved and so have I.  Maintaining a mathematics
  pastebin service like this single-handedly has become increasingly
  difficult over the years.  Over the past 13 years, I have received
  notices from regulatory authorities whenever someone submitted
  content that triggered compliance concerns.  Each time, my server
  would be taken offline and I would be given a 7-day deadline to boot
  it into rescue mode, remove the offending content and restore
  service.  Missing the deadline would put my server hosting account
  at risk of cancellation.
</p>
<p>
  To prevent these disruptions, I began reviewing and filtering
  incoming content as much as possible every few days.  The
  appreciation and positive feedback from happy users kept me going.
  However, at this stage of my life, I can no longer afford to spend
  time moderating user content.  On top of that, the growing
  complexity of data protection and digital safety regulations places
  a significant burden on me as the maintainer of this service.
  Complying with these regulations requires considerable legal
  expertise that I cannot afford.
</p>
<p>
  Some might suggest that I could improve the spam-detection
  capabilities of this service and indeed, I have done so over the
  years.  However, all anti-spam measures are inherently
  probabilistic.  No matter how much automation is in place, a manual
  review of every post is still necessary to guarantee that all
  content is legitimate.  It only takes one dodgy submission to
  trigger compliance alerts.  While I respect the need for these
  regulations, I do not want to spend my weekends worrying about what
  users from around the world might be posting on this little pastebin
  service.  Nor do I want to be in a constant state of vigilance just
  to keep my server running.  It takes up more time than I can spare.
</p>
<p>
  Some have suggested forming a team of volunteers to review
  submissions, but that does not solve the core issue: since the
  server hosting account is in my name, I would still be responsible
  for remediating any compliance issues or risk having my account
  cancelled.  Another alternative is to move the service under a
  non-profit organisation, but with increased responsibilities in
  other areas of my life, handling the operational demands of such an
  endeavour is far beyond what I can commit to.  After all, this was
  meant to be a fun project built for me and my friends, not something
  that requires me to deal with regulatory issues.
</p>
<p>
  Another alternative would be to encode the content of a MathB.in
  post and embed it into the URL, which could then be distributed with
  others.  Upon visiting the URL, the application would read the
  encoded content from the URL, decode it and render it.  While this
  eliminates the need to store user content on my server, it
  introduces a new concern: the risk of someone sharing URLs with
  malicious content embedded in them.  I am not comfortable with such
  content being rendered on a page served from a domain that I am the
  registrant of.  The regulatory implications of rendering such
  content are also unclear.  I could still be held accountable for
  content rendered on the website, regardless of whether it's stored
  on the server.  This problem could be mitigated to some extent by
  refusing to render content containing known malicious patterns but
  no such solution can be foolproof.
</p>
<p>
  As a result, after much thought, I have regrettably made the
  decision to shut down MathB.in on Sunday, 16 March 2025.  The
  website will go offline on that day.  If you have any important
  posts that you would like to keep, now is the time to copy and save
  them for yourself.
</p>
<p>
  To all of you who have used this project, I want to express my
  sincere gratitude.  Running a project that could serve you in a
  meaningful way has given me a strong sense of accomplishment and
  pride.  To those who are disappointed by this service's closure, I
  am sorry.  I wish I could continue to dedicate the time and effort
  needed to maintain and develop it, but I must acknowledge my
  limitations and step away from a project that has become an artefact
  of my past, not my present.
</p>
<p>
  The source code for this website is available at
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mathb">github.com/susam/mathb</a>
  under the MIT licence.  Feel free to use the code and set up your
  own instance if you'd like!  Alternatively, consider hosting your
  mathematical snippets and notes on your own web space using a kit
  like MathCask available at
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mathcask">github.com/susam/mathcask</a>.
</p>
<p>
  Finally, I hope you'll hold no hard feelings.  If you have enjoyed
  using MathB.in, I would love to stay connected on the Fediverse.  My
  Mastodon handle is
  <a href="https://mastodon.social/@susam">@susam@mastodon.social</a>.
  See you there!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/mathbin-is-shutting-down.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>The IndieWeb Doesn't Need to 'Take Off'</title>
<link>https://susam.net/indieweb-does-not-need-to-take-off.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">fgxtg</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  There's a corner of the Internet where people have been reclaiming
  their digital independence by hosting their own websites and
  promoting the idea of owning your own content.  It's called the
  IndieWeb.  This community has its own
  <a href="https://indieweb.org/">website</a>, IRC channels, social
  media presence, etc., all dedicated to the idea that individuals
  should control their own digital presence through personal websites.
</p>
<p>
  Publishing your own website isn't a new concept.  It is the very
  essence of the Web!  This is what the Web has always been about
  since its early days.  But in an era where corporate-controlled
  platforms dominate online interaction, the IndieWeb emphasises the
  original spirit of the Web, where individuals have control over
  their content, identities and online spaces.  Every time this topic
  arises in online discussions, someone inevitably claims that the
  IndieWeb hasn't taken off!
</p>
<p>
  I feel that such claims about the IndieWeb not 'taking off' are
  either stating the obvious or, if that's not the intention,
  completely missing the point.  It's like saying that gardening
  hasn't taken off because most people buy their vegetables at the
  supermarket.  The IndieWeb doesn't need to 'take off' to be valuable
  to those who participate in it.  Maintaining a personal website is
  about owning your digital presence, embracing creative freedom and
  expressing your individuality!  It's not about appealing to the
  masses!
</p>
<p>
  I remember how, in the early 2000s, I used to spend my spare time
  learning HTML and writing my website, one HTML tag at a time.
  Writing a few lines of code in a text editor and then watching the
  browser render that code into a vibrant web page full of colours and
  images felt like an art form.  It was doubly fun to find other
  netizens who shared that same joy of maintaining and publishing
  their websites.  The IndieWeb is about preserving that hacker
  culture where websites are crafted and hosted not for mass appeal
  but for the sheer joy of creation and sharing with like-minded
  individuals.
</p>
<p>
  The IndieWeb doesn't need to go mainstream to be meaningful.  It's a
  celebration of a more personal, decentralised and creative world
  wide web.  For those of us who still care about these values, it is
  already meaningful.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/indieweb-does-not-need-to-take-off.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>FXYT 0.5.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/fxyt/0.5.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">nwtao</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  FXYT 0.5.0 is a minor update of FXYT, a tiny, esoteric, stack-based,
  postfix, canvas colouring language with only 36 simple commands.
  This release fixes an annoying bug that has been affecting some
  mobile device users for a while.  On some mobile web browsers, such
  as Chrome on Samsung Galaxy S8, the drawing canvas would appear to
  be larger than the viewport thus overflowing the visible screen on
  the mobile device.  The user would then be required to manually zoom
  out in order to use this tool conveniently.  This issue has been
  fixed in this release.
</p>
<p>
  If you follow my <a href="../../../cfrs.html">CFRS[]</a> project,
  you might have noticed yesterday that a very similar fix has gone
  into CFRS[] too.  For more details about that, see
  the release page for <a href="../cfrs/0.3.0.html">CFRS[] 0.3.0</a>.
</p>
<p>
  Visit <a href="../../../fxyt.html">FXYT</a> to play with FXYT and
  draw some interesting patterns!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/fxyt/0.5.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>CFRS[] 0.3.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/cfrs/0.3.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">ojrjp</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  CFRS[] 0.3.0 is a minor update of CFRS[], an extremely minimal
  drawing language consisting of only 6 simple commands.  This update
  fixes an annoying bug that caused CFRS[] canvas to overflow the
  visible screen on some mobile web browsers.  In particular, this
  issue was observed on Chrome running on Samsung Galaxy S8.
</p>
<p>
  To read more about CFRS[], go to
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/cfrs#readme">github.com/susam/cfrs</a>.
  Also, visit <a href="../../../cfrs.html">cfrs.html</a> to play with CFRS[]
  now and draw some nice patterns!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/cfrs/0.3.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>FXYT 0.4.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/fxyt/0.4.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">zgrko</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  FXYT 0.4.0 is a minor update of FXYT, a tiny, esoteric, stack-based,
  postfix, canvas colouring language with only 36 simple commands.
  This release increases the maximum allowed code length from 256
  bytes to 1024 bytes.  This means there is now more room for writing
  more complex FXYT programs!
</p>
<p>
  Further, the maximum code length for distributable demo links has
  been increased from 64 bytes to 256 bytes.  This allows several more
  impressive demos to have their own distributable links.  As a
  specific example of one such demo, take a look at
  this <a href="https://susam.net/fxyt.html#XTsN128dN3142pN128qDN3142gbN6284dcDN1571gbN3142SdcDNN1571dlbNN3142dSdcDDN166SDpN120000qdSDpN1000qpN1000qN1000SdpN1000qN1100sN3pN25qYgNSbPN255c">animated
  sine wave</a> developed by <a href="https://github.com/ncw">Nick
  Craig-Wood</a>, of Rclone fame!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/fxyt/0.4.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Guess My RGB 0.3.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/myrgb/0.3.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">shmtq</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  <a href="../../../myrgb.html">Guess My RGB</a>, the little colour
  guessing game, just got a small update.  This update adds a
  "Mode" link to the footer which can be used to toggle the game
  between normal mode and expert mode.
</p>
<p>
  The expert mode was introduced as a hidden feature five months ago
  in the <a href="0.2.0.html">previous release</a>.  With the current
  release, the expert mode no longer remains a hidden feature.  You
  can simply toggle between modes via the new footer link.
</p>
<p>
  Ready to test your colour skills?  Head over to
  <a href="../../../myrgb.html">myrgb.html</a> and start playing
  today!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/myrgb/0.3.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Guess My RGB 0.2.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/myrgb/0.2.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">vojtv</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  <a href="../../../myrgb.html">Guess My RGB</a>, the little colour
  guessing game, received a minor update today.  This update adds a
  hidden feature that lets you play the game in <em>expert mode</em>.
  In this mode, the match percentage for your submitted guess is not
  shown on the screen.
</p>
<p>
  Thanks to @steffahn for
  <a href="https://lobste.rs/s/sbcayb/guess_my_rgb#c_gqrj3r">suggesting
  this feature</a> on th Lobsters forum!
</p>
<p>
  Visit <a href="../../../myrgb.html#x">myrgb.html#x</a> now to play
  the game in the expert mode.
</p>
<p>
  Alternatively, visit <a href="../../../myrgb.html">myrgb.html</a> to
  play it in the normal mode like before.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/myrgb/0.2.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>From Web Feed Entry to 186k Hits</title>
<link>https://susam.net/from-web-feed-to-186850-hits.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">blshr</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Last Sunday (31 Mar 2024), I published a tiny colour guessing game
  called <a href="myrgb.html">Guess My RGB</a>.  I developed most of
  it on Saturday afternoon, took a break and revisited it later that
  night for some final code cleanup.  Around 02:00 UTC, I uploaded the
  game to my website.  Since the entire game is contained in a single
  HTML file named <a href="myrgb.html">myrgb.html</a>, it was just a
  matter of uploading this file to my web server.  Shortly after, I
  went to bed.
</p>
<p>
  I had no intention of sharing this game with a wide audience yet, as
  it hadn't been thoroughly tested.  However, when I woke up the next
  morning, I discovered that a Hacker News (HN) user had already found
  and shared the game on HN in this post:
  <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39882018">news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39882018</a>.
</p>
<p>
  Since I had not shared this game with anyone anywhere yet, I was
  quite surprised to wake up Sunday morning and find my game trending
  at the top of HN.  I believe this is where maintaining an RSS feed
  on my website might have helped.  Every new page that I publish on
  this website also appears as an entry in the RSS feed for this
  website.  This feed can be found here:
  <a href="feed.xml">feed.xml</a>.  I have a few hundred subscribers
  to this feed.  It is very likely that the HN user who shared this
  game on HN found it through this feed.  Indeed my web server logs
  show that the feed was fetched by a feed reader just minutes before
  the game was posted on HN.
</p>
<p>
  In the week since its HN mention, my game has received a total of
  186,850 hits.  Not a staggering number but encouraging!  The actual
  numbers for each day look like this:
</p>
<!-- 95467 + 48330 + 22305 + 10189 + 4685 + 2101 + 3773 = 186850 -->
<table class="grid center textcenter">
  <tr>
    <th>Date</th>
    <th>Hits</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>31 Mar 2024</td>
    <td>95467</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>01 Apr 2024</td>
    <td>48330</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>02 Apr 2024</td>
    <td>22305</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>03 Apr 2024</td>
    <td>10189</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>04 Apr 2024</td>
    <td>4685</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>05 Apr 2024</td>
    <td>2101</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>06 Mar 2024</td>
    <td>3773</td>
  </tr>
</table>
<p>
  So the next time someone tells you that RSS is dead, remember how an
  RSS feed entry helped my little game get discovered.  It took only
  one entry in my web feed, one generous subscriber and a handful of
  HN upvotes to reach a large audience!  It is a good reminder that
  simple, open web tools still work well and sometimes they work
  surprisingly well.
</p>
<p>
  To all visitors of this website who played this game and shared this
  game with others, thank you!  Crafting
  <a href="https://github.com/susam?tab=repositories&amp;sort=stargazers">tiny
  software tools</a> like this is a creative outlet for me.  To know
  that there are others out there who enjoyed this game brings me joy!
  To play this game now, visit <a href="myrgb.html">myrgb.html</a> and
  guess some colours!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/from-web-feed-to-186850-hits.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>CFRS[] 0.2.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/cfrs/0.2.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">ihmkl</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  CFRS[] 0.2.0 is a minor update of CFRS[], an extremely minimal
  drawing language consisting of only 6 simple commands.  This update
  brings minor changes to the built-in help screen that can be invoked
  by typing <code>?</code> in the input pane.  For example, the help
  screen now has a direct links to built-in demos and community demos.
  Further, based on community feedback, the description of
  the <code>]</code> command has been updated with clearer language
  that better clarifies that this command repeats a repeatable block
  once (i.e. executes the repeatable block again).  See
  the <a href="https://github.com/susam/cfrs/blob/main/CHANGES.md">changelog</a>
  for more details.
</p>
<p>
  To read more about CFRS[], go to
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/cfrs#readme">github.com/susam/cfrs</a>.
  Visit <a href="../../../cfrs.html">cfrs.html</a> to play with CFRS[]
  now and draw some nice pictures and animation.  If you end up
  developing any cool demos, do share them by creating a
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/cfrs/issues">new post here</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/cfrs/0.2.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Guess My RGB 0.1.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/myrgb/0.1.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">ndivu</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 03 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Guess My RGB 0.1.0 is the first stable release
  of <a href="../../../myrgb.html">this tiny colour guessing game</a>.
  The game is available as a single HTML page that runs in a web
  browser.  It presents a page with a randomly chosen background
  colour.  The player then needs to guess the three RGB hexademical
  digits that make the given background colour.  See
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/myrgb">github.com/susam/myrgb</a>
  for more information about this game.
</p>
<p>
  I wrote this game last Saturday afternoon and shared it on my
  website at <a href="../../../myrgb.html">myrgb.html</a> later that
  night.  I had no intention of sharing this with a wide audience yet
  because I had not had sufficient time testing it well.  But somehow
  a Hacker News (HN) user named <em>talonx</em> discovered this game
  on Sunday morning and shared it on HN in this post:
  <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39882018">news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39882018</a>.
</p>
<p>
  Since I had not shared this game with anyone anywhere yet, I was
  quite surprised to wake up Sunday morning and find my game trending
  at the top of HN.  I believe this is where maintaining an RSS feed
  on my website might have helped.  Every new page that I publish on
  this website also appears as an entry in the RSS feed for this
  website.  This feed can be found
  here: <a href="../../../feed.xml">feed.xml</a>.  I have a couple of
  hundred subscribers to this feed.  It is very likely that the HN
  user who shared this game on HN found it through this feed.
</p>
<p>
  Ever since this game was shared on HN, my website has received a
  large number of hits.  In the last three days (excluding today),
  this game has received a total of 166102 hits.  The actual numbers
  for each day look like this:
</p>
<table class="grid center textcenter">
  <tr>
    <th>Date</th>
    <th>Hits</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>31 Mar 2024</td>
    <td>95467</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>01 Mar 2024</td>
    <td>48330</td>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <td>02 Mar 2024</td>
    <td>22305</td>
  </tr>
</table>
<p>
  To all visitors of this website who played this game and shared this
  game with others, thank you!  Crafting tiny software tools like this
  is a creative outlet for me.  To know that there are others out
  there who enjoyed this game brings me joy!
</p>
<p>
  To play this game, go to <a href="../../../myrgb.html">myrgb.html</a>
  now and guess some colours!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/myrgb/0.1.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Guess My RGB</title>
<link>https://susam.net/myrgb.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">uiorn</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A tiny, web-based, RGB colour guessing game.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/myrgb.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/game.html">#game</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>FXYT 0.3.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/fxyt/0.3.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">snbrx</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  FXYT 0.3.0 is a minor release of FXYT, a tiny, esoteric,
  stack-based, postfix, canvas colouring language with only 36 simple
  commands.  This release comes with minor bug fixes pertaining to
  initialising the input and output from code embedded in
  distributable links.  No change in the language definition or the
  language implementation has been made in this release.
</p>
<p>
  Visit <a href="../../../fxyt.html">fxyt.html</a> to play with FXYT.
  See <a href="https://github.com/susam/fxyt#readme">README</a> for
  more details.  Also, see
  <a href="https://susam.github.io/fxyt/demo.html">this demo page</a>
  for some nice demos developed by the tiny community around FXYT.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/fxyt/0.3.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>CFRS[] 0.1.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/cfrs/0.1.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">fmbcp</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  CFRS[] 0.1.0 is the first release of CFRS[], an extremely minimal
  drawing language that consists of only six simple commands.  Ever
  since this new esoteric language and its implementation was
  <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37956065">announced
  about two months ago</a>, a small but enthusiastic community has
  sprung up around it.  Feedback and enhancement requests from the
  community has been crucial in polishing the implementation and
  arriving at the current stable release.  Further, some community
  members have also submitted very interesting and impressive demos.
</p>
<p>
  To play with CFRS[] now, please
  visit <a href="../../../cfrs.html">cfrs.html</a>.
</p>
<p>
  See <a href="https://github.com/susam/cfrs#readme">github.com/susam/cfrs</a>
  for more information about CFRS.  Also, see this
  <a href="https://susam.github.io/cfrs/demo.html">demo page</a> for a
  curated collection of community demos.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/cfrs/0.1.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>FXYT 0.2.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/fxyt/0.2.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">pqtku</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  FXYT 0.2.0 is a minor update of FXYT, a tiny, stack-oriented, canvas
  colouring language written in postfix notation with only 36 simple
  commands.  This update specifies and implements a much stricter
  definition of the <code>F</code> command that sets the frame
  interval.  The problem with the earlier definition as well as
  implementation was that the <code>F</code> command was evaluated for
  every cell in the canvas and the frame interval was set for every
  such interval.  This meant that the frame interval that would be set
  for the next frame would depend on the order in which the evaluation
  occurred.  See section
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/fxyt#frame-interval">Frame
  Interval</a> of the README for the complete details.
</p>
<p>
  This update now ensures that a coordinate-dependent frame interval
  set with the <code>F</code> command behaves uniformly across any
  implementation of FXYT regardless of the order of evaluation.  This
  is done by ensuring that while the command <code>F</code> is
  evaluated for all cells, it is only the frame interval value found
  during the evaluation of cell (0, 0) that is honoured as the frame
  interval for the next frame.
</p>
<p>
  The new update is now available at
  <a href="../../../fxyt.html">fxyt.html</a>.  You are very welcome to
  try it out and play with it.  If you come up with any interesting
  demos, please do
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/fxyt/issues">share them here</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/fxyt/0.2.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>FXYT</title>
<link>https://susam.net/fxyt.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">kzrxk</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Tiny, stack-based, postfix, canvas colouring language with only 36
  simple commands.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/fxyt.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>FXYT 0.1.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/fxyt/0.1.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">dtrrv</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  FXYT 0.1.0 is the first release of this project that introduces the
  FXYT canvas colouring language and a reference implementation.  This
  project is inspired by Martin Kleppe's very popular Tixy project.
  While Tixy supports JavaScript expressions to determine the size and
  colour of circles in a 16x16 grid, FXYT comes with its own tiny,
  stack-based language that is written in postfix notation.  Further,
  FXYT provides a 256x256 grid of cells each of which can be painted
  with an arbitrary colour determined by the result of the evaluation
  of the input code.
</p>
<p>
  To see some demos, visit these links:
  <a href="../../../fxyt.html#XYxTN1srN255pTN1sqD">#1</a>,
  <a href="../../../fxyt.html#XYaTN1srN255pTN1sqN0">#2</a>,
  <a href="../../../fxyt.html#XYoTN1srN255pTN1sqDN0S">#3</a>,
  <a href="../../../fxyt.html#XYpTN1srN255pTN1sqD">#4</a> and
  <a href="../../../fxyt.html#XYN256sTdrD">#5</a>.
</p>
<p>
  Also, see
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/fxyt#readme">github.com/susam/fxyt</a>
  for more details about this project.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/fxyt/0.1.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>CFRS[]</title>
<link>https://susam.net/cfrs.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">toujs</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  An extremely minimal drawing language consisting of only 6 simple
  commands: <code>C</code>, <code>F</code>, <code>R</code>,
  <code>S</code>, <code>[</code> and <code>]</code>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/cfrs.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>TextMetrics</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/web/textmetrics.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">otimn</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  An example page that demonstrates text metrics measurements.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/web/textmetrics.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>MathB 1.2.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/mathb/1.2.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">ffzvj</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  MathB 1.2.0 is a minor update of MathB, a web-based mathematics
  pastebin service.
</p>
<p>
  This release introduces a number of new customisable properties,
  including the ability to set a minimum title length, minimum code
  length, etc.  The stylesheet for rendered pages has been improved so
  that the print preview displays only the rendered mathematical
  content, allowing users to print beautifully rendered pages to
  paper.  A few rendering bug fixes are included too.
</p>
<p>
  See <a href="https://github.com/susam/mathb/blob/main/CHANGES.md">CHANGES.md</a>
  for a detailed changelog.  To read more about this project, please see
  <a href="http://github.com/susam/mathb">github.com/susam/mathb</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/mathb/1.2.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>MathB 1.1.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/mathb/1.1.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">akquu</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  MathB 1.1.0 is a minor update of MathB, a web-based mathematics
  pastebin service.
</p>
<p>
  This release introduces a few additional features for webmasters
  hosting MathB on their own web servers.  Notably, administrators can
  now ban specific IP addresses, helping mitigate spam attacks from
  known sources.  Additionally, the included Nginx configuration has
  been updated to fix a memory leak issue.  Several other minor fixes
  and improvements are also included.
</p>
<p>
  See <a href="https://github.com/susam/mathb/blob/main/CHANGES.md">CHANGES.md</a>
  for a detailed changelog.  To read more about this project, please see
  <a href="http://github.com/susam/mathb">github.com/susam/mathb</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/mathb/1.1.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>MathB 1.0.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/mathb/1.0.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">wmrtf</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  MathB 1.0.0 is the first major release of MathB since 2012, bringing
  significant updates to this web-based mathematics pastebin service.
</p>
<p>
  The most notable change is a complete rewrite in Common Lisp,
  replacing the original PHP codebase.  This shift reflects my
  preference for Lisp, a language I truly enjoy.  It also makes the
  project easier for me to maintain actively.
</p>
<p>
  This release introduces the use of the
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/texme">TeXMe</a> parser to
  robustly parse and render posts written using Markdown and LaTeX.
  Further, now there is support for dark colour scheme for systems
  that have dark colour scheme enabled.  For those who host this
  service on their web servers, MathB now supports a runtime control
  file named <code>opt.lisp</code> where a number of properties of
  this service can be customised.  These customisable properties
  include maximum title length, maximum code length, minimum time
  interval between two posts, etc.  See
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mathb/blob/main/CHANGES.md">CHANGES.md</a>
  for a detailed changelog.
</p>
<p>
  To read more about this project, please see
  <a href="http://github.com/susam/mathb">github.com/susam/mathb</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/mathb/1.0.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>MathB.in Turns Ten</title>
<link>https://susam.net/mathbin-turns-ten.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">hhdiy</guid>
<pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  On this day, ten years ago, MathB.in was released on the world wide
  web.  MathB.in is a web-based mathematics pastebin service that is
  used for sharing snippets of mathematical text with others.  The
  source code is available
  at <a href="https://github.com/susam/mathb">github.com/susam/mathb</a>.
</p>
<h2 id="brief-history-mathematics-pastebins">A Brief History of Mathematics Pastebins<a href="#brief-history-mathematics-pastebins"></a></h2>
<p>
  MathB.in is the oldest mathematics pastebin that is still alive and
  serving its community of users.  It isn't the first mathematics
  pastebin though.  It's the second.  The first one was written by
  Mark A. Stratman and hosted at <em>mathbin.net</em> until 2020.  It
  was very popular in the <code>#math</code> and <code>#physics</code>
  channels on IRC networks between 2006 and 2013.  It did not have
  live preview but it used an actual LaTeX system in the backend for
  rendering mathematical formulas into images, so the output was of
  pretty good quality.  It served IRC users very well for sharing
  problems and solutions quickly with each other on IRC channels.
  Since late-2014, Mark's website began intermittently displaying a
  notice that the website was shutting down.  The notice replaced the
  actual pastebin on some days, so users were forced to look for
  alternatives.  MathB.in was already available on the web and popular
  among IRC users by then, so it turned out to be a good alternative.
  Mark's website disappeared sometime in late-2020.
</p>
<p>
  Another alternative to the first mathematics pastebin was Huy
  Nguyen's <em>texpaste.com</em>.  It was released on the web in
  September 2013.  I believe it was the third mathematics pastebin to
  be released on the web.  In fact, it was a bit more than a pastebin.
  It allowed users to sign up for accounts and save their notes in
  their accounts.  It had some nifty widgets to click and
  automatically insert common LaTeX symbols instead of typing them out
  manually.  It had its own community of users.  However, it suffered
  from serious spam problems.  Searching for "texpaste.com" on Twitter
  shows how the service was being exploited by spammers to share
  dubious content and links several times every single day between
  December 2016 and February 2018.  Despite the spam problems, it
  continued to serve its genuine users for many years.  Finally, the
  website disappeared in 2021 and has not returned since then.
</p>
<h2 id="story-of-mathbin">The Story of MathB.in<a href="#story-of-mathbin"></a></h2>
<p>
  MathB.in was born on Sunday, 25 March 2012, after a single night of
  furious coding.  The previous night, I happened to stumble
  upon <a href="https://math.stackexchange.com/">math.stackexchange.com</a>
  and I noticed that it seemed to have decent LaTeX support.  As I
  dove deeper into the HTML source code of the pages of this website,
  I was surprised to see that the rendered LaTeX was not made of image
  files embedded into the web pages which used to be a prevalent
  practice in those days.  Instead, the mathematical formulas were
  rendered as text with sophisticated styling done with CSS to make
  the rendered mathematics formula look as good as a PDF rendered by
  an actual LaTeX system.  On further investigation I realised that
  this Stack Exchange website was
  using <a href="https://www.mathjax.org/">MathJax</a> to produce
  high-quality typography from LaTeX code.  As a frequent participant
  in the <code>#math</code> channels on various IRC networks, I
  immediately realised that using MathJax could lead to a modern
  mathematics pastebin with live preview and beautiful mathematics
  rendering right within the web browser without requiring a LaTeX
  system in the backend.
</p>
<p>
  Thanks to that chance encounter with MathJax, I spent the rest of
  the Saturday night coding a new mathematics pastebin using MathJax
  and PHP.  After coding all through the night, registering a new
  domain name and setting up a website, MathB.in was published early
  Sunday morning.  I shared the link to the website with some of my
  friends who were fond of sharing mathematics puzzles and solutions.
  I also
  <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/mathjax-users/c/_YAetB0gx2w/m/Xocb-aJOu4IJ">announced</a>
  its availability on the MathJax mailing list.  Since then word about
  my new website spread to various IRC communities and it soon became
  quite popular in mathematically-oriented channels.
</p>
<h2 id="source-code">Source Code<a href="#source-code"></a></h2>
<p>
  The source code of MathB.in was originally written in PHP.  I
  gradually began releasing its source code part by part in November
  2013.  The first complete open source release of MathB.in was done
  in December 2013.
</p>
<p>
  The early source code of MathB.in was quite complicated and
  over-engineered.  I was young and naive.  Much like how toddlers and
  young kids like to play with miniature forms of real world objects
  like cars, trains, trucks and kitchen sets, in my naivety, I had
  ended up creating a miniature form of the multiple levels of
  abstractions and complexity we see in the corporate world of
  software engineering.
</p>
<p>
  The thought of rewriting the software and simplifying it crossed my
  mind many times.  Incidentally, several years before writing
  MathB.in, I had stumbled upon the Lisp family of languages.  It was
  during a long layover at an airport in September 2007 that I decided
  to boot my laptop running Debian GNU/Linux 4.0 (Etch) and learn some
  Lisp programming.  I happened to have GNU CLISP 2.41 installed on
  it, so I fired it up and began learning Common Lisp.  A few months
  later I also dabbled in Scheme.  I found the sheer simplicity,
  beauty and elegance of Lisp and Scheme to be fascinating.  But the
  thought of writing websites using Common Lisp did not occur to me
  until much later.
</p>
<p>
  At some point much later, I began rewriting MathB.in in Common Lisp
  while preserving its user interface and most of its behaviour.
  MathB.in no longer runs on PHP.  It has been rewritten in Common
  Lisp and the entire application code is now a single Lisp source
  code file.
</p>
<h2 id="mathbin-today">MathB.in Today<a href="#mathbin-today"></a></h2>
<p>
  While the user interface and behaviour of MathB.in has remained
  largely the same as it was on its first day of release back in 2012,
  there have been some new additions to its feature set.  Support for
  GitHub Flavoured Markdown (GFM) has been added by popular demand.
  It now uses the <a href="https://github.com/susam/texme">TeXMe</a>
  renderer to more robustly parse a mix of Markdown and LaTeX.  A dark
  colour scheme has been added which is displayed on web browsers that
  are running on a desktop with dark colour scheme enabled.  The
  layout of the user interface elements are now responsive and adapt
  to small screen devices.
</p>
<p>
  Today MathB.in is used in various IRC channels for exchanging
  mathematics problems and solutions.  From the testimonials I have
  received so far, I know that it is also used by many teachers in
  schools and colleges to hand out problems, sample solutions and
  notes to their students.  Occasionally I receive emails and messages
  from kind strangers on the Internet who tell me how useful MathB.in
  has been for them.  Running this project for a decade and knowing
  that it has been useful to many people has brought me joy.
</p>
<p>
  <strong>Update on 16 Mar 2025:</strong> After about 13 years of
  continuous service, MathB.in has been shut down today.  See the
  post <a href="mathbin-is-shutting-down.html">MathB.in Is Shutting
  Down</a> for more details about this.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/mathbin-turns-ten.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Comfort of Bloated Web</title>
<link>https://susam.net/comfort-of-bloated-web.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">bngdw</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 12 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  There is a tiny <a href="form/comment/?post=hello">comment form</a>
  application on this website to accept comments from visitors and
  save them on the file system of the web server for me to review
  later and publish.  This form is the only thing on this website that
  is dynamic in nature.  Everything else on this website is static in
  nature.
</p>
<h2 id="mysterious-copies">Mysterious Copies<a href="#mysterious-copies"></a></h2>
<p>
  Most of this website is made of handcrafted HTML.  The blog posts
  and other content files are handcrafted HTML pages.  A Common Lisp
  program adds common headers and footers to these pages and generates
  the HTML pages that are served as static files via Nginx running on
  a Debian system.  The comment form, however, is a dynamic web
  application served via another Common Lisp program that makes use of
  the Hunchentoot web server to serve the form, accept the input
  submitted by the user and then process it.  This comment form is a
  very simple, minimal and stateless application that fulfills the
  modest requirements of this modest website pretty well.
</p>
<p>
  However, often I see multiple copies of the same comment being saved
  on my web server.  In the initial days of encountering this issue, I
  felt quite confused.  I could rule out a bug in my program by
  carefully reviewing and testing it.  Further, the web server logs
  clearly showed multiple POST requests being received by it from the
  same client usually with a few seconds of intervals between the
  consecutive requests.  The comments seemed to have legitimate
  content.  Since the duplicate copies would all have the same
  comment, I would arbitrarily pick one and publish it on my website.
  But I often wondered why on earth well meaning visitors would
  sometimes submit the same comment multiple times.  For good measure?
  Perhaps!  But still quite odd!
</p>
<h2 id="so-what-is-the-problem">So What's the Problem?<a href="#so-what-is-the-problem"></a></h2>
<p>
  The mystery of duplicate comment submission remained a puzzle for
  several months.  Then one day, one of the visitors to my website
  contacted me via Twitter messages to tell me that my comment form
  was broken and it was not working for them.
</p>
<p>
  The conversation began like this: "Hey!  The comment form on your
  website seems to be broken.  It says it has accepted my comment but
  I don't think it is doing that."
</p>
<p>
  I responded, "Hi!  Thank you for contacting me about this issue.
  What do you mean it does not accept your comment?  Do you see an
  error?"
</p>
<p>
  "There is no error.  In fact, after submitting, I get a success
  message that says, 'Comment was submitted successfully.  It may be
  published after review.'"
</p>
<p>
  "That sounds about right.  So what's the problem?"
</p>
<p>
  In the meantime, I performed some testing at my end to find that the
  comment form appeared to be working fine with no apparent issues.
  Further, I found that there were multiple copies of their comment
  saved neatly on the server for me to review later and publish.
</p>
<p>
  Before I could share my findings, they continued, "Well!  That
  success message appears almost instantly.  It couldn't be storing my
  comment successfully that fast, could it?"
</p>
<p>
  That is when the mystery unfolded for me!  The issue was that the
  comment form accepts the user's comment and returns a success
  message too soon for the user to believe that it could have possibly
  saved the comment.  I have had a couple of other very similar
  conversations since then when a visitor contacted me via email or
  another means to double-check if my comment form was really working
  fine.  In all of these cases, they were skeptical about the success
  message because it appeared much sooner than they expected.
</p>
<h2 id="bloated-expectations">Bloated Expectations<a href="#bloated-expectations"></a></h2>
<p>
  Depending on where the visitor is located, the comment form on this
  website may take anywhere between 30 ms to 900 ms (and very rarely a
  little longer) to accept the user's comment, save it successfully
  and then display a success message to the user.  But apparently, a
  few hundred millseconds is too fast for many people to be able to
  trust that the comment application is actually doing its job.  I
  presume that they have become so used to waiting for at least a
  second or more for dynamic pages to load that a web application that
  finishes its job in a few milliseconds appears to be fishy.
</p>
<p>
  I must clarify here that the duplicate comment submissions do not
  bother me at all.  The duplicate comments I receive is a very small
  fraction of the total number of comments.  I just find it
  interesting that users can mistrust a simple piece of software that
  does a simple thing in a reasonable amount of time.  I had one
  visitor to my website even say, "I really was expecting a spinning
  wheel on the browser tab or some sort of progress indicator to be
  assured that it is saving my comment.  The instant success message
  took me by surprise!"  They felt nervous that their comment was not
  saved and resubmitted the comment again.
</p>
<p>
  As a result of these conversations, I have sometimes even wondered
  whether I should add some artificial delay in the comment
  application before responding with a success message to satisfy the
  expectations of people who are so used to the bloated web.  Of
  course, I am not actually going to do that.  I want to keep it
  simple.  I do not like adding artificial restrictions to a simple
  piece of functionality.  Further, I do not mind the duplicate
  comment submissions at all.  However, I cannot help but remark that
  the users of the web today have become so comfortable with the
  bloated web that a simple web application without bells and whistles
  that is fast and responsive makes them nervous!
</p>
<h2 id="update">Update<a href="#update"></a></h2>
<p>
  <strong>Update on 13 Mar 2022:</strong> Many commenters to this post
  have suggested that the issue here might not be the fast response of
  a successful comment application but instead the fact that the
  comment form elements remain intact even after the comment
  submission.  In their opinion, merely displaying a success message
  may not be assuring enough.  They further suggested that I should
  change the state of the form in some way on successful submission.
  Popular recommendations included disabling, clearing or removing the
  form elements entirely on successful submission.
</p>
<p>
  These suggestions are valid of course.  However, I also think that
  these suggestions reinforce the point of my blog post.  Without
  these fancy features and restrictions, web surfers today feel unsure
  if the comment form application has really done what it
  is <em>literally</em> saying it has done.
</p>
<p>
  Do I really need to consider <em>artificially</em> clearing,
  disabling or removing the form elements and thus removing the
  ability to edit a comment again and resubmit it (even if the user
  really so desires) with a single click of a button?  What if someone
  wants to post another comment immediately after the first one?  What
  if someone wants to edit their previous comment slightly and repost
  it?  Do I need to force the user to hop through separate links and
  buttons to be able to do these simple tasks?  "But every other
  website clears, disables or removes the form elements," you might
  rightfully offer as a counterpoint.  I know.  I know.  But why is it
  so that the "right" user experience nowadays involves artifically
  encumbering the user or hiding the user's own submitted text from
  themselves?
</p>
<p>
  In fact, in an earlier version of this website, the comment form
  application did disable the form elements on a successful comment
  submission.  In an even older version of this website, a new page
  consisting only a success message appeared.  However, visitors would
  still report their suspicion regarding the comment form doing its
  job to me.  So I have observed the results of employing at least two
  of the measures suggested and they were still consistent with the
  reporters' claims that they find the instant success message from
  the application to be disconcerting.
</p>
<p>
  UX best practices notwithstanding, I do not want to hide the users'
  content from themselves after a successful form submission.  Maybe
  they want to copy the message and keep it for themselves.  Maybe
  they want to edit it again and repost it.  I do not want to restrict
  any of these simple activities.  I also do not want the user to hop
  through an additional link or button to be able to do these things.
  However, heeding some of the other advice I have received in the
  comments section, I have now made two tiny changes to the comment
  form application that is consistent with its original spirit of
  simplicity, minimalism and statelessness.  I have moved the success
  message to the top of the response page.  I have also added
  additional text in the success message that explains that the
  submitted input has been left intact in case the submitter wants to
  copy it or edit it and resubmit it.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/comfort-of-bloated-web.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Andromeda Invaders</title>
<link>https://susam.net/andromeda-invaders.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">lygkw</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  The arcade-style computer games of 1980s played a big role in
  getting me fascinated about computers.  Last weekend I decided to
  fulfill a childhood dream of writing my own invaders-like game.
  After a few hours of programming, I ended up with a simple game that
  I call <em>Andromeda Invaders</em>.  You can play it now by clicking
  the link below:
</p>
<p style="text-align: center">
  <a href="invaders.html">Play Andromeda Invaders</a>
</p>
<p>
  It is a 1980s-arcade-style game that runs in a modern web browser.
  This game is inspired by Space Invaders, the 1978 arcade game
  developed by Tomohiro Nishikado.  However, the game characters,
  gameplay and some technical aspects of this game are very different
  from those of Space Invaders.
</p>
<h2 id="inspiration">Inspiration<a href="#inspiration"></a></h2>
<p>
  I first came across Space Invaders in the 1990s in the computer
  laboratory of my lower secondary school.  Soon after playing the
  game a few times, I wanted to develop a similar game of my own.
  However, the little GW-BASIC programming I knew then was
  insufficient to write anything more sophisticated than simple
  text-based input/output programs.  I did write several simple
  text-based quiz and adventure games back then but a more
  sophisticated game with graphics and audio remained elusive.  As
  years went by, I gradually forgot about it, learnt more mainstream
  languages like C, Python, Lisp, etc. and got into programming as a
  career.
</p>
<p>
  Although it is 25 years too late, I decided to spend a weekend now
  to fulfill my childhood desire to write my own Invaders-like game.
  This game fulfills a childhood dream of mine!
</p>
<h2 id="graphics-and-audio">Graphics and Audio<a href="#graphics-and-audio"></a></h2>
<p>
  All of the graphics is done by drawing rectangles and text on an
  HTML5 <code>&lt;canvas&gt;</code> element using the Canvas API.
</p>
<p>
  All of the audio is done by generating sine waves using
  <code>OscillatorNode</code> of the Web Audio API.  The sine waves
  used for the game audio correspond to actual musical notes from the
  C major scale.  Multiple notes are played together to form chords.
  The background music is a chord progression consisting of four
  chords repeating over and over again as long as the game is being
  played.  When the game characters get hit, the hit sounds are made of
  a single chord that plays for a very short duration.
</p>
<p>
  There is rudimentary support for playing this game on small screens
  and touchscreens using the buttons provided below the game canvas.
  However, this game is best enjoyed on a laptop/desktop device with a
  physical keyboard.  On a device with physical keyboard, the game can
  be played in fullscreen mode by typing <kbd>f</kbd>.  Since it is a
  single-file HTML game, it can be saved as a standalone file on your
  system.
</p>
<h2 id="levels">Levels<a href="#levels"></a></h2>
<p>
  The game can be played indefinitely long in theory.  However in
  practice, the difficulty level of the game rises steeply with each
  level and I would consider it remarkable if someone manages to reach
  level 10.  None of my friends and colleagues who played this game
  over the weekend has been able to reach level 9 yet.  However, many
  of them have reached level 8 within a few hours of practice.  The
  steep rise in difficulty level is intentional, so that a single
  session of this game does not last too long.
</p>
<p>
  Levels 1 to 20 present new difficulty levels in terms of the speed
  of the objects moving on the canvas.  The difficultly levels remain
  constant between levels 21 and 1000.  If someone were to complete
  level 1000, the game would reset to level 1 with the score intact.
  This is how one could potentially play the game indefinitely long.
</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion"></a></h2>
<p>
  Like I mentioned above, this game is the result of a weekend's work.
  I wanted to keep it as simple as possible.  Despite the simplicity,
  there are a few interesting concepts such as loss and recovery of
  health of the game characters, automatic release of laser pulses,
  etc.
</p>
<p>
  There is a Git repository for this game at
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/invaders">github.com/susam/invaders</a>.
  The README file in this repository documents several technical
  details of this game.  The source code is released under the MIT
  licence, so please feel free to play with the code, modify the game
  parameters and logic and alter the game.  If you like this game, do
  <a href="invaders.html">share it</a> with others.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/andromeda-invaders.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Andromeda Invaders</title>
<link>https://susam.net/invaders.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">bffow</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 13 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A 1980s-arcade-style game written using HTML5, Canvas and Web Audio.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/invaders.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/game.html">#game</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/graphics.html">#graphics</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Against URL-Based Content Rendering</title>
<link>https://susam.net/against-url-based-content-rendering.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">kxrke</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Today I received a nice pull request to my project
  named <a href="https://github.com/susam/muboard">Muboard</a>.  It is
  a shame I am not going to merge this pull request.  Muboard is a
  simple web-based tool that can be used as a virtual chalkboard.  You
  can type in text with LaTeX snippets in it and Muboard renders your
  input as you type it.  Muboard is quite useful to me when I host
  online mathematics book club meetings.  Muboard can also be used to
  create distributable self-rendering HTML documents.  See the
  preceding link to see demo link, screenshots, usage notes, etc.
</p>
<p>
  The <a href="https://github.com/susam/muboard/pull/4">pull
  request</a> I received adds the ability to create a shareable link
  to a Muboard instance.  I am hosting mine
  at <a href="https://muboard.net">muboard.net</a>.  The shareable
  link encodes the entire content in the URL itself.  When someone
  visits the shareable link, it loads Muboard which then looks at the
  encoded content in the URL and renders the content.  It is a nifty
  idea.  An idea, I have thought of myself while developing Muboard
  but then decided not to implement.  If there is anything that
  running <a href="https://github.com/susam/mathb">MathB.in</a> for
  ten years has taught me, it is that allowing arbitrary users to
  render content that appears on a domain name I have registered is
  going to end up as a huge time sink for me.  I would be spending a
  significant portion of my leisure time moderating content, keeping
  regulatory authorities happy and ensuring that no bad content
  appears on my website.  Here is a copy of my complete response on
  this matter from the pull request:
</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>
    Thank you for the comment and the pull request.  The ability to
    share URLs with the content encoded in the URL query parameter or
    fragment identifier has crossed my mind earlier.  It is a very
    useful feature indeed.  However, I decided against implementing
    such a feature because such features are often abused to display
    spam content or illegitimate content.
  </p>
  <p>
    Now one might wonder why I, as someone who is merely hosting the
    Muboard tool on a website, should care about what kind of content
    one chooses to display on Muboard.  After all, the content is
    rendered on the client side, so I am not responsible for the
    content.  Unfortunately, the regulatory authorities do not see it
    that way.
  </p>
  <p>
    From my experience of running MathB.in (another project that
    offers a pastebin for mathematics) for the last 10 years, I have
    learnt that as long as such bad content is displayed on a domain
    name I am the registrant of, the regulatory authorities are going
    to contact me and ask me to ensure that such content is not
    displayed on my website.  They do not care whether that content is
    rendered on the server side or client side.  Further, they usually
    provide only a week's notice.  If no measures are taken to prevent
    such content from being rendered on the website, the regulatory
    authorities go ahead and force the cloud provider, hosting
    provider, etc. to take down the website completely.
  </p>
  <p>
    With something like MathB.in which stores the content on the
    server side, I can at least remove the content from its data
    store.  However, if the content is rendered entirely on the client
    side on the basis of the encoded content in the URL query
    parameter or fragment identifier, it becomes more difficult to
    know what content is being displayed on the website and block bad
    content from being rendered, say, with some JavaScript code that
    looks for patterns in the content and refuse to render the content
    if it appears to contain bad content.  This is not a problem I
    want to solve in Muboard because my prior experience with MathB.in
    shows that it takes considerable time and effort to keep track of
    all possible bad content and to fine tune the patterns to match,
    on a regular basis.
  </p>
  <p>
    Your pull request has a very useful feature and it's a shame I
    cannot add it to the copy of Muboard.net I am running.  I do not
    have the time to get involved in maintaining pattern-based content
    blocklisting.  If you are really interested in this feature and
    have the risk appetite to allow arbitrary content from users to be
    rendered on your website, I would recommend hosting a clone of
    Muboard.net with this feature on a separate URL that you own.  I
    would be happy to link to your clone from the README of this
    project.
  </p>
</blockquote>
<p>
  Encoding content in the URL and then rendering that content is fine
  as long as the content is composed from an allowed set of tokens.
  Examples include virtual pianos, online synthesisers and fun games
  like <a href="https://tixy.land/">Tixy</a>.  However, for something
  like Muboard that shows arbitrary text content from users, quite
  unfortunately, I have to decline any pull request that renders
  arbitrary content encoded in the URLs!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/against-url-based-content-rendering.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Web Golden</title>
<link>https://susam.net/web-golden.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">cavac</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  In a recent online discussion about simple static websites, Chris
  Chapman <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=30139081">posted</a>
  this quite clever comment:
</p>
<blockquote>
  Firm supporter of Web Pi (3.14159).  When it comes to building for
  the web today, I'm always amazed that "so much can be done with so
  little" and yet the default is the opposite - "so much is needed to
  deliver so little" - so irrational!  Where did we go wrong?  I
  wonder what Web Euler (2.71828) would have looked like?
</blockquote>
<p>
  I enjoyed the amusing play on the terms "Web 2.0" and "Web 3.0" as
  well as the irony-infused pun involving the word "irrational".  I
  piled on to the witty wordplay with my own comment where I remarked
  how my favourite phase of the web was Web Golden
  (<a href="phi.txt">1.61803</a>).  I will elaborate here what that
  phase of the web looked like and why I was fond of it.
</p>
<h2 id="fascinating-realisation">Fascinating Realisation<a href="#fascinating-realisation"></a></h2>
<p>
  I believe I was fortunate enough to grow up during a time when the
  web was a very diverse place full of various eccentric digital
  gardens.  I was introduced to the world wide web around 1999.
  Access to the Internet was very limited where I lived.  My friends
  and I would visit so-called Internet caf&eacute;s and shell out a
  significant chunk of our pocket money for just an hour of Internet
  usage.
</p>
<p>
  I was already quite familiar with computers then but the Internet
  and the world wide web were completely new to me.  Until then,
  thanks to my <a href="fd-100.html">prior exposure</a> to the
  Logo programming language, I had only considered computers to be a
  device for problem solving and recreation.  However, the Internet
  showed me that computers were very flexible and malleable
  communication devices too.  It was a fascinating realisation!
</p>
<p>
  While on the Internet, I used to spend most of my time browsing
  websites and joining various chat forums where I could talk to other
  programmers from all over the world.  I learnt a lot about the world
  and its various cultures by talking to them.  I met people who wrote
  their own full blown chat clients, people who were nearing
  retirement after having programmed about twenty different
  microcontrollers throughout their careers, people who developed
  software for global positioning systems and so on.  These
  experiences broadened my horizons.  I could see that my enthusiasm
  for computers could one day lead to a fulfilling career.
</p>
<h2 id="simplicity">Simplicity<a href="#simplicity"></a></h2>
<p>
  The world wide web was a delightful place.  There were no major
  social media websites yet.  I believe the closest thing to social
  media we had back then
  was <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/19990125095557/http://www.geocities.com/">Geocities.com</a>
  where we could create our own websites for free.  One could also
  host their websites on shared website hosting providers for a fixed
  annual fee.  Some also hosted their websites on servers running in
  their own houses.
</p>
<p>
  Most websites were made up of static HTML pages.  Some websites had
  tiny guestbooks that allowed a little user-generated content.  I
  remember some of the website hosting providers made it really easy
  to add guestbooks, even for someone with no programming experience.
  All one needed to do was create an HTML page that contained
  a <code>&lt;form&gt;</code> element with the <code>action</code>
  attribute set to a URL of a CGI script provided by the hosting
  provider.  The CGI script would accept every comment submitted via
  the guestbook and automatically insert the new comment into a static
  HTML page.  The good scripts would escape the special characters in
  the comments properly before saving it in the static comments page.
  But the poor ones would let any script kiddie deface the guestbook
  page by inserting cleverly crafted HTML snippets or JavaScript code
  within the comments.  That would be the first lesson on cross-site
  scripting for many of us in those days.
</p>
<p>
  While most personal websites were static in nature, the motivated
  web developers would teach themselves enough programming to add
  little pieces of dynamic functionality by writing CGI scripts.  Many
  used PHP instead which was much easier to write code in and deploy.
  I taught myself ASP to develop dynamic pages.  It allowed me to
  write my own guestbook page and a dynamic quiz application for the
  visitors of my website.
</p>
<p>
  Despite various types of dynamic functionality offered by the
  websites, the web was simple.  Web pages with infinite scrolling was
  unheard of.  Visiting useful websites did not result in the web
  browser loading dozens of massive JavaScript files in the
  background.  Web developers were used to doing less with less.  But
  the old web had its own problems too.  Just like how the current web
  is riddled with banner advertisements, the old web too was riddled
  with pop-ups!  A prevalent user-hostile trend back then involved web
  pages creating new pop-ups for advertisements.  They would often
  clutter the desktop because the major web browsers back then would
  create a new desktop-level window for each popup.
</p>
<h2 id="nostalgia">Nostalgia<a href="#nostalgia"></a></h2>
<p>
  Although these old, simple and crude websites can still be found in
  certain corners of the web, the mainstream web no longer looks like
  this.  Websites are generally heavier and more complex these days.
  Talking about the old web today only serves as nostalgia for people
  like me who grew up during that magical time.  One might argue that
  the world wide web today is much more advanced and has much more
  utility than the old web I am reminiscing about here.  That is true.
  The web today is a very versatile tool of great utility.  The web
  today is a powerful agent that is shaping our civilisation and
  influencing how societies evolve and function.  Indeed, the web was
  quite limited in terms of utility back then.  Online banking was not
  prevalent.  Electronic commerce was very new and clunky.  The most
  practical utility of the old web I can recall involved publishing
  and retrieving university exam results and even that was painfully
  slow.  It would take a minute or two for university pages to load
  over dial-up connections.
</p>
<p>
  However, what the web of the 90s lacked in terms of utility, it more
  than compensated by being a fertile ground for creativity.  Thanks
  to the early web, many computer enthusiasts, including me, learnt to
  build their first few websites by writing one line of HTML at a
  time.  To write a few lines of HTML code in a text editor and then
  watch the web browser render that code as a glorious web page full
  of colours, images and text was a magical feeling.  I do think that
  was the golden era of the web.  It was quirky and yet beautiful.  It
  was limited and yet diverse.  It was the sweet spot between Web 1.0
  and Web 2.0.  It was Web 1.61803!  It was Web Golden!
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/web-golden.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/humour.html">#humour</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/retrospective.html">#retrospective</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Blank Page</title>
<link>https://susam.net/blank.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">egmnd</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  A blank page.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/blank.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Minimal HTML Page</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/web/minimal.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">zkxsb</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  An example page that demonstrates the minimal page that can be
  written in HTML while passing W3 Validator checks.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/web/minimal.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>MathB 0.2.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/mathb/0.2.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">flsrk</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 28 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  MathB 0.2.0 is a minor update of MathB, a web-based mathematics
  pastebin service.  The key change in this release is the removal of
  image support.  Image tags are now disallowed in new posts and older
  posts containing images will no longer be rendered.  This update
  aims to mitigate spam on the live instances of this software.
</p>
<p>
  To read more about this project, please see
  <a href="http://github.com/susam/mathb">github.com/susam/mathb</a>.
</p>
<p>
  See the file
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mathb/blob/main/CHANGES.md">CHANGES.md</a>
  for a detailed changelog.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/mathb/0.2.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>Sticking With MathJax</title>
<link>https://susam.net/sticking-with-mathjax.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">bazuh</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  I have considered switching from MathJax to KaTeX for my
  MathJax-based projects such
  as <a href="https://github.com/susam/texme">TeXMe</a>
  and <a href="https://github.com/susam/mathb">MathB</a> but I had to
  decide against doing so because MathJax supports commands
  like <code>\label</code>, <code>\eqref</code>, <code>\notag</code>,
  etc. and environments like <code>align</code>,
  <code>multiline</code>, etc.  KaTeX does not support them, so
  switching to KaTeX would break many existing documents written using
  TeXMe or MathBin.  I am going to stick with MathJax for now.
</p>
<p>
  Here are some useful resources:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <a href="http://docs.mathjax.org/en/latest/input/tex/macros/">MathJax: Supported TeX/LaTeX commands</a>
  </li>
  <li>
    <a href="https://katex.org/docs/supported.html">KaTeX: Supported Functions</a>
  </li>
</ul>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/sticking-with-mathjax.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>QuickQWERTY</title>
<link>https://susam.net/quickqwerty.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">zlnzx</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Touch typing tutor that runs in your web browser.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/quickqwerty.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>QuickQWERTY 1.0.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/1.0.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">qqozz</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Version 1.0.0 of QuickQWERTY is now available.  This is the first
  release of this touch typing tutor on GitHub.  With this release,
  source code and release management has been moved from SVN and
  SourceForge to Git and GitHub.  You can now run QuickQWERTY
  here: <a href="../../../quickqwerty.html">quickqwerty.html</a>.
</p>
<p>
  Apart from changes in source code and release management, this
  release introduces input commands like <code>restart</code>
  and <code>rst</code> to quickly restart the current lesson.
  Further, in this release, the licence was changed from the GNU
  General Public Licence, version 3 to the Simplified BSD Licence
  (BSD-2-Clause).
</p>
<p>
  With these updates, QuickQWERTY reaches its first major release.
  The source code of QuickQWERTY is now available on GitHub
  at <a href="https://github.com/susam/quickqwerty">github.com/susam/quickqwerty</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/1.0.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>MathB 0.1.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/mathb/0.1.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">pskny</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  MathB is a web-based mathematics pastebin service.  It was developed
  on Sunday, 25 March 2022, as a weekend project to share mathematical
  notes with friends.  After more than one and a half years of
  development and tweaks, this is the first stable release of the
  software.  To read more about this project, please
  see <a href="http://github.com/susam/mathb">github.com/susam/mathb</a>.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/mathb/0.1.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/technology.html">#technology</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/release.html">#release</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>QuickQWERTY 0.4.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/0.4.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">qqzfz</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 23 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Version 0.4.0 of QuickQWERTY is now available.  This release marks
  the final version hosted on SourceForge.
</p>
<p>
  Several issues have been addressed in this update.  Lessons now
  avoid using characters that have not yet been introduced and a
  problem that caused the lessons bar to shrink in Google Chrome has
  been fixed.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/0.4.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>QuickQWERTY 0.3.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/0.3.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">qqzth</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 09 May 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Version 0.3.0 of QuickQWERTY is now available.  This release adds
  support for both 5-6 split and 6-7 split typing styles.  With this
  addition, learners can choose where the number keys split between
  the two hands that best matches their preference or training
  requirements.
</p>

<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/0.3.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>QuickQWERTY 0.2.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/0.2.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">qqztz</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Version 0.2.0 of QuickQWERTY is now available.  The number row has
  been adjusted so that keys <code>1</code> to
  <code>5</code> are now typed with the left hand and keys
  <code>6</code> to <code>0</code> with the right hand.  In addition,
  the minimum speed requirement for moving to the next lesson has been
  removed, giving learners greater flexibility in their practice.
</p>
<p>
  These changes make QuickQWERTY more consistent with standard typing
  conventions and more adaptable to different learning speeds.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/0.2.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>QuickQWERTY 0.1.0</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/0.1.0.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">qqzoz</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Version 0.1.0 of QuickQWERTY, a touch typing tutor that runs in the
  web browser, is now available.  This is the first release with the
  complete set of 21 units with a total of 101 lessons.
</p>
<p>
  The lesson progression has also been improved.  A new lesson is now
  suggested only when the current one is completed at a speed of at
  least 50 characters per minute.
</p>
<p>
  This release is available under the terms of the GNU General Public
  Licence, version 3.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/0.1.0.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>QuickQWERTY 0.0.6</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/0.0.6.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">qqzzs</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  Version 0.0.6 of QuickQWERTY, a touch typing tutor that runs in the
  web browser, is now available.  This update focuses on improving
  compatibility with Internet Explorer.
</p>
<p>
  In this release, trailing commas were removed from
  <code>db.js</code>, as they caused errors in Internet Explorer 6 and
  7.  An issue was also fixed that led to an extra unit appearing in
  the unit list when the tutor was used in Internet Explorer.
</p>
<p>
  With these fixes, QuickQWERTY should now run more smoothly across
  different browsers.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/0.0.6.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>
<item>
<title>QuickQWERTY 0.0.5</title>
<link>https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/0.0.5.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="false">qqzzf</guid>
<pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2008 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
<description>
<![CDATA[
<p>
  An initial draft of QuickQWERTY, a touch typing tutor that runs in
  the web browser, is now available on SourceForge at
  <a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/quickqwerty/">sourceforge.net/projects/quickqwerty/</a>.
  This release includes 15 units with a total of 73 typing lessons
  designed for QWERTY keyboards.
</p>
<p>
  This draft is version 0.5.0 of the tutor.  As the version number
  suggests, it is the fifth revision of the software.  The first four
  were internal releases shared only with friends, who tested the
  software for several months.  Their feedback helped uncover and fix
  a number of issues.  Version 0.5.0 marks the first public release of
  QuickQWERTY.
</p>
<p>
  Over the coming months, I plan to expand the software with
  additional typing lessons.
</p>
<!-- ### -->
<p>
  <a href="https://susam.net/code/news/quickqwerty/0.0.5.html">Read on website</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/web.html">#web</a> |
  <a href="https://susam.net/tag/programming.html">#programming</a>
</p>
]]>
</description>
</item>


</channel>
</rss>
